<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<tmx version="1.4">
<header creationtool="ABBYY Aligner" creationtoolversion="1.0" segtype="sentence" o-tmf="ATM" adminlang="en-US" srclang="en-US" datatype="plaintext">
</header>
<body>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在第十一届全国人民代表大会第三次会议上的政府工作报告</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>REPORT ON THE WORK OF THE GOVERNMENT--Delivered at the Third Session of the Eleventh National People's Congress</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院总理 温家宝</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Wen Jiabao, Premier of the State Council</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>2010年3月5日</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>on March 5, 2010</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现在，我代表国务院向大会作政府工作报告，请予审议，并请全国政协各位委员提出意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I now present to you my report on the work of the government for your deliberation and approval. I also invite the members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC) to provide comments and suggestions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一、2009年工作回顾</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I. Review of Work in 2009</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>2009年是新世纪以来我国经济发展最为困难的一年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The year 2009 was the most difficult year for our country's economic development since the beginning of the new century. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年这个时候，国际金融危机还在扩散蔓延，世界经济深度衰退，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This time last year the global financial crisis was still spreading, and the world economy was in a deep recession.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国经济受到严重冲击，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our economy was severely affected;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>出口大幅下降，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>our exports decreased significantly;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>不少企业经营困难，有的甚至停产倒闭，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a large number of enterprises had operating difficulties, and some even suspended production or closed down;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>失业人员大量增加，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the number of unemployed people increased significantly;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农民工大批返乡，经济增速陡然下滑。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>many migrant workers had to return to their home villages; and the pace of our economic growth suddenly slowed down. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在异常困难的情况下，全国各族人民在中国共产党的坚强领导下，坚定信心，迎难而上，顽强拼搏，从容应对国际金融危机冲击，在世界率先实现经济回升向好，改革开放和社会主义现代化建设取得新的重大成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In these unusually difficult circumstances, the people of all our ethnic groups fortified their confidence, tackled difficulties head on, worked tenaciously, and responded calmly to the impact of the global financial crisis under the firm leadership of the Communist Party of China (CPC). Our economy was the first in the world to have made a turnaround, and we made major new achievements in reform and opening up as well as socialist modernization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值达到33.5万亿元，比上年增长8.7%；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>GDP reached 33.5 trillion yuan, an increase of 8.7% over the previous year (here and below). </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政收入6.85万亿元，增长11.7%；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal revenue was 6.85 trillion yuan, up 11.7%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食产量5.31亿吨，再创历史新高，实现连续6年增产；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Grain production was 531 million tons, a new record and an increase for the sixth consecutive year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业1102万人；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 11.02 million urban jobs were created.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇居民人均可支配收入17175元，农村居民人均纯收入5153元，实际增长9.8%和8.5%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The per capita disposable income of urban residents was 17,175 yuan, and the net per capita income of rural residents was 5,153 yuan, up 9.8% and 8.5% respectively in real terms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国在全面建设小康社会道路上又迈出坚实的一步。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took another steady step along the path of building a moderately prosperous society in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实践再次证明，任何艰难险阻都挡不住中华民族伟大复兴的历史进程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Events again proved that no difficulties or obstacles can impede the course of the great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去的一年，极不平凡，令人振奋。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The past year was truly extraordinary and inspiring. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们隆重庆祝新中国成立60周年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We held a grand celebration of the 60th anniversary of the founding of New China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抚今追昔，伟大祖国的辉煌成就极大地激发了全国人民的自信心和自豪感，极大地增强了中华民族的向心力和凝聚力，极大地提升了我国的国际地位和影响力，必将激励我们在中国特色社会主义道路上继续奋勇前进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The outstanding achievements we made in that time have greatly boosted the confidence and pride of the people, strengthened the cohesiveness of the Chinese nation, and raised China's international standing and influence. All this definitely encourages us to continue to forge ahead on the path of socialism with Chinese characteristics.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们主要做了以下工作：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the last year, we mainly undertook the following work.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（一）加强和改善宏观调控，促进经济平稳较快发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. Strengthening and improving macro-control and promoting steady and rapid economic development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们实行积极的财政政策和适度宽松的货币政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We carried out a proactive fiscal policy and a moderately easy monetary policy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实施并不断完善应对国际金融危机的一揽子计划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We comprehensively implemented and constantly improved the package plan for addressing the global financial crisis. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大规模增加财政支出和实行结构性减税，保持货币信贷快速增长，提高货币政策的可持续性，扩大直接融资规模，满足经济社会发展的资金需求，有效扩大了内需，很快扭转了经济增速下滑趋势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We significantly increased government spending, implemented structural tax reductions, rapidly increased supplies of money and credit, made our monetary policy more sustainable, and increased the amount of direct financing. We thus ensured funding for economic and social development, effectively boosted domestic demand, and quickly reversed the slowdown in economic growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力扩大居民消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We vigorously expanded consumer spending.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们鼓励消费的政策领域之宽、力度之大、受惠面之广前所未有。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our policies to encourage consumption covered more areas, were stronger and benefited more people than ever before. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政投入资金450亿元，补贴家电汽车摩托车下乡、汽车家电以旧换新和农机具购置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government provided 45 billion yuan in subsidies for rural residents to purchase home appliances and motor vehicles, including motorbikes. Part of the subsidies also supported trading-in old motor vehicles and home appliances for new ones and purchasing agricultural machinery and tools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>减半征收小排量汽车购置税，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We halved the purchase tax on small-displacement automobiles.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>减免住房交易相关税收，支持自住性住房消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We reduced or exempted taxes on buying and selling homes to support the purchase of homes to be used as their owners' residences. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年汽车销售1364万辆，增长46.2%；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Throughout the year 13.64 million motor vehicles were sold, an increase of 46.2%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>商品房销售9.37亿平方米，增长42.1%；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>commodity housing sales amounted to 937 million square meters, up 42.1%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>社会消费品零售总额实际增长16.9%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and total retail sales of consumer goods increased 16.9% in real terms:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>消费对经济增长的拉动作用明显增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumption played a much bigger role in fueling economic growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进投资快速增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We promoted rapid growth in investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们发挥政府投资“四两拨千斤”的作用，引导带动社会投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We guided and stimulated non-government investment by means of well-leveraged government investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施两年新增4万亿元的投资计划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented a plan to invest an additional 4 trillion yuan over two years. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>2009年中央政府公共投资9243亿元，比上年预算增加5038亿元，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In 2009, the central government's public investment was 924.3 billion yuan, 503.8 billion yuan more than in the previous year's budget.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>其中，保障性住房、农村民生工程、社会事业投资占44%，自主创新、结构调整、节能减排和生态建设占16%，重大基础设施建设占23%，灾后恢复重建占14%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Of this, 44% was invested in. low-income housing, projects to improve the wellbeing of rural residents, and social programs; 16% in independent innovation, restructuring, energy conservation, emissions reductions, and ecological improvement; 23% in major infrastructure projects; and 14% in post-Wenchuan earthquake recovery and reconstruction. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全社会固定资产投资增长30.1%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fixed asset investment increased 30.1% nationwide.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>投资结构进一步优化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We further improved the investment structure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>投资快速增长有效弥补了外需下降的缺口，加强了薄弱环节，为经济社会长远发展奠定了坚实的基础。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Rapid investment growth effectively compensated for the shortfall created by shrinking external demand, strengthened weak links, and laid a solid foundation for long-term economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们加快推进汶川地震灾后恢复重建，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We accelerated the post-Wenchuan earthquake recovery and reconstruction work.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重灾区已完成投资6545亿元，占规划总投资的65.5%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We have already invested 654.5 billion yuan, 65.5% of the total planned investment, in the worst hit areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家的大力支持，全国人民的无私援助，灾区群众的艰苦奋斗，使遭受重大创伤的灾区呈现出崭新面貌。一座座新城拔地而起，一个个村庄焕发出蓬勃生机。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Thanks to the government's strong support, the selfless assistance of people throughout the country, and the hard work of residents of the earthquake area, the badly damaged areas have taken on a brand-new appearance, with new towns rising straight out of the ground, and villages brimming with vitality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这充分体现了中华民族的无疆大爱，有力彰显了社会主义制度的无比优越。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All this fully reflects the boundless love of the Chinese nation and powerfully demonstrates the incomparable superiority of the socialist system.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（二）大力调整经济结构，夯实长远发展基础。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2. Vigorously carrying out economic restructuring, and shoring up the foundation for long-term development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们把保增长与调结构紧密结合起来，加快解决制约经济发展的结构性矛盾。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We closely integrated sustaining economic growth with economic restructuring, and moved more quickly to resolve structural problems limiting economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“三农”工作进一步加强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We further strengthened the work related to agriculture, rural areas, and farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政用于“三农”的支出7253亿元，增长21.8%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government used 725.3 billion yuan to support agriculture, rural areas, and farmers, an increase of 21.8%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大幅度提高粮食最低收购价。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We raised the minimum grain purchase prices by a large margin. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动实施全国新增千亿斤粮食生产能力建设规划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We began implementation of 'the plan to increase grain production capacity by 50 million tons nationwide. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续改善农村生产生活条件，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued to improve living and working conditions in rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农村饮水安全工程使6069万农民受益，新增510万沼气用户，新建和改造农村公路38万公里、农村电网线路26.6万公里，又有80万户农村危房得到改造，9.2万户游牧民实现了定居。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented rural drinking water safety projects that benefited 60.69 million people, increased the number of methane gas users by 5.1. million, built and upgraded 380,000 kilometers of roads and 266,000 kilometers of electric power lines and renovated 800,000 dilapidated houses in the countryside, and helped build permanent housing for 92,000 nomadic families. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们加大扶贫力度，贫困地区的生产生活条件得到明显改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We also intensified our efforts to fight poverty. As a result, working and living conditions notably improved in poverty-stricken areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>产业结构调整力度加大。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We intensified industrial restructuring. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定并实施十大重点产业调整振兴规划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We formulated and implemented a plan for restructuring and invigorating ten key industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励企业加快技术改造，安排200亿元技改专项资金支持4441个技改项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We encouraged enterprises to accelerate technological upgrading, and provided 20 billion yuan to support 4,441 technological upgrading projects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点行业兼并重组取得新进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Further progress was made in mergers and reorganization in key industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>下大力气抑制部分行业产能过剩和重复建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made great efforts to restrict excess production capacity and redundant development in some industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>关停小火电机组2617万千瓦，淘汰落后的炼钢产能1691万吨、炼铁产能2113万吨、水泥产能7416万吨、焦炭产能1809万吨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We closed down 26.17 million kilowatts of small thermal power stations, and eliminated backward facilities with total production tons in the steelmaking industry, 21.13 million tons in the iron-smelting 74.16 million tons in the cement industry, and 18.09 million tons in the coke industry. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快实施国家科技重大专项，中央财政用于科技的支出1512亿元，增长30%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We accelerated the implementation of major national science and technology projects, and spent 151.2 billion yuan of central government funds on science and technology, an increase of 30%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极支持自主创新产品推广应用，清洁能源、第三代移动通信等一批新兴产业快速发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We vigorously supported the widespread use of domestically innovated products, and the development of emerging industries such as clean energy and third-generation mobile communications. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力加强基础设施建设，新建铁路投入运营5557公里，高速公路新建通车4719公里，城市轨道交通建设加快，新建、改扩建民用机场35个；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We vigorously strengthened infrastructure development; put 5,557 kilometers of newly built railway lines into operation; opened 4,719 kilometers of new expressways to traffic, accelerated urban rail development; and built, renovated or expanded 35 civil airports.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新增发电装机8970万千瓦，西气东输二线西段工程实现供气，南水北调工程建设加快推进，6183座病险水库除险加固工程开工建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased the installed power-generating capacity by 89.7 million kilowatts, began supplying gas through the western section of the second line of the project for shipping natural gas from west to east, accelerated construction on the South-to-North Water Diversion Project, and began reinforcing 6,183 dangerous reservoirs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>节能减排和环境保护扎实推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made solid progress in conserving energy, reducing emissions and protecting the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>安排预算内资金，支持重点节能工程、循环经济等项目2983个；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We supported 2,983 key energy conservation and recycling projects through budgetary investment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施节能产品惠民工程，推广节能空调500多万台、高效照明灯具1.5亿只。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented a project to promote energy-efficient products for the benefit of the people, putting into use more than 5 million energy-saving air-conditioners and 150 million energy-efficient light bulbs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进林业重点生态工程建设，完成造林8827万亩，森林覆盖率达到20.36%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued to develop key ecological projects in the forestry industry, and completed the afforestation of 5.88 million hectares, thereby raising the percentage of land covered by forest to 20.36%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>综合治理水土流失面积4.8万平方公里。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Through combined measures, we brought soil erosion on 48,000 square kilometers of land under control. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强"三河三湖"等重点流域水污染防治和工业废水废气废渣治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened the prevention and treatment of water pollution in the key watersheds of the Huai, Hai, and Liao rivers and Tai, Chao, and Dianchi lakes, and improved the control of wastewater, gases and residues from industry. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“十一五”前四年累计单位国内生产总值能耗下降14.38%，化学需氧量、二氧化硫排放量分别下降9.66%和13.14%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the first four years of the Eleventh Five-Year Plan period, energy consumption per unit of GDP fell 14.38%, and chemical oxygen demand and sulfur dioxide emissions decreased 9.66% and 13.14% respectively. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极开展应对气候变化工作，明确提出2020年我国控制温室气体排放行动目标和政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made vigorous efforts to respond to climate change, and set forth our country's targets, policies and measures for controlling greenhouse gas emissions by 2020. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>气象预报预警和地震监测工作得到加强，灾害防御能力不断提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved our weather forecasting and early warning; as well as earthquake monitoring, and constantly improved our disaster prevention and protection capabilities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>区域协调发展迈出新步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took new steps in balancing development between regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施区域发展总体战略，制定若干区域发展重大规划和政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We thoroughly implemented the overall strategy for regional development; and formulated several major regional development plans and policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中西部和东北地区加快开放开发，积极承接产业转移，发展基础不断夯实；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central and western regions and northeast China accelerated opening up and development, welcomed industries relocated from other parts of the country, and continuously strengthened their foundation for development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>东部地区加快结构和自主创新，经济发展活力增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The eastern region accelerated restructuring and independent innovation, and the vitality of its economic development increased. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>区域发展呈现布局改善、结构优化、协调性提高的良好态势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A favorable situation emerged in which regional development was better distributed, structured and coordinated.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（三）坚持深化改革开放，不断完善有利于科学发展的体制机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. Steadfastly deepening reform and opening up, and constantly improving institutions and mechanisms conducive to developing scientifically. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们把深化改革开放作为应对国际金融危机的强大动力，努力消除体制障碍，不断提高对外开放水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We deepened reform and opening up to respond more powerfully to the global financial crisis, worked hard to remove institutional obstacles and continued to open wider to the outside world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点领域和关键环节改革加快推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We accelerated reform in key areas and links. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增值税转型全面实施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We comprehensively carried out VAT reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>成品油价格和税费改革顺利推进，新的成品油价格形成机制规范运行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The reform of the prices of refined oil products and taxes and fees on them was implemented smoothly, and a new mechanism for pricing them worked well. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家开发银行商业化转型和农业银行股份制改革扎实推进，跨境贸易人民币结算试点启动实施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made solid progress in commercializing the China Development Bank and introducing the joint stock system in the Agricultural Bank of China, and launched a pilot project to use the renminbi as the settlement currency for cross-border trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创业板正式推出，为自主创新及其他成长型创业企业开辟了新的融资渠道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The ChiNext stock market was officially launched, which opened a new financing channel for enterprises based on independent innovation and other growth enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>地方政府机构改革有序开展，事业单位分类改革试点稳步进行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We proceeded with the reform of local government departments in an orderly manner, and steadily carried out a trial of reforming institutions by type. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>集体林权制度改革全面推开，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We comprehensively launched the reform of tenure in collective forests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>15亿亩林地确权到户，占全国集体林地面积的60%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We devolved tenure in 100 million hectares of forest land to rural households, equaling 60% of the country's total area of collective forests.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是继土地家庭承包之后我国农村经营制度的又一重大变革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is another major reform of China's rural operation system, and follows in the footsteps of the household land contract responsibility system.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开放型经济水平不断提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We constantly raised the level of the open economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>出台一系列稳定外需的政策措施，采取符合国际惯例的方式支持出口企业，完成短期出口信用保险承保900亿美元，安排421亿美元大型成套设备出口融资保险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We introduced policies and measures to stabilize foreign demand, adopted methods that conform to international practices to support export companies, completed the issuance of short-term export credit insurance worth US$ 90 billion, and arranged $42.1 billion of export financing insurance for complete sets of large equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励增加进口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We encouraged increases in imports:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年下半年开始进出口降幅明显收窄，国际市场份额得到巩固，全年进出口总额2.2万亿美元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Since the second half of last year; falls in imports and exports have clearly eased, and we have consolidated our share of international markets. Last year imports and exports totaled $2.2 trillion. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扭转利用外资下降局面，全年实际利用外商直接投资900亿美元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We reversed the decline in utilized foreign investment, and actual utilized foreign direct investment amounted to $90 billion for the entire year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>企业“走出去”逆势上扬，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More enterprises "went global" in spite of the adverse situation;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>非金融类对外直接投资和对外工程承包营业额分别达433亿美元和777亿美元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>non-financial outward direct investment amounted to $43.3 billion, and receipts from overseas project contracting operations reached $77.7 billion. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极参与国际宏观经济政策对话协调和经贸金融合作，在共同应对国际金融危机中发挥了建设性作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We actively participated in international macroeconomic policy dialogue and coordination as well as economic, trade and financial cooperation, and played a constructive role in the joint response to the global financial crisis.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（四）着力改善民生，加快发展社会事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. Striving to improve people's wellbeing and accelerating the development of social programs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在应对国际金融危机的困难情况下，我们更加注重保障和改善民生，切实解决人民群众最关心、最直接、最现实的利益问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the difficult circumstances of responding to the global financial crisis, we gave greater priority to ensuring and improving people's wellbeing and effectively solved the most practical problems of the greatest and most direct concern to the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施更加积极的就业政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented a more active employment policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化政府促进就业的责任。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased the responsibility of the government for stimulating employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政安排就业专项资金426亿元，比上年增长59%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government allocated 42.6 billion yuan in special employment funds, an increase of 59%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施困难企业缓缴社会保险费或降低部分费率、再就业税收减免及提供相关补贴等政策，鼓励企业稳定和增加就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For distressed enterprises, we postponed and in some cases reduced their payment of social security contributions. We also reduced or exempted reemployment tax and provided related subsidies to encourage enterprises to maintain or increase their levels of employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展系列就业服务活动，多渠道开辟公益性就业岗位，促进高校毕业生到基层就业、应征入伍和到企事业单位就业见习。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We launched a series of employment service activities, created public-service jobs through multiple channels, and encouraged college graduates to take jobs at the primary level, enlist in the army, or join enterprises and institutions as interns. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年组织2100万城乡劳动者参加职业培训。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We provided job training for 21 million urban and rural workers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这些措施促进了就业的基本稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These measures helped bring about basic employment stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快完善社会保障体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We accelerated improvements in the social security system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>普遍建立养老保险省级统筹制度，出台包括农民工在内的城镇企业职工养老保险关系转移接续办法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We established a nationwide pension planning system at the provincial level, and introduced a method for transferring pension accounts for workers of urban enterprises, some of whom are rural migrant workers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在320个县开展新型农村社会养老保险试点，推动我国社会保障制度建设迈出历史性步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We launched a pilot project for a new rural pension insurance system in 320 counties - a historic step forward in the development of China's social security system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政安排社会保障资金2906亿元，比上年增长16.6%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government allocated 290.6 billion yuan in social security funds, an increase of 16.6%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>企业退休人员基本养老金连续5年增加，去年又人均提高10%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pensions for enterprise retirees increased for the fifth consecutive year and registered another 10% rise per person. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农村五保户供养水平、优抚对象抚恤补助标准、城乡低保对象保障水平都有新的提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We provided better care for childless and infirm rural residents receiving guarantees of food, clothing, medical care, housing and burial expenses. We increased subsidies for entitled groups and subsistence allowances for both urban and rural recipients. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政安排保障性安居工程补助资金551亿元，比上年增长2倍。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government used 55.1 billion yuan to develop low-income housing projects, a two-fold increase over the previous year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新建、改扩建各类保障性住房200万套，棚户区改造解决住房130万套。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We built, renovated or expanded 2 million low-income housing units of various types, and renovated or built 1.3 million housing units in run-down areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全国社会保障基金积累6927亿元，比上年增长44.2%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Nationwide, social security funds reached 692.7 billion yuan, an increase of 44.2%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>社会保障体系得到加强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened the social security system.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步促进教育公平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made education more equitable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大幅度增加全国教育支出，其中中央财政支出1981亿元，比上年增长23.6%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased education spending nationwide significantly, including central government spending of 198.1 billion yuan, an increase of 23.6%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面落实城乡义务教育政策，中央下达农村义务教育经费666亿元，提前一年实现农村中小学生人均公用经费500元和300元的目标。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We comprehensively implemented the urban and rural compulsory education policy, spent 66.6 billion yuan of central government funds on rural compulsory education, and reached the target of raising public spending for rural secondary and primary school students to an average of 500 yuan and 300 yuan per student respectively a year ahead of schedule. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实行义务教育阶段教师绩效工资制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented a performance-based pay system for compulsory education teachers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中等职业学校农村家庭经济困难学生和涉农专业学生免学费政策开始实施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We started to implement the policy of free tuition for rural students attending secondary vocational schools whose families have financial difficulties and students in such schools who are studying agriculture-related majors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家助学制度不断完善，资助学生2871万人，基本保障了困难家庭的孩子不因贫困而失学。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We constantly improved the national student financial aid system; which benefited 28.71 million students and basically ensured that no children from poor families were denied schooling due to financial difficulties.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推进医药卫生事业改革发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made steady progress in the reform and development of the pharmaceutical and healthcare fields. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>组织实施医药卫生体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We organized the implementation of the reform of the pharmaceutical and healthcare systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政医疗卫生支出1277亿元，比上年增长49.5%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government spent 127.7 billion yuan on medical and health care, an increase of 49.5%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇职工和城镇居民基本医疗保险参保4.01亿人，新型农村合作医疗制度覆盖8.3亿人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 401 million urban workers and non-working urban residents subscribed to basic medical insurance; and coverage of the new type of rural cooperative medical care system reached $30 million people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政安排429亿元，解决关闭破产国有企业退休人员医疗保险问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government allocated 42.9 billion yuan to solve the problem of medical insurance for retired workers from closed and bankrupt state-owned enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>基本药物制度在30％的基层医疗卫生机构实施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The basic drug system has been implemented in 30% of primary-level medical and health care institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政支持建设了一批县级医院、乡镇中心卫生院和社区卫生服务中心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government funds were used to support the construction of a number of county-level hospitals, town and township central hospitals, and community health service centers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动实施扩大乙肝疫苗接种等重大公共卫生服务专项。加强食品、药品安全专项整治。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We launched major public health service projects, including one to increase vaccinations against hepatitis B. We intensified special campaigns for food and drug safety. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对突如其来的甲型HlN1流感疫情，我们依法科学有序地开展防控工作，有效保障了人民群众生命安全，维护了社会正常秩序。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Faced with the sudden outbreak of influenza A (H1N1), we carried out scientific and orderly prevention and control work in accordance with the law, and thereby effectively protected people's lives and maintained normal order in society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在国际金融危机严重冲击、世界经济负增长的背景下，我国取得这样的成绩极为不易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It was not at all easy for our country to make all these achievements against the backdrop of the severe impact of the global financial crisis and the negative growth of the world economy:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是以胡锦涛同志为总书记的党中央统揽全局、正确领导的结果，是全党全军全国各族人民和衷共济、团结奋斗的结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>They were the result of the overall planning and correct leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Hu Jintao as General Secretary as well as the concerted and strenuous efforts of the whole Party, the entire army, and the people of all of our ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在这里，我代表国务院，向全国各族人民，各民主党派、各人民团体和各界人士，表示诚挚的感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the Mate Council, I hereby express our sincere gratitude to the people of all of our ethnic groups and to the democratic parties, mass organizations, and people from all sectors of society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向香港特别行政区同胞、澳门特别行政区同胞、台湾同胞和海外侨胞，表示诚挚的感谢！向关心和支持中国现代化建设的各国政府、国际组织和各国朋友，表示诚挚的感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I also express our sincere thanks to our compatriots in the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions, in Taiwan, and overseas, as well as to foreign governments, international organizations, and friends in other countries that take an interest in and support China's modernization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们认真贯彻落实科学发展观，积极应对国际金融危机，全面做好政府工作，有以下几点体会：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the course of the past year, as we conscientiously applied the Scientific Outlook on Development; vigorously responded to the global financial crisis and completed all of our government work, we came to the following conclusions:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持运用市场机制和宏观调控两种手段，在坚持市场经济改革方向、发挥市场配置资源基础性作用、激发市场活力的同时，充分发挥我国社会主义制度决策高效、组织有力、集中力量办大事的优势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must continue to make use of both market mechanisms and macro-control, that is, at the same time as we keep our reforms oriented toward a market economy, let market forces play their basic role in allocating resources, and stimulate the market's vitality, we must make best use of the socialist system's advantages, which enable us to make decisions efficiently, organize effectively, and concentrate resources to accomplish large undertakings. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持处理好短期和长期两方面关系，注重远近结合、标本兼治，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must balance long- and short-term interests, take into account long- and short-term needs, and address both the symptoms and root causes of problems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>既克服短期困难、解决突出矛盾，又加强重点领域和薄弱环节、为长远发展奠定基础。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must overcome short-term difficulties and solve major problems as well as strengthen key areas and weak links in order to lay a foundation for long-term development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持统筹国内国际两个大局，把扩大内需作为长期战略方针，坚定不移地实行互利共赢的开放战略，加快形成内需外需协调拉动经济增长的格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must continue to consider domestic and international situations, make it a long-term strategic policy to boost domestic demand, adhere to the win-win strategy of opening up, and quickly formulate a pattern in which domestic demand and foreign demand drive economic growth in concert. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持发展经济与改善民生、维护社会公平正义的内在统一，围绕改善民生谋发展，把改善民生作为经济发展的出发点、落脚点和持久动力，着眼维护公平正义，让全体人民共享改革发展成果，促进社会和谐稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must always remember that developing the economy is inseparable from improving people's wellbeing and safeguarding social fairness and justice; make improving people's wellbeing the focus of development, and the starting point, goal, and lasting driving force of economic development; strive to safeguard fairness and justice; ensure that all of the people share in the fruits of reform and development; and promote social harmony and stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持发挥中央和地方两个积极性，既强调统一思想、顾全大局，又鼓励因地制宜、探索创新，形成共克时艰的强大合力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must give free rein to the initiative of both the central and local authorities. While stressing unity of thinking and keeping overall interests in mind, we also need to encourage everyone to proceed in light of local conditions and make explorations and innovations, in order to form a powerful, concerted force for overcoming present difficulties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这些经验对我们坚持中国特色社会主义道路，提高驾驭社会主义市场经济能力，推进现代化进程，具有重要而深远的意义。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All of these experiences are of vital and profound significance for keeping to the path of socialism with Chinese characteristics, improving our ability to run the socialist market economy, and pushing ahead the process of modernization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二、2010年主要任务</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>II. Main Tasks for 2010</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年是继续应对国际金融危机、保持经济平稳较快发展、加快转变经济发展方式的关键一年，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is a crucial year for continuing to deal with the global financial crisis, maintaining steady and rapid economic development, and accelerating the transformation of the pattern of economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>是全面实现“十一五”规划目标、为“十二五”发展打好基础的重要一年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It is also an important year for achieving all the targets of the Eleventh Five-Year Plan and laying a solid foundation for development on the basis of the Twelfth Five-Year Plan.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年发展环境虽然有可能好于去年，但是面临的形势极为复杂。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Although this year's development environment may be better than last year's, we still face a very complex situation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各种积极变化和不利影响此长彼消，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some positive changes and negative influences are growing while others are diminishing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>短期问题和长期矛盾相互交织，国内因素和国际因素相互影响，经济社会发展中“两难”问题增多。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Short-term and long-term problems are interwoven, domestic and international factors mutually affect each other, and the dilemmas facing economic and social development are increasing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从国际看，世界经济有望恢复性增长，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Internationally, the global economy will hopefully turn around. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国际金融市场渐趋稳定，经济全球化深入发展的大趋势没有改变，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>International financial markets are stabilizing, and the overall trend toward increased economic globalization has not changed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>世界经济格局大变革、大调整孕育着新的发展机遇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Considerable changes and adjustments in the world economic structure will bring new development opportunities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时，世界经济复苏的基础仍然脆弱，金融领域风险没有完全消除，各国刺激政策退出抉择艰难，国际大宗商品价格和主要货币汇率可能加剧波动，贸易保护主义明显抬头，加上气候变化、粮食安全、能源资源等全球性问题错综复杂，外部环境不稳定、不确定因素依然很多。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At the same time, many destabilizing factors and uncertainties remain in our external environment. The foundation for global economic recovery remains weak; financial risks have not been completely eliminated; individual countries face difficult choices in phasing out their stimulus policies; larger fluctuations may occur in the prices of major commodities and exchange rates among the major currencies; trade protectionism is clearly reasserting itself; and global problems such as climate change, food security and energy and resource supplies remain complex. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从国内看，我国仍处在重要战略机遇期。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Domestically, our country is still in an important period of strategic opportunities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济回升向好的基础进一步巩固，市场信心增强，扩大内需和改善民生的政策效应继续显现，企业适应市场变化的能力和竞争力不断提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The foundation for economic turnaround is becoming stronger, market confidence has increased, the policy we adopted to boost domestic demand and improve people's wellbeing continues to show results, and enterprises are constantly becoming more competitive and better able to adapt to market changes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>但是，经济社会发展中仍然存在一些突出矛盾和问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Nevertheless, there are still some serious problems affecting economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济增长内生动力不足，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There is insufficient internal impetus driving economic growth;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>自主创新能力不强，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>our independent innovation capability is not strong;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>部分行业产能过剩矛盾突出，结构调整难度加大；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>there is still considerable excess production capacity in some industries and it is becoming more difficult to restructure them;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>就业压力总体上持续增加和结构性用工短缺的矛盾并存；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>while the pressure on employment is constantly growing overall, there is a structural shortage of labor;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农业稳定发展和农民持续增收的基础不稳固；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the foundation for keeping agricultural production and farmers' incomes growing steadily is weak;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政金融领域潜在风险增加；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>latent risks in the banking and public finance sectors are increasing</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>医疗、教育、住房、收入分配、社会管理等方面的突出问题亟待解决。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and major problems in the areas of healthcare, education, housing, income distribution and public administration urgently require solutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们必须全面、正确判断形势，决不能把经济回升向好的趋势等同于经济运行根本好转。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must make a comprehensive and correct judgment of the situation, and we must not interpret the economic turnaround as a fundamental improvement in the economic situation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要增强忧患意识，充分利用有利条件和积极因素，努力化解矛盾，更加周密地做好应对各种风险和挑战的准备，牢牢把握工作的主动权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to strengthen our awareness of potential dangers, make full use of favorable conditions and positive factors, strive to resolve problems, make even more thorough preparations to deal with risks and challenges of all kinds, and firmly keep the initiative in our work.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好今年的政府工作，要认真贯彻党的十七大和十七届三中、四中全会精神，以邓小平理论和“三个代表”重要思想为指导，深入贯彻落实科学发展观，着力搞好宏观调控和保持经济平稳较快发展，着力加快经济发展方式转变和经济结构调整，着力推进改革开放和自主创新，着力改善民生和促进社会和谐稳定，全面推进社会主义经济建设、政治建设、文化建设、社会建设以及生态文明建设，加快全面建设小康社会进程，努力实现经济社会又好又快发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To do a good job of our government work this year, we need to conscientiously implement the guiding principles of the Seventeenth National Party Congress and the third and fourth plenary sessions of the Seventeenth Central Committee; take Deng Xiaoping Theory and the important thought of Three Represents as our guide; thoroughly implement the Scientific Outlook on Development; strive to apply macro-control appropriately and maintain steady and rapid economic development; work hard to accelerate economic restructuring and the transformation of the pattern of economic development; press ahead with reform and opening up and with independent innovation; strive to improve people's wellbeing and to promote social harmony and stability; make headway with our efforts to encourage socialist economic, political, cultural, social, and ecological development; pick up the pace of building a moderately prosperous society in all respects; and work hard to achieve sound, rapid economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年经济社会发展的主要预期目标是：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year the main targets we have set for economic and social development are:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值增长8％左右；城镇新增就业900万人以上，城镇登记失业率控制在4.6％以内；居民消费价格涨幅3％左右；国际收支状况改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>increasing GDP by approximately 8%, creating jobs for more than 9 million people entering the urban workforce, keeping the urban registered unemployment rate no higher than 4.6%, holding the rise in consumer prices to around 3%, and improving the balance of payments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这里要着重说明，提出国内生产总值增长8％左右，主要是强调好字当头，引导各方面把工作重点放到转变经济发展方式、调整经济结构上来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Here I would like to stress that in targeting a GDP increase of around 8%, we are emphasizing sound development, and we need to guide all sectors to focus on transforming the pattern of economic development and restructuring the economy in their work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提出居民消费价格涨幅3％左右，综合考虑了去年价格变动的翘尾因素、国际大宗商品价格的传导效应、国内货币信贷增长的滞后影响以及居民的承受能力，并为资源环境税费和资源性产品价格改革留有一定空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By targeting an increase in consumer prices of around 3%, we are giving full consideration to the carry-over effects of last year's price changes, the reverberations caused by price changes for major international commodities, the continued impact of increases in domestic supplies of money and credit, and consumers' ability to bear price increases, while also leaving room for reform in resource and environment taxes and fees and in the pricing of resource products.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要重点抓好八个方面工作：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year we will focus on the following eight areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（一）提高宏观调控水平，保持经济平稳较快发展</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. Exercising better macro-control and maintaining steady and rapid economic development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要继续实施积极的财政政策和适度宽松的货币政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to continue to implement a proactive fiscal policy and a moderately easy monetary policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持政策的连续性和稳定性，根据新形势新情况不断提高政策的针对性和灵活性，把握好政策实施的力度、节奏和重点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to maintain continuity and stability in our policies while constantly making them better-targeted and more flexible as circumstances and conditions change, and keep a good grasp of the intensity, pace and focus of their implementation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>处理好保持经济平稳较快发展、调整经济结构和管理好通胀预期的关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to skillfully handle the relationship between maintaining steady and rapid economic development, restructuring the economy and managing inflation expectations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>既要保持足够的政策力度、巩固经济回升向好的势头，又要加快经济结构调整、推动经济发展方式转变取得实质性进展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We not only need to maintain sufficient policy intensity and consolidate the momentum of the economic turnaround, but we also need to accelerate economic restructuring and make substantive progress in transforming the pattern of economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>还要管理好通胀预期、稳定物价总水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addition, we need to manage inflation expectations well and keep the overall level of prices stable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施积极的财政政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement a proactive fiscal policy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是保持适度的财政赤字和国债规模。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will keep the deficit and government bonds at appropriate levels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年拟安排财政赤字10500亿元，其中中央财政赤字8500亿元，继续代发地方债2000亿元并纳入地方财政预算。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we have projected a deficit of 1.05 trillion yuan, which consists of 850 billion yuan in central government deficit and 200 billion yuan in local government bonds, which will be included in local government budgets. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这样的安排主要是考虑到今年财政收支矛盾仍然十分突出。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These arrangements are based mainly on the consideration that this year revenue will fall significantly short of expenditures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从财政收入看，上一年一次性特殊增收措施没有或减少了，还要继续实施结构性减税政策，财政收入增长不会太快；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Regarding revenue, last year's one-off measures to increase revenue will either not be repeated or will be decreased. We also need to continue to implement the policy of structural tax reductions; consequently, revenue will not increase very quickly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从财政支出看，继续实施应对国际金融危机的一揽子计划，完成在建项目、加强薄弱环节、推进改革、改善民生、维护稳定等都需要增加投入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Regarding expenditures, we will continue to implement the package plan for dealing with the global financial crisis, and increase spending to complete work on projects now under construction, strengthen weak links, carry forward reform, improve people's wellbeing and maintain stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是继续实施结构性减税政策，促进扩大内需和经济结构调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will continue to implement the structural tax reduction policy to expand domestic demand and promote economic restructuring.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是优化财政支出结构，有保有压，把钱花在刀刃上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will improve the structure of expenditures, maintain expenditures in some areas while reducing them in others, and spend our money where it counts the most. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续向“三农”、民生、社会事业等领域倾斜，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to give preference to agriculture, farmers, and rural areas, and to improving people's wellbeing and developing social programs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持节能环保、自主创新和欠发达地区的建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support energy conservation, environmental protection, independent innovation, and development in underdeveloped areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格控制一般性支出，大力压缩公用经费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strictly control regular expenditures, and do all we can to reduce public spending.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是切实加强政府性债务管理，增强内外部约束力，有效防范和化解潜在财政风险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will effectively improve government debt management, strengthen internal and external restraints, and effectively guard against and fend off latent public finance risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时，要依法加强税收征管和非税收入管理，严厉打击偷骗税行为，做到应收尽收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addition, we need to strengthen tax collection and supervision as well as supervision of non-tax revenue in accordance with the law, strictly crack down on tax fraud, and collect all due taxes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施适度宽松的货币政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement a moderately easy monetary policy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是保持货币信贷合理充裕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will ensure that there are proper and sufficient supplies of money and credit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年广义货币M2增长目标为17％左右，新增人民币贷款7.5万亿元左右。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year's target for expanding the broad money supply (M2) is around 17%, and we will increase the total quantity of renminbi loans by approximately 7.5 trillion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这两个指标虽然都低于去年实际执行结果，但仍然是一个适度宽松的政策目标，能够满足经济社会发展的合理资金需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Although both of these increases are less than the actual increases last year, they are still moderately easy policy goals, and they can satisfy reasonable financial demands of economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时也有利于管理好通胀预期、提高金融支持经济发展的可持续性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addition, these goals are beneficial for managing inflation expectations and making financial support for economic development more sustainable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是优化信贷结构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will improve the credit structure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实有保有控的信贷政策，加强对重点领域和薄弱环节的支持，有效缓解农户和小企业融资难问题，严格控制对“两高”行业和产能过剩行业的贷款。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement a credit policy that guarantees credit in some areas and limits it in others; increase support for important areas and weak links; effectively alleviate the difficulties farmers and small businesses have in obtaining financing; and strictly control loans to industries that are energy-intensive, highly polluting or saddled with overcapacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化贷后管理，确保信贷资金支持实体经济。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen post-loan supervision and ensure that loans are used to support the real economy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是积极扩大直接融资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will actively expand direct financing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善多层次资本市场体系，扩大股权和债券融资规模，更好地满足多样化投融资需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the system of multilevel capital markets, increase financing by selling equities and issuing bonds, and better satisfy the diverse demand for investment and financing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是加强风险管理，提高金融监管有效性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will strengthen risk management and make financial oversight and supervision more effective. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>探索建立宏观审慎管理制度，强化对跨境资本流动的有效监控，防范各类金融风险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will explore ways to establish a system of prudent macro management, strengthen the monitoring of the cross-border flow of capital, and guard against all kinds of financial risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续完善人民币汇率形成机制，保持人民币汇率在合理、均衡水平上的基本稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve the mechanism for setting the renminbi exchange rate and keep it basically stable at an appropriate and balanced level.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极扩大居民消费需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will energetically expand consumer demand. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续提高农民收入、企业退休人员基本养老金、部分优抚对象待遇和城乡居民最低生活保障水平，增强居民特别是中低收入者消费能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to increase farmers' incomes, basic pensions of enterprise retirees, allowances to some entitled groups, subsistence allowances for urban and rural residents, and people's purchasing power, especially low- and middle-income earners. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>巩固扩大传统消费，积极培育信息、旅游、文化、健身、培训、养老、家庭服务等消费热点，促进消费结构优化升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen and expand traditional consumption, and promote the upgrading of the consumption structure by actively cultivating areas of high consumption, such as information, tourism, culture, fitness, training, services for the elderly and household services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大消费信贷。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase consumer credit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强商贸流通体系等基础设施建设，积极发展电子商务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen infrastructure, such as the logistics system, and vigorously develop e-commerce. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>整顿和规范市场秩序，努力营造便利、安全、放心的消费环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will overhaul and standardize markets to create a convenient, safe and worry-free environment for consumers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施和完善鼓励消费的各项政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement and improve all of our policies and measures for encouraging consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大幅提高家电下乡产品最高限价，增加品种和型号，扩大补贴范围，完善补贴标准和办法，加强对中标企业的管理和考核，提高产品质量和服务水平；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will considerably raise the maximum price limits for home appliances sold, in the countryside, increase types of appliances and models eligible for subsidies, expand the scope of subsidies, improve the criteria for qualifying for subsidies and the way subsidies are granted, strengthen supervision and evaluation of enterprises that win bids for contracts, and raise the quality of products and services.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善家电、汽车以旧换新和汽车、摩托车下乡政策，小排量汽车购置税按7.5％征收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the policies for getting consumers to trade-in old motor vehicles and home appliances for new ones and getting rural residents to buy motor vehicles, and set the purchase tax for small-displacement automobiles at 7.5%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们一定要落实好这些政策措施，把好事办好，真正让广大群众得到实惠。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must implement these policies and measures, do meaningful work and do it well, and make sure the benefits reach the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力优化投资结构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strive to improve the investment structure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府投资都要集中力量保重点，严格控制新开工项目，资金安排主要用于项目续建和收尾，切实防止出现“半拉子”工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government investment at all levels needs to be concentrated in the most important areas, and the launching of new projects must be strictly controlled. It should be used mainly for carrying on and completing projects, and we need to ensure that projects are not stopped midway. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进地震灾区恢复重建，保质保量完成任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will steadily move forward with the recovery and reconstruction of quake-hit areas, and make sure quality and quantity targets are met. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励扩大民间投资，完善和落实促进民间投资的相关政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage greater non-government investment, and improve and implement policies to achieve this goal. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强和改进投资管理，严格执行用地、节能、环保、安全等市场准入标准和产业政策，切实防止重复建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen and improve the supervision of investment; strictly enforce market entry standards and industrial policies concerning land use, energy conservation, environmental protection, and safety; and effectively prevent redundant construction. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对有财政资金投入的建设项目，要加强全程监督，坚决避免以扩大内需为名，搞劳民伤财的形象工程和政绩工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For projects financed through the public treasury, relevant departments need to exercise oversight of the entire course of the project, and we must prevent the construction of image and vanity projects that waste manpower and money in the name of boosting domestic demand. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持科学民主决策，确保公共投资真正用于推进经济社会发展和改善人民生活，经得起实践和历史的检验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adhere to scientific and democratic decision making, and ensure that public funds are spent on projects that promote economic and social development and improve people's lives and that will stand the test of practice and history.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（二）加快转变经济发展方式，调整优化经济结构</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Accelerating the transformation of the pattern of economic development and adjusting and optimizing the economic structure.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>转变经济发展方式刻不容缓。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We urgently need to transform the pattern of economic development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要大力推动经济进入创新驱动、内生增长的发展轨道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to put economic development onto the track of endogenous growth driven by innovation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进重点产业调整振兴。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to promote restructuring and revitalization in key industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是加大技术改造力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will intensify technological upgrading. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>用好技改专项资金，引导企业开发新产品和节能降耗。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively use funds for technological upgrading to guide enterprises in developing new products, saving energy and reducing resource consumption.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是促进企业兼并重组。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will encourage mergers and reorganization of enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>打破行业垄断和地区封锁，推动优势企业兼并困难企业，加快淘汰落后产能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will break industry monopolies, remove regional blockades, support superior enterprises in acquiring ones in financial difficulties, and close down backward production facilities more quickly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是全面提升产品质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will comprehensively raise product quality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导企业以品牌、标准、服务和效益为重点，健全质量管理体系，强化社会责任。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide enterprises to improve their quality management systems; focusing on brands, standards, service, and performance, and to enhance their sense of social responsibility.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实加强市场监管和诚信体系建设，努力把我国产品质量提高到新水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively strengthen the market oversight and credibility systems, and strive to raise the quality of China's products to a new level.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力培育战略性新兴产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will foster emerging industries of strategic importance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国际金融危机正在催生新的科技革命和产业革命。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The global financial crisis is hastening the birth of a new technological and industrial revolution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展战略性新兴产业，抢占经济科技制高点，决定国家的未来，必须抓住机遇，明确重点，有所作为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It is of decisive importance for the future of our country that we develop emerging industries of strategic importance and capture the economic, scientific and technological high ground; therefore, we must seize opportunities, identify priorities, and achieve results. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要大力发展新能源、新材料、节能环保、生物医药、信息网络和高端制造产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to vigorously develop new energy sources, new materials, energy conservation, environmental protection, biomedicine, information networks, and high-end manufacturing industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推进新能源汽车、“三网”融合取得实质性进展，加快物联网的研发应用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make substantive progress in developing motor vehicles powered by new energy sources and in integrating telecommunications networks, cable television networks, and the Internet, and accelerate R&amp;D in and application of the Internet of Things. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大对战略性新兴产业的投入和政策支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also increase investment in and policy support for emerging industries of strategic importance.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步促进中小企业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further promote the development of small and medium-sized enterprises.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是建立和完善中小企业服务体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will set up a sound service system for small and medium-sized enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓紧修订中小企业划分标准，加快中小企业公共服务平台、信息服务网络和小企业创业基地建设，进一步减少、简化行政审批，坚决清理和取消不合理收费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promptly revise the criteria for classifying such enterprises, accelerate the development of a public service platform and an information service network for them and bases for small business startups, continue to reduce and streamline administrative examination and approval procedures, and resolutely sort out fees and eliminate unreasonable ones.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是继续落实财政对中小企业支持政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will continue to implement the policy of fiscal support for small and medium-sized enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政扶持中小企业发展专项资金安排106亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will allocate 10.6 billion yuan to support their development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对部分小型微利企业实行所得税优惠政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A preferential income tax policy for small enterprises with low profits will be implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政预算内技术改造专项投资要覆盖中小企业，地方政府也要加大投入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Small and medium-sized enterprises will be eligible to receive money from special funds for technological upgrading in the central budget, and local governments should also increase investment in technological upgrading.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是加强对中小企业的金融支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will provide better financial support for small and medium-sized enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善小企业信贷考核体系。鼓励建立小企业贷款风险补偿基金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the credit assessment system for small enterprises, and encourage the establishment of a loan risk compensation fund for them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中小企业贷款税前全额拨备损失准备金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will allow full tax deductions for loan loss reserves for loans to small and medium-sized enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展多层次中小企业信用担保体系，落实好对符合条件的中小企业信用担保机构免征营业税、准备金提取和代偿损失在税前扣除的政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop a multilevel system of credit guarantees for these enterprises, and implement the policy of exempting business tax for qualified credit guarantee agencies serving them and allow those agencies to exempt withdrawals from reserve funds and compensation for losses from taxation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓宽中小企业融资渠道，切实解决中小企业特别是小企业融资难问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand channels for small and medium-sized enterprises to obtain financing in order to effectively solve their financing problems, especially those of small enterprises.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快发展服务业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of the service sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步提高服务业发展水平和在国民经济中的比重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further raise the development level of the service sector and its proportion of the national economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展金融、物流、信息、研发、工业设计、商务、节能环保服务等面向生产的服务业，促进服务业与现代制造业有机融合。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously develop production-oriented service industries, including finance, logistics, information, R&amp;D, industrial design, commerce, energy conservation, and environmental protection services, and promote the intimate integration of service industries with modern manufacturing industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展市政公用事业、房地产和物业服务、社区服务等面向民生的服务业，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also develop public utilities, real estate, and property management services, community services and other service industries closely related to people's wellbeing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快发展旅游业，积极拓展新型服务领域。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of tourism and expand new types of services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农村服务业基础薄弱、发展潜力大，要加快构建和完善以生产销售、科技信息和金融服务为主体的农村生产生活服务体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In view of the weak foundation and great potential of the service sector in rural areas, we need to accelerate the establishment of a sound system of rural workplace and consumer services, mainly revolving around production, sales, scientific and technological information, and financial services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建立公开平等规范的服务业准入制度，鼓励社会资本进入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up the establishment of an open, fair, and standardized system for licensing service providers and encourage the participation of non-government capital. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步完善促进服务业发展的政策，逐步实现国家鼓励类服务业用电、用水、用气、用热与工业基本同价。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further improve policies for promoting development in the service sector, and gradually lower the electricity, water, gas, and heat rates for service industries encouraged by the state to the same levels charged to industrial enterprises.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>打好节能减排攻坚战和持久战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strive to conserve energy and reduce emissions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一要以工业、交通、建筑为重点，大力推进节能，提高能源效率。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will energetically promote energy conservation and raise the efficiency of energy consumption, especially in industry, transportation, and construction. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进十大重点节能工程、千家企业节能行动和节能产品惠民工程，形成全社会节能的良好风尚。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make solid progress in the ten major energy conservation projects, the campaign to save energy in 1,000 enterprises, and the project to promote energy-efficient products that benefit the people, and make saving energy a good habit throughout society. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要新增8000万吨标准煤的节能能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase our energy-saving capacity by an equivalent of 80 million tons of standard coal. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>所有新建、改建、扩建燃煤机组必须同步建成并运行烟气脱硫设施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Every newly built, renovated or expanded coal-fired power generating unit must be equipped with and continuously employ desulphurization equipment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二要加强环境保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will strengthen environmental protection. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推进重点流域区域环境治理及城镇污水垃圾处理、农业面源污染治理、重金属污染综合整治等工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to improve the environment in key watersheds and regions, treat urban sewage and garbage, deal with pollution from non-point agricultural sources, and comprehensively clean up heavy metal pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新增城镇污水日处理能力1500万立方米、垃圾日处理能力6万吨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In urban areas, the daily sewage treatment capacity will increase by 15 million cubic meters and the daily garbage disposal capacity will grow by 60,000 tons.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三要积极发展循环经济和节能环保产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will energetically develop a circular economy and the energy conservation and environmental protection industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持循环经济技术研发、示范推广和能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For the circular economy, we will support R&amp;D in technology, demonstrations and applications, and capacity building. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓好节能、节水、节地、节材工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will save energy, water, land and materials. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进矿产资源综合利用、工业废物回收利用、余热余压发电和生活垃圾资源化利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will comprehensively utilize mineral resources, recycle industrial waste, use by-product heat and pressure to generate electricity, and transform household solid waste into resources.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四要积极应对气候变化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will actively respond to climate change. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强适应和减缓气候变化的能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve our ability to adapt to it and ameliorate its effects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力开发低碳技术，推广高效节能技术，积极发展新能源和可再生能源，加强智能电网建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to develop low-carbon technologies; promote application of highly efficient, energy-conserving technologies; develop new and renewable energies; and intensify development of smart power grids. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快国土绿化进程，增加森林碳汇，新增造林面积不低于592万公顷。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate afforestation, increase forest carbon sinks and expand our forests by at least 5.92 million hectares. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要努力建设以低碳排放为特征的产业体系和消费模式，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to energetically build an industrial system and consumption pattern with low carbon emissions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极参与应对气候变化国际合作，推动全球应对气候变化取得新进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will participate in international cooperation to address climate changes and work for further progress in the global fight against climate change.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进区域经济协调发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote balanced economic development between regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续深入推进西部大开发，全面振兴东北地区等老工业基地，大力促进中部地区崛起，积极支持东部地区率先发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to develop the western region on a large scale, comprehensively reinvigorate the old industrial bases in northeast China and elsewhere, energize the development of the central region, and support the eastern region in taking the lead in development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真落实促进区域经济社会发展的各项规划和政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will conscientiously implement all plans and policies for promoting regional economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进主体功能区建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate growth of development priority zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点抓好西藏和四省藏区、新疆经济社会发展政策的制定和实施工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on formulating and implementing policies for economic and social development in Xinjiang, Tibet, and Tibetan ethnic areas in Sichuan, Yunnan, Gansu and Qinghai provinces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对革命老区、民族地区、边疆地区和贫困地区的支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase support for old revolutionary areas, ethnic minority areas, border areas and poverty-stricken areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施区域发展总体战略，重在发挥各地比较优势，有针对性地解决各地发展中的突出矛盾和问题；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>When implementing the overall strategy for regional development, we will emphasize exploiting different regions' comparative advantages and making well-targeted efforts to solve major problems arising in the course of development in each region.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重在扭转区域经济社会发展差距扩大的趋势，增强发展的协调性；重在加快完善公共财政体系，促进基本公共服务均等化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on reversing the growing gap in economic and social development between regions, balancing their development better, accelerating the improvement of the public finance system, and snaking access to basic public services more equal.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（三）加大统筹城乡发展力度，强化农业农村发展基础</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. Improving the balance between urban and rural development and strengthening the foundation for the development of agriculture and rural areas</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在连续6年增产增收之后，更要毫不松懈地抓好“三农”工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>After six consecutive years of increases in grain output and rural incomes, it is vital we sustain our good work in the areas of agriculture, rural areas, and farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要按照统筹城乡发展的要求，坚持把解决好“三农”问题作为全部工作的重中之重，进一步强化强农惠农政策，协调推进工业化、城镇化和农业农村现代化，巩固和发展农业农村好形势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In accordance with the requirements for balancing urban and rural development, we need to make solving problems faced by agriculture, rural areas, and farmers a top priority in all our work; further strengthen our policies to aid agriculture and benefit farmers; coordinate industrialization, urbanization, and agricultural and rural modernization; and consolidate and build upon the good situation in agriculture and rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进农业稳定发展和农民持续增收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the steady development of agriculture and a continuous increase in rural incomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定粮食生产，扩大油料种植面积，增加重要紧缺农产品供应，大规模开展粮棉油糖高产创建，大规模开展园艺产品生产和畜牧水产养殖标准化创建，保障“米袋子”、“菜篮子”安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep grain production stable; expand the total area sown with oilseed; increase supplies of important agricultural products in short supply; implement a large-scale effort to increase the production of grain, cotton, oilseed, and sugar; standardize farming practices in horticulture, animal husbandry, and aquaculture; and ensure the security of the "rice bag" (grain supply) and "vegetable basket" (non-staple food supply). </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施对种粮农民直接补贴，增加农资综合补贴、良种补贴、农机具购置补贴，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to provide direct subsidies for grain producers, and increase general subsidies for purchasing agricultural supplies and subsidies for purchasing superior crop varieties and agricultural machinery and tools.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政拟安排补贴资金1335亿元，比上年增加60.4亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will allocate 133.5 billion yuan for this purpose, a year-on-year increase of 6.04 billion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步提高粮食最低收购价，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further raise minimum grain purchase prices. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>早籼稻、中晚籼稻、粳稻每斤分别提高3分、5分和1毛钱，小麦每斤提高3分钱，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The minimum prices of early indica rice, middle-season and late indica rice and japonica rice will be raised by 0.06 yuan, 0.1 yuan and 0.2 yuan per kilogram respectively, and the minimum price of wheat will be raised by 0.06 yuan per kilogram.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施重要农产品临时收储政策，让农民得到更多实惠。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement the policy of purchasing and temporarily stockpiling major agricultural products and give farmers more tangible benefits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对产粮大县、养猪大县、养牛大县的财政扶持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase fiscal support for major grain-producing, pork-producing, and cattle farming counties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展农产品加工业，推进农业产业化经营，支持批发市场和农贸市场升级改造，推动生产与市场对接。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously develop the processing industry for agricultural products, promote industrialization in agriculture, support the upgrading and renovation of wholesale markets and markets for farm produce, and promote closer linkage between production and the market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进农民就业创业，多渠道增加农民收入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will help rural residents find jobs or start their own businesses, and increase rural incomes through a variety of channels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步加大扶贫开发力度。我们要坚持不懈地消除贫困落后，让农民群众早日过上富裕安康的生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify poverty alleviation and development and work tirelessly to eradicate poverty and backwardness so that rural residents can soon live a prosperous and happy life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农业基础设施建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen agricultural infrastructure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持财政支出优先支持农业农村发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to give high priority in government spending to supporting agricultural and rural development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>预算内固定资产投资优先投向农业基础设施和农村民生工程，土地出让收益优先用于农业土地开发和农村基础设施建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the budget, our priority for fixed asset investment will be agricultural infrastructure and projects that improve the wellbeing of rural residents, and our priority for use of proceeds from the transfer of land-use rights will be developing agricultural land and building rural infrastructure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政拟安排“三农”投入8183亿元，比上年增加930亿元，地方各级财政也要增加投入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government plans to allocate 818.3 billion yuan for agriculture, farmers, and rural areas, an increase of 93 billion yuan over last year, and local governments at all levels will also increase their investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以主产区为重点，全面实施全国新增千亿斤粮食生产能力建设规划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will comprehensively implement the plan to increase grain production by 50 billion kilograms nationwide, with the emphasis on major grain-producing regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以农田水利为重点，加强农业基础设施建设，加快大中型灌区的配套改造，扩大节水灌溉面积，建设高标准农田，完成大中型和重点小型病险水库除险加固任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Focusing on water conservancy, we will improve agricultural infrastructure, accelerate related upgrades of large and mediumsized irrigated areas, expand the area in which water-conserving irrigation methods are used, create high-grade cropland, and finish reinforcing dilapidated large, medium-sized, and key small reservoirs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以良种培育为重点，加快农业科技创新和推广，实施好转基因生物新品种培育科技重大专项。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the focus on breeding improved crop varieties, we will accelerate innovation in agricultural technology and the widespread adoption of scientific and technological advances, and carry out a major science and technology project to create new crop varieties using gene transfer technology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推进现代农业示范区建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move forward with the construction of modem agriculture demonstration sites. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建设乡镇和区域性农技推广、动植物疫病防控、农产品质量监管等公共服务机构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of public services for extending agricultural technology, preventing and controlling animal and plant diseases, and providing quality oversight of agricultural products in townships, towns and regions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化农村改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen rural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>毫不动摇地坚持农村基本经营制度，加快完善有关法律法规和政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold the basic rural operation system; quickly improve relevant laws, regulations and policies;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现有土地承包关系要保持稳定并长久不变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and maintain existing land contract relationships over the long term. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强土地承包经营权流转的管理和服务，在依法自愿有偿流转基础上发展多种形式规模经营。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen supervision of and services for the transfer of contracted land use rights, and develop diverse large-scale farming operations on the basis of legal, voluntary, and compensated transfers of land-use rights. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进农村综合改革。完善集体林权制度改革配套政策。启动国有林场改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to carry out comprehensive rural reform, improve supporting policies for the reform of tenure in collective forests, and launch the reform of state tree farms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进草原基本经营制度改革。发展农民专业合作社，提高农业组织化程度。加快培育小型农村金融机构，积极推广农村小额信用贷款，切实改善农村金融服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reform the basic system for the use of grasslands, develop specialized farmer cooperatives, improve the organization of agriculture, more quickly develop small rural financial institutions, actively promote micro-credit loans in rural areas, and improve rural financial services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进乡镇机构改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also deepen reforms in township and town government departments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹推进城镇化和新农村建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will balance promoting urbanization and building a new countryside. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持走中国特色城镇化道路，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep to the path of urbanization with Chinese characteristics. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进大中小城市和小城镇协调发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote balanced development between towns and large, small and medium-sized cities;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力提高城镇综合承载能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>increase the overall carrying capacity of cities and towns;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥城市对农村的辐射带动作用，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>ensure that cities stimulate the development of surrounding rural areas;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进城镇化和新农村建设良性互动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and promote positive interaction between urbanization and the building of a new countryside. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>壮大县域经济，大力加强县城和中心镇基础设施和环境建设，引导非农产业和农村人口有序向小城镇集聚，鼓励返乡农民工就地创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen county economies, improve infrastructure and environmental protection in county towns and hub towns, guide an orderly flow of nonagricultural industries and rural people to small towns, and encourage returned rural migrant workers to start businesses in their hometowns. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城乡建设都要坚持最严格的耕地保护制度和最严格的节约用地制度，切实保护农民合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>When developing urban and rural areas, we must adhere to the strictest possible systems for protecting arable land and economizing land use to genuinely safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进户籍制度改革，放宽中小城市和小城镇落户条件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out reform of the household registration system and relax requirements for household registration in towns and small and medium-sized cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有计划有步骤地解决好农民工在城镇的就业和生活问题，逐步实现农民工在劳动报酬、子女就学、公共卫生、住房租购以及社会保障方面与城镇居民享有同等待遇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will solve employment and living problems rural migrant workers face in cities and towns in a planned and step-by-step manner, and gradually ensure that they receive the same treatment as urban residents in areas such as pay, children's education, healthcare, housing, and social security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步增加农村生产生活设施建设投入，启动新一轮农村电网改造，扩大农村沼气建设规模，今年再解决6000万农村人口的安全饮水问题，实施农村清洁工程，改善农村生产生活条件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further increase spending on the development of rural work and living facilities, begin a new round of upgrades of rural power grids, expand the construction of rural methane facilities, provide safe drinking water to another 60 million rural people, carry out the project to build a clean countryside, and improve working and living conditions there. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要让符合条件的农业转移人口逐步变为城镇居民，也要让农民有一个幸福生活的美好家园。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will allow eligible workers who have left agricultural work to gradually become urban residents, and develop a beautiful rural environment where farmers can live a happy life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（四）全面实施科教兴国战略和人才强国战略</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. Fully implementing the strategies of reinvigorating China through science and education and strengthening the nation through human resource development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育、科技和人才，是国家强盛、民族振兴的基石，也是综合国力的核心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Education, science, and human resources are the cornerstones of national prosperity and rejuvenation, and are also at the core of overall national strength.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优先发展教育事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give high priority to the development of education.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强国必先强教。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For a country to become strong, it must first strengthen education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>只有一流的教育，才能培养一流人才，建设一流国家。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First-class education is a prerequisite for cultivating high-caliber personnel and building a great country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要抓紧启动实施国家中长期教育改革和发展规划纲要。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promptly begin to implement the Outline of the National Medium-and Long-Term Program for Education Reform and Development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着重抓好五个方面：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on the following five areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是推进教育改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will advance education reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要解放思想，大胆突破，勇于创新，鼓励试验，对办学体制、教学内容、教育方法、评价制度等进行系统改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to emancipate our minds, boldly make breakthroughs and innovations, encourage experimentation, and carry out a systematic reform of the system for operating schools, curricula, teaching methods, and evaluation systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持育人为本，大力推进素质教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to give top priority to cultivating the integrity of students and vigorously promote well-rounded education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>探索适应不同类型教育和人才成长的学校管理体制和办学模式，提高办学和人才培养水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will explore systems of school management and ways of providing education that are suitable for different types of education and the development of people with different skills, so that we run schools better and turn out better graduates. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励社会力量兴办教育，满足群众多样化的教育需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage nongovernmental sectors to run schools in order to meet people's diverse demands for education.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是促进义务教育均衡发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will promote the balanced development of compulsory education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在合理布局的基础上，加快推进中西部地区初中校舍改造和全国中小学校舍安全工程，尽快使所有学校的校舍、设备和师资达到规定标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the basis of a rational allocation of resources, we will accelerate the renovation of junior secondary school buildings in the central and western regions. We will also accelerate implementation of the nationwide program for safe primary and secondary school buildings, and ensure that buildings, equipment and teaching staff in all schools reach established standards as soon as possible. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为农村中小学班级配备多媒体远程教学设备，让广大农村和偏远地区的孩子共享优质教育资源。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide multimedia distance learning facilities for rural primary and secondary schools so that children living in the vast rural and remote areas have access to quality education resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强学前教育和特殊教育学校建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve preschool education and develop special education schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大对少数民族和民族地区教育的支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase educational support for ethnic minorities and ethnic minority areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是继续加强职业教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will continue to strengthen vocational education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以就业为目标，整合教育资源，改进教学方式，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the goal of helping students find jobs, we will integrate education resources, improve teaching methods;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力培养学生的就业创业能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and focus on nurturing students' employability and entrepreneurial abilities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是推进高等学校管理体制和招生制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will reform the management and admissions systems of institutions of higher learning. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步落实高等学校办学自主权，鼓励高等学校适应就业和经济社会发展需要，调整专业和课程设置，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give them more decision-making power, encourage them to adjust their majors and curricula to meet employment needs and the needs of economic and social development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动高等学校人才培养、科技创新和学术发展紧密结合，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>more intimately integrate personnel training, scientific and technological innovation, and academic development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>激励教师专注于教育，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>inspire their teachers to concentrate on education;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力建设有特色、高水平大学。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and become high-level universities with their own distinctive features. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创建若干一流大学，培养杰出人才。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop a number of first-class universities that produce outstanding personnel. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政要加大对中西部高等教育发展的支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will increase support for the development of higher education in the central and western regions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是加强教师队伍建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we will improve the ranks of our teachers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从多方面采取措施，吸引优秀人才投身教育事业，鼓励他们终身从教。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take a variety of measures to attract outstanding personnel to pursue careers in education and devote their lives to it. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点加强农村义务教育学校教师和校长培训，鼓励优秀教师到农村贫困地区从教。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on strengthening training for teachers and principals of rural compulsory education schools, and encourage excellent teachers to teach in impoverished rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强师德教育，增强教师的责任感和使命感。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify education to improve the professional ethics of our teachers, and enhance their sense of responsibility and mission. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育寄托着亿万家庭对美好生活的期盼，关系着民族素质和国家未来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Hundreds of millions of families place their hopes for a better life on education, and education has a direct bearing on the quality of the nation and the future of the country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>不普及和提高教育，国家不可能强盛。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A country cannot become strong and prosperous if it does not make education universal and improve its quality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这个道理我们要永远铭记。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must always keep this in mind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展科学技术。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously develop science and technology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要认真贯彻自主创新的方针，全面推进创新型国家建设，加快实施科技重大专项。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to earnestly implement the policy of independent innovation, comprehensively build an innovative country, and accelerate the implementation of our major science and technology programs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力突破带动技术革命、促进产业振兴的关键科技问题，突破提高健康水平、保障改善民生的重大公益性科技问题，突破增强国际竞争力、维护国家安全的战略高技术问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to concentrate on making breakthroughs in key scientific and technological problems that can drive the technological revolution forward and promote industrial invigoration, in major scientific and technological problems related to public welfare that can improve people's health and the quality of their lives, and in problems in strategic, high-tech fields that can enhance our country's international competitiveness and safeguard our national security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>前瞻部署生物、纳米、量子调控、信息网络、气候变化、空天海洋等领域基础研究和前沿技术研究。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make farsighted arrangements for basic research and research in cutting-edge technologies in the fields of biology, nano science, quantum control, information networks, climate change, aerospace and oceanography. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化科技体制改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the system for managing science and technology;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力解决科技与经济脱节的问题，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>strive to bridge the gap between science and technology and the economy;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动以企业为主体、市场为导向、产学研相结合的技术创新体系建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>promote the development of a system of technological innovation in which enterprises play the leading role, the market provides orientation, and the efforts of enterprises, universities and research institutes are integrated;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进科技资源优化配置、开放共享和高效利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and promote optimal allocation, open sharing, and highly efficient use of scientific and technological resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要大力实施知识产权战略，加强知识产权创造、应用和保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously implement the strategy for intellectual property rights and strengthen the creation, application and protection of them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步激发广大科技工作者和全社会的创新活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further arouse the creativity of scientists, engineers and all of society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快人才资源开发。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of human resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人才是第一资源。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Talented personnel are the primary resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要统筹推进各类人才队伍建设，突出培养创新型科技人才、经济社会发展重点领域专门人才和高技能人才，积极引进海外高层次人才。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to develop all types of human resources in a coordinated and all-round way, with the focus on producing innovative scientists and engineers, and experts and professionals in key areas of economic and social development, and energetically attract high caliber personnel from overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全政府、社会、用人单位和个人等多元化的人才培养投入机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will set up a mechanism for diversifying funding for personnel training, so that the government, nongovernmental bodies, employers and employees all do their part.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分发挥市场配置人才资源的基础性作用，努力营造人才辈出、人尽其才的制度环境，建设人力资源强国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make full use of the basic role of market forces in allocating human resources, strive to create an institutional environment conducive to bringing forth talented people in large numbers and tapping their full potential, and make our country rich in human resources.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（五）大力加强文化建设</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Energetically promoting cultural progress</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家发展、民族振兴，不仅需要强大的经济力量，更需要强大的文化力量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To develop the country and rejuvenate the nation, we must not only be economically strong, but more importantly, be culturally strong. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>文化是一个民族的精神和灵魂，是一个民族真正有力量的决定性因素，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Culture is the spirit and soul of a nation, and the determining factor of whether it is truly strong or not.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>可以深刻影响一个国家发展的进程，改变一个民族的命运。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It can profoundly affect the progress of a country's development and change the destiny of a nation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>没有先进文化的发展，没有全民族文明素质的提高，就不可能真正实现现代化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>If we do not develop an advanced culture and improve the whole nation's cultural and ethical levels, we cannot truly modernize. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>解放思想、改革开放的时代精神，已经成为推动社会前进的先进文化力量，使中华民族充满生机与活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Emancipating our minds, and reform and opening up embody the spirit of our times, and they have become an advanced cultural force driving social progress and have filled the Chinese nation with vigor and vitality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们大力发展公益性文化事业，加快推进文化体制改革，加强公共文化服务体系建设，促进文化产业快速成长，繁荣文化市场，有效扩大了内需。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the past year, we vigorously developed non-profit cultural programs, sped up the reform of the cultural management system, improved the system of public cultural services, stimulated the rapid growth of our culture industry, brought prosperity to the culture market, and effectively expanded domestic demand. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，我们要更加重视和大力加强文化建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the new year, we need to pay greater attention to and vigorously promote cultural progress. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继承和弘扬中华民族优秀传统文化，吸收和借鉴世界各国文明成果，建设中华民族共有精神家园。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw upon and carry forward the fine traditional culture of the Chinese nation, draw on and make use of the achievements of the cultures of other countries, and build a home of spirit shared by the whole Chinese nation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府要更好地履行发展公益性文化事业的责任，保障人民群众的基本需求和权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our government needs to better carry out its responsibility for developing non-profit cultural programs and ensure that the people's basic demands are met and that their rights and interests are protected. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>文化基础设施建设和公共文化资源配置要向基层、特别是农村和中西部地区倾斜，推进美术馆、图书馆、文化馆、博物馆免费开放，丰富人民群众的精神文化生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give high priority to the primary, level, especially rural areas and the central and western regions in developing cultural infrastructure and allocating public cultural resources; make admission to more art galleries, libraries, cultural centers and museums free of charge; and enrich the people's intellectual and cultural lives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要继续推进文化体制改革，扶持公益性文化事业，发展文化产业，鼓励文化创新，培育骨干文化企业，生产更多健康向上的文化产品，满足人民群众多样化的文化需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reform the cultural management system, support non-profit cultural programs, develop the culture industry, encourage cultural innovation, foster leading cultural enterprises, and produce more healthy and inspirational cultural works to meet the diverse cultural needs of our people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进哲学社会科学、广播影视、新闻出版、档案事业发展，繁荣文学艺术创作，加强文物保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of philosophy, the social sciences, radio, television, film, the press, publishing, and archives; make literary and artistic creation flourish; and strengthen the protection of our cultural heritage. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极开展对外文化交流，增强中华文化国际影响力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously develop cultural exchanges with foreign countries, and make Chinese culture more influential internationally. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展公共体育事业，广泛开展全民健身运动，提高人民的身体素质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will energetically develop recreational sports, launch an extensive exercise campaign for the general public, and improve the people's health. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中华民族不仅能够创造经济奇迹，也一定能够创造新的文化辉煌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Chinese nation can not only create economic miracles but also make brilliant new cultural achievements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（六）着力保障和改善民生，促进社会和谐进步</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>6. Vigorously ensuring and improving people's wellbeing, and promoting social harmony and progress</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改善民生是经济发展的根本目的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Improving people's wellbeing is the fundamental goal of economic development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>只有着力保障和改善民生，经济发展才有持久的动力，社会进步才有牢固的基础，国家才能长治久安。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We can ensure that there is sustained impetus for economic development, a solid foundation for social progress, and lasting stability for the country only by working hard to ensure and improve people's wellbeing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>千方百计扩大就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do everything in our power to increase employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是保障和改善民生的头等大事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is the top priority in our work of ensuring and improving people's wellbeing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年就业形势依然严峻，工作上不能有丝毫松懈。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year the employment situation will still be serious, and we cannot slacken our efforts in the slightest. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要继续实施积极的就业政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to continue to implement a proactive employment policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政拟投入433亿元用于促进就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will allocate 43.3 billion yuan to stimulate employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点做好高校毕业生、农民工、就业困难人员就业和退伍转业军人就业安置工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Emphasis will be given to helping college graduates, rural migrant workers, people experiencing employment difficulty, and demobilized military personnel find jobs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>2009年到期的“五缓四减三补贴”就业扶持政策延长一年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The "five-four-three" employment support policies, originally scheduled to expire in 2009, will be extended for another year. [These policies allow qualified enterprises to postpone their payments of five types of social security contributions; reduce urban workers' contributions to four types of insurance funds, namely medical insurance, unemployment insurance, workers' compensation, and maternity insurance; and continue three types of subsidized, enterprise-based job training programs. - Tr.]</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强政策支持和就业指导，鼓励高校毕业生到城乡基层、中西部地区和中小企业就业；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase policy support and employment guidance to encourage college graduates to take community-level jobs in urban and rural areas, and jobs in the central and western regions and in small and medium-sized enterprises.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓宽就业、择业、创业渠道，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand channels for seeking employment and starting businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励自主创业、自谋职业等多种形式的灵活就业，以创业带动就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage different forms of flexible employment, including starting businesses and finding jobs independently. We will also encourage job growth through the creation of new businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全公共投资带动就业的机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish a sound mechanism for stimulating employment through public investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续加强职业技能培训，重点提高农民工和城乡新增劳动力的就业能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to strengthen vocational training, with the focus on increasing the employability of rural migrant workers and new members of the workforce in urban and rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善就业服务体系，健全劳动力输出输入地区协调协作机制，引导劳动力特别是农民工有序流动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the employment services system, strengthen coordination and cooperation between labor-exporting and labor-importing regions, and guide workers in an orderly flow, especially rural migrant workers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建立统一规范的人力资源市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of a unified and standardized human resources market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>维护劳动者合法权益，构建和谐的劳动关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will safeguard the lawful rights and interests of workers and establish harmonious labor relations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要通过持之以恒的努力，创造更多的就业机会，让广大劳动者各尽所能、各得其所。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work tirelessly to create more job opportunities and to enable workers to tap their full potential and find suitable jobs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快完善覆盖城乡居民的社会保障体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to improve the social security system for both urban and rural residents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进新型农村社会养老保险试点，试点范围扩大到23%的县。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move steadily forward with the pilot program for a new old-age insurance system for rural residents by expanding it to 23% of the country's counties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快解决未参保集体企业退休人员基本养老保障等遗留问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will act more quickly to solve longstanding problems, including the lack of basic old-age pensions for retirees of collectively owned enterprises that do not participate in group pension programs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>将全国130万“老工伤”人员全部纳入工伤保险范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Workers' compensation will be extended to all of the 1.3 million workers injured previous jobs who are not receiving benefits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推进农民工参加社会保险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to extend coverage of social security to rural migrant workers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强城乡低保工作，逐步提高保障水平，切实做到动态管理、应保尽保。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen our work concerning subsistence allowances in both urban and rural areas, gradually increase allowances, and ensure that they are managed in a manner that reflects changing conditions and that everyone who is entitled to such allowances receives them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强残疾人社会保障和服务体系建设，进一步落实好扶残助残的各项政策，为他们平等参与社会生活创造更好的环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work harder to build the social security and social services system for people with a disability, further implement policies for assisting and supporting them, and create a better environment for them to participate in social activities on an equal footing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>企业退休人员基本养老金今年再提高10%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase basic old-age pensions for enterprise retirees by 10%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要进一步增加社会保障投入，中央财政拟安排3185亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels need to spend more on social security, and the central government will appropriate 318.5 billion yuan for this purpose. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要多渠道增加全国社会保障基金，加强监管，实现保值增值。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase the country's social security funds through multiple channels and strengthen oversight and supervision to maintain and increase their value. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要加快构建更加完善的社会保障安全网，使人民生活有基本保障、无后顾之忧。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to build a better social safety net to provide basic security to people and free them from worries.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革收入分配制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform the income distribution system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>合理的收入分配制度是社会公平正义的重要体现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A rational income distribution system is an important manifestation of social fairness and justice. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们不仅要通过发展经济，把社会财富这个“蛋糕”做大，也要通过合理的收入分配制度把“蛋糕”分好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will not only make the "pie" of social wealth bigger by developing the economy, but also distribute it well on the basis of a rational income distribution system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持和完善按劳分配为主体、多种分配方式并存的分配制度，兼顾效率与公平，走共同富裕的道路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to uphold and improve the system in which distribution according to work is dominant and multiple forms of distribution coexist, give due consideration to efficiency and fairness, and take the path to common prosperity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一要抓紧制定调整国民收入分配格局的政策措施，逐步提高居民收入在国民收入分配中的比重，提高劳动报酬在初次分配中的比重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will promptly formulate policies and measures to adjust the distribution of national income, and gradually increase the proportion, of income individuals receive from the distribution of national income and the proportion of the primary distribution of income that goes to wages and salaries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大财政、税收在收入初次分配和再分配中的调节作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the role of fiscal and taxation policies in adjusting the primary and secondary distribution of income. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创造条件让更多群众拥有财产性收入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create conditions for more people to earn income from property.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二要深化垄断行业收入分配制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will deepen the reform of the income distribution system of monopoly industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善对垄断行业工资总额和工资水平的双重调控政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the policy of dual control over total payroll and wage scales in these industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格规范国有企业、金融机构经营管理人员特别是高管的收入，完善监管办法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will set strict standards for the income of executives, especially senior ones, of state-owned enterprises and financial institutions, and improve related oversight and supervision rules.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三要进一步规范收入分配秩序。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will further standardize the pattern of income distribution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决打击取缔非法收入，规范灰色收入，逐步形成公开透明、公正合理的收入分配秩序，坚决扭转收入差距扩大的趋势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will firmly crack down on and ban illegal income; regulate off-the-books income; gradually form a transparent, fair and rational pattern of income distribution; and resolutely reverse the widening income gap.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进房地产市场平稳健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the steady and sound development of the real estate market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚决遏制部分城市房价过快上涨势头，满足人民群众的基本住房需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will resolutely curb the precipitous rise of housing prices in some cities and satisfy people's basic need for housing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是继续大规模实施保障性安居工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will continue to carry out low-income housing projects on a large scale. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政拟安排保障性住房专项补助资金632亿元，比上年增加81亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will allocate 63.2 billion yuan for low-income housing, an increase of 8.1 billion yuan over last year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设保障性住房300万套，各类棚户区改造住房280万套。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build 3 million housing units for low-income families and renovate 2.8 million housing units in run-down areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大农村危房改造试点范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the pilot program for renovating dilapidated houses in rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要切实负起责任，严格执行年度建设计划，确保土地、资金和优惠政策落实到位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels must genuinely take responsibility to ensure that the annual construction plan is strictly carried out and that policies concerning land, funding, and preferential treatment are implemented well.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是继续支持居民自住性住房消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will continue to support the purchase of homes to be used as their owners' residences. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加中低价位、中小套型普通商品房用地供应，加快普通商品房项目审批和建设进度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase the land supply for building small and medium-sized condominiums to be sold at low and medium price levels, and expedite the approval procedure for and construction of such housing projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>规范发展二手房市场，倡导住房租赁消费。盘活住房租赁市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will standardize and develop the market for used homes, encourage home renting, and stimulate rental housing market.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是抑制投机性购房。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will rein in speculative housing purchases. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大差别化信贷、税收政策执行力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify the implementation of differentiated credit and tax policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善商品房预售制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the advance purchase system for commodity housing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是大力整顿和规范房地产市场秩序。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will work to rectify and standardize the real estate market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善土地收入管理使用办法，抑制土地价格过快上涨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the methods for managing and using income from land, and keep land prices from rising too fast. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大对圈地不建、捂盘惜售、哄抬房价等违法违规行为的查处力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make greater efforts to deal with violations of laws and regulations such as keeping land unused, property hoarding, and price rigging.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进医药卫生事业改革发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the reform and development of the pharmaceutical and healthcare fields. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极稳妥推进医药卫生体制改革，全面落实五项重点工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively yet prudently carry forward the reform of the pharmaceutical and healthcare systems, and comprehensively accomplish five key tasks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续扩大基本医疗保障覆盖面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to expand the coverage of guaranteed basic medical care. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要把城镇居民基本医保和新农合的财政补助标准提高到120元，比上年增长50%，并适当提高个人缴费标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year we will raise government subsidies on basic medical insurance for non-working urban residents and on the new type of rural cooperative medical care system to 120 yuan per person per year, up 50% over last year, and appropriately increase rates for individual contributions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展农村儿童白血病、先天性心脏病医疗保障试点，尽力为这些不幸的儿童和家庭提供更多帮助。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out a pilot program for ensuring that rural children with leukemia or congenital heart disease receive medical treatment and provide more assistance to these less fortunate children and their families. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在60％政府举办的基层医疗卫生机构实施基本药物制度，其他医疗机构也要优先选用基本药物。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will install the basic drug system in 60% of community medical institutions and urge other medical institutions to give high priority to the use of basic drugs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进基本药物集中采购和统一配送。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the centralized purchase and unified distribution of basic drugs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>基本完成城乡基层医疗卫生机构建设规划，大规模开展适宜人才培养和培训。进一步完善支持村卫生室建设和乡村医生发展的政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will basically complete the plan for building community medical institutions in urban and rural areas, undertake personnel education and training on a large scale, and further improve the policies and measures for supporting the development of village clinics and rural doctors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善基层医疗卫生机构补偿机制，落实岗位绩效工资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the mechanism for subsidizing community medical institutions and link salaries to performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展社区首诊试点，推动形成基层医疗卫生机构和医院功能区分合理、协作配合、互相转诊的服务体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out a pilot program for making community medical institutions the first option in medical treatment and work to create a service system in which hospitals and community medical institutions (each with its own well-defined functions) coordinate and collaborate with each other and refer cases to each other. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实加强甲型H1N1流感等重大传染病防控和慢性病、职业病、地方病防治，提高突发公共卫生事件应急处置能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen prevention and control of influenza A (H1N1) and other major communicable diseases as well as chronic, occupational, and endemic diseases, and enhance our ability to handle public health emergencies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展公立医院改革试点，坚持基本医疗的公益性方向，创新体制机制，充分调动医务人员积极性，提高服务质量，控制医疗费用，改善医患关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out a pilot reform of public hospitals; maintain the non profit nature of bask medical services; make institutional and procedural innovations; boost the morale of medical workers; raise the quality of service; control medical costs; and improve relations between medical service providers and consumers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力支持社会资本兴办医疗卫生机构，在服务准入、医保定点等方面一视同仁。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will energetically support the use of non-government capital to run medical and healthcare institutions, and such institutions will be treated the same as public hospitals in obtaining operating licenses and providing medical services covered by the public medical insurance system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扶持和促进中医药、民族医药事业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support and promote the development of traditional Chinese medicine and folk medicines of ethnic minorities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>医药卫生事业改革发展关系人民身体健康和家庭幸福，我们要克服一切困难，把这个世界性难题解决好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The reform and development of the pharmaceutical and healthcare fields affects the health of the people and the happiness of their families; therefore, we must overcome all difficulties and solve this universal problem.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好人口和计划生育工作。继续稳定低生育水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do a good job in population and family planning work We will continue to maintain a low birthrate. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好流动人口计划生育服务工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide good family planning services for the floating population. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实好农村妇女妇科疾病定期检查和住院分娩补助政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide regular gynecological examinations and subsidize hospital childbirths for rural women. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强出生缺陷干预，开展免费孕前优生健康检查试点，做好孕产妇和婴幼儿保健工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen intervention in birth defects; carry out a pilot program of free pre-pregnancy checkups; and provide quality health services for infants, pre-school children, and prenatal and nursing women. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施农村部分计划生育家庭奖励扶助制度和西部地区少生快富工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reward and support eligible rural families that comply with family planning regulations, and carry out the "lower birthrate equals faster prosperity" project in the western region. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实保护好妇女和未成年人权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take effective measures to protect the rights and interests of women and minors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强应对人口老龄化战略研究，加快建立健全养老社会服务体系，让老年人安享晚年生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify strategic research on coping with an aging population and move more quickly to create a sound system of old-age services so that people can live a happy life in their old age.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（七）坚定不移推进改革，进一步扩大开放</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Firmly advancing reform and further expanding opening up</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要继续深化重点领域和关键环节改革，努力实现新的突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year we will continue to deepen reform in key areas and crucial links and work hard to achieve new breakthroughs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要继续推进国有经济布局和结构战略性调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to make strategic adjustments in the distribution and structure of the state-owned sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快大型国有企业特别是中央企业母公司的公司制改革，实现产权多元化，完善法人治理结构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up the reform to introduce the corporate system in large state-owned enterprises, especially parent companies of enterprises under the central government, and we will diversify their ownership and improve their corporate governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进垄断性行业改革，推进公用事业改革，切实放宽市场准入，积极引入竞争机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the reform of monopoly industries; promote reforms in public utilities; effectively expand market access; and actively introduce competitive mechanisms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力营造多种所有制经济公平竞争的市场环境，更好地促进非公有制经济发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create a market environment for fair competition among economic entities under diverse forms of ownership and facilitate stronger growth of the non-public sector.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化资源性产品价格和环保收费改革，作为节约能源资源、保护环境、实现可持续发展的重要举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of prices for resource products and environmental protection charges. This is an important measure for conserving energy and resources, protecting the environment, and achieving sustainable development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要扩大用电大户与发电企业直接交易试点，推行居民用电用水阶梯价格制度，健全可再生能源发电定价和费用分摊机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the trial of direct transactions between major electricity consumers and producers; introduce tiered prices for household consumption of electricity and water; and improve the mechanism of price setting and cost sharing for electricity generated from renewable energy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善农业用水价格政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the pricing policy for water used in apiculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革污水处理、垃圾处理收费制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform the system of sewage and garbage treatment charges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大排污权交易试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the trial of pollution rights trading. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在推进这些改革中要注意协调好各方面利益关系，决不能让低收入群众的基本生活受到影响。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While pushing forward these reforms, we will balance the interests of different parties and ensure that the basic living conditions of people with low incomes are not adversely affected.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要继续推进财税体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reform the fiscal and taxation systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全公共财政体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the public finance system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善财政转移支付制度，加大一般性转移支付，增强地方政府提供基本公共服务的能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the system of transfer payments, increase general transfer payments, and enhance the ability of local governments to provide basic public services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全省以下财政管理体制，完善县级基本财力保障机制，推进省直管县财政管理方式改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the fiscal management system at and below the provincial level, set up a mechanism to ensure basic funding for county governments, and carry forward reforms that place county finances directly under the management of provincial governments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面编制中央和地方政府性基金预算，试编社会保险基金预算，完善国有资本经营预算制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw up budgets for all funds controlled by central and local governments, prepare budgets for social security funds on a trial basis, and improve the budget system for the use of state capital. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续做好增值税转型工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to make progress in VAT reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进资源税改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry forward the reform of resource taxes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统一内外资企业和个人城建税、教育费附加制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will extend the urban construction and maintenance tax and education surcharges to foreign enterprises and nationals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全金融体系是应对国际金融危机冲击的重要举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Improving the financial system is an important measure for countering the impact of the global financial crisis. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要继续完善国有控股金融机构公司治理，改善经营管理机制，提高风险管控能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve corporate governance in financial institutions in which the state holds a controlling stake, improve their business management, and raise their ability to manage and control risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推动政策性金融机构改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue the reform of policy-based financial institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推进资产管理公司转型。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will steadily promote the transformation of asset management companies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化农村信用社改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of rural credit cooperatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动中小金融机构规范发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote orderly development of small and medium-sized financial institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展金融市场，鼓励金融创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously develop the financial market and encourage financial innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进跨境贸易人民币结算试点，逐步发展境外人民币金融业务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote pilot projects for the use of the renminbi in cross-border trade, and gradually develop overseas financial activities using the renminbi. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进存款保险制度建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue building the deposit insurance system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快发展农业保险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up the development of agricultural insurance.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要按照政事分开、事企分开和管办分离的要求，在科学分类的基础上，积极稳妥推进事业单位改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively yet prudently push forward the reform of institutions on the basis of scientific classifications and in accordance with the requirements that government and business functions be spun off from institutions, and that supervision be separated from day-to-day operations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们的改革是全面的改革，包括经济体制改革、政治体制改革以及其他各领域的改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The reforms we are undertaking, including economic and political restructuring and reforms in other areas, are comprehensive. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>没有政治体制改革，经济体制改革和现代化建设就不可能成功。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Without political restructuring, it would not be possible for economic restructuring and the modernization drive to succeed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要发展社会主义民主，切实保障人民当家作主的民主权利，特别是选举权、知情权、参与权、表达权和监督权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop socialist democracy, and effectively safeguard the democratic rights of the people as masters of the country, particularly their rights to vote and to stay informed about, participate and in, express views on, and oversee government affairs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步扩大基层民主，健全基层自治组织和民主管理制度，让广大群众更好地参与管理基层公共事务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further expand primary-level democracy, strengthen primary-level self-governing bodies, and improve the system of democratic administration at the primary level so that the people can better participate in the management of local public affairs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持依法治国、依法行政。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold the rule of law and continue to run the government in accordance with the law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步健全法制，特别要重视那些规范和监督权力运行的法律制度建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further improve the legal system, particularly laws concerning the standardization and oversight of the exercise of power. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新政府立法工作的方法和机制，扩大立法工作的公众参与。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will innovatively revise the methods and mechanisms of the government's legislative Work and expand public participation in it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要全面适应国际形势变化和国内发展要求，拓展对外开放的广度和深度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully adapt to changes in the international situation, meet the needs of domestic development, and expand the breadth and depth of opening up.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定发展对外贸易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will steadily develop foreign trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年的主要着力点是拓市场、调结构、促平衡。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year the main focus is on opening new markets and adjusting the structure of and promoting balance in foreign trade.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持实施市场多元化战略和以质取胜战略，落实和完善出口退税、出口信贷、出口信用保险等各项政策措施，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adhere to the strategy of diversifying markets and the strategy of competing on quality; implement and improve policies and measures on export tax rebates, export credit, and export credit insurance;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续改善海关、质检、外汇等方面的服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and continue to improve services related to customs, quality inspection, and foreign exchange. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>巩固传统市场，大力开拓新兴市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen traditional markets and vigorously develop new markets. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化出口产品结构，稳定劳动密集型产品出口，扩大机电产品和高新技术产品出口，大力发展服务贸易和服务外包，努力培育出口品牌和营销网络，继续严格控制“两高一资”产品出口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the export mix;stabilize exports of labor-intensive products; increase exports of electromechanical products as well as new-and high-technology products; energetically develop trade in services and service outsourcing; strive to cultivate exports of brand-name products and develop marketing networks and continue to strictly limit exports of resource products and products whose production consumes large quantities of energy and resources or is highly polluting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推进加工贸易转型升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will vigorously promote the transformation and upgrading of the processing trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进进出口平衡发展，重点扩大先进技术装备、关键零部件和国内紧缺物资进口，稳定各项进口促进政策和便利化措施，敦促发达国家放宽高新技术产品出口限制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the balanced development of imports and exports; focus on increasing imports of advanced technology and equipment, key spare parts, and goods in short supply domestically; keep all policies and measures for promoting and facilitating imports stable; and urge developed countries to ease export restrictions on new-and high-technology products to China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动利用外资和对外投资协调发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote coordination between using other countries' investment in China and making Chinese investment overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化利用外资结构，鼓励外资投向高端制造业、高新技术产业、现代服务业、新能源和节能环保产业，鼓励跨国公司在华设立地区总部等各类功能性机构，鼓励中外企业加强研发合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will optimize the utilization of foreign investment; encourage more foreign investment in high-end manufacturing, new-and high-technology industries, modern service industries, and the new energy, energy-conservation and environmental protection industries; encourage multinational corporations to set up regional headquarters and other functional agencies in China; and encourage Chinese and foreign enterprises to strengthen cooperation in R&amp;D. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励外资参与国内企业改组改造和兼并重组，加快建立外资并购安全审查制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the use of foreign investment for restructuring, upgrading, merging, and reorganizing Chinese companies, and quickly establish a security review system for mergers and acquisitions involving foreign investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进“引资”与“引智”相结合。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to attract both investment and talent from overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导外资向中西部地区转移和增加投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide foreign investors to transfer and increase their investments to the central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快实施“走出去”战略，鼓励符合国外市场需求的行业有序向境外转移产能，支持有条件的企业开展海外并购，深化境外资源互利合作，提高对外承包工程和劳务合作的质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the implementation of the "go global" strategy; encourage Chinese industries whose products are in demand in foreign markets to transfer their production capacity overseas in an orderly manner; support qualified enterprises to carry out overseas mergers and acquisitions; deepen mutually beneficial cooperation concerning foreign resources; and improve the quality of overseas contracted projects and labor service cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步简化各类审批手续，落实企业境外投资自主权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further simplify examination and approval procedures, and give enterprises decision-making power over their overseas investments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“走出去”的企业要依法经营，规避风险，防止恶性竞争，维护国家整体利益和良好形象。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Enterprises that have "gone global" should operate in accordance with the law, avoid risks, prevent vicious competition, and safeguard the country's overall interests and good image.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化多边双边经贸合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen multilateral and bilateral business cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强和改善与发达国家的经贸关系，深化与发展中国家的互利合作，认真落实中非务实合作八项新举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen and improve business ties with developed countries, deepen mutually beneficial cooperation with other developing countries, and conscientiously implement the eight new policy measures for China's pragmatic cooperation with African countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥经济高层对话和双边经贸联委会作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make full use of the role of high-level economic dialogue and bilateral economic and trade joint commissions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快自由贸易区建设步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will quicken the pace of establishing free trade zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极参与多哈回合谈判，推动早日达成更加合理、平衡的谈判结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively 'participate in the Doha round of trade talks to reach a more reasonable and balanced outcome as early as possible. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>反对各种形式的保护主义，妥善处理贸易摩擦。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will oppose protectionism in all forms and properly handle trade frictions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>上海世博会即将拉开帷幕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Shanghai World Expo will open soon. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要加强与各参展国家、地区和国际组织的合作，把上海世博会办成一届成功、精彩、难忘的盛会，办成一届促进人类文明进步，促进科技创新，促进我国与世界各国交流合作、共同发展的盛会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen cooperation with all participating countries, regions, and international organizations to make the Expo a successful, spectacular, and unforgettable event, and one that promotes the progress of human civilization, scientific and technological innovation, and exchanges and cooperation between, and common development of China and other countries of the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（八）努力建设人民满意的服务型政府</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>8. Working hard to build a service-oriented government that the people are satisfied with</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，政府自身改革和建设取得新进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the past year, new progress was made in government self-reform and self-development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为应对各种困难，我们特别注意发扬民主、倾听基层群众意见，重视维护群众利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To deal with difficulties of all kinds, we paid particular attention to promoting democracy, listening to the opinions of the masses, and protecting their interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广大公务员兢兢业业、勤勉尽责，为保增长、保民生、保稳定作出了积极贡献。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our civil servants are devoted, diligent and responsible, and they made positive contributions to sustaining economic growth and ensuring people's well-being and maintaining stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>但是政府工作与人民的期望还有较大差距。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Nevertheless, the government's work still fell considerably short of public expectations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>职能转变不到位，对微观经济干预过多，社会管理和公共服务比较薄弱；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The transformation of government functions is incomplete; there is too much government interference in the micro-economy, and public administration and services are relatively weak.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些工作人员依法行政意识不强；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some government employees give too little consideration to carrying out their official duties in accordance with the law;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些领导干部脱离群众、脱离实际，形式主义、官僚主义严重；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>some leading cadres are divorced from reality and the masses, and are excessively formalistic and bureaucratic;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些领域腐败现象易发多发。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and some areas are prone to corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要以转变职能为核心，深化行政管理体制改革，大力推进服务型政府建设，努力为各类市场主体创造公平的发展环境，为人民群众提供良好的公共服务，维护社会公平正义。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the focus on transforming government functions, we will deepen reform of the administrative system, work hard to make the government devoted to service, strive to create a fair development environment for all types of market entities, deliver quality public services to the masses, and uphold social fairness and justice.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要全面正确履行政府职能，更加重视公共服务和社会管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully and properly perform government functions and attach greater importance to public services and administration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快健全覆盖全民的公共服务体系，全面增强基本公共服务能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will quickly improve the public service system with full coverage for all, and comprehensively improve our ability to provide basic public services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全重大自然灾害、突发公共安全事件应急处理机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the mechanisms for responding to major natural disasters and emergencies that threaten public safety. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强防灾减灾能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve our ability to prevent and mitigate natural disasters. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强食品药品质量监管，做好安全生产工作，遏制重特大事故发生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the oversight and supervision of food and drug quality. We will ensure workplace safety and reduce the occurrence of major accidents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要适应新形势，推进社会管理体制改革和创新，合理调节社会利益关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to adapt to new circumstances, promote reform and innovation in the public administration system, and properly adjust the relationships between different interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真解决企业改制、征地拆迁、环境保护、劳动争议、涉法涉诉等领域损害群众利益的突出问题，保障人民群众的合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will earnestly deal with serious infringements on the interests of the people related to conversion of enterprises to a stockholding system, land expropriation, housing demolition and resident relocation, environmental protection, labor disputes, and legal and litigation issues in order to safeguard the people's lawful rights and interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强和改进信访工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the handling of public complaints lodged via letters or visits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改善流动人口管理和服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve supervision of and services for the floating population. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强社会治安综合治理，着力解决突出治安问题，防范和依法严厉打击各类违法犯罪活动，维护国家安全和社会稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen all facets of public security, focus on resolving serious public security issues, and guard against and severely crack down on crimes of all sorts in accordance with the law in order to safeguard national security and social stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要努力提高执行力和公信力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to improve our executive ability and earn greater public trust. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持决策的科学化、民主化，使各项政策更加符合实际、经得起检验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to make decision making more scientific and democratic, and ensure that all of our policies are more suitable to conditions and can stand the test of time. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对政策执行情况的检查监督，做到令行禁止。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen inspection and oversight of policy implementation and ensure that all orders are carried out and all prohibitions are observed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化行政问责，对失职渎职、不作为和乱作为的，要严肃追究责任。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen administrative accountability. All persons who are derelict in their duty, fail to do their jobs or do them irresponsibly will be held fully accountable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地区、各部门对中央的决策部署要执行有力，绝不允许各自为政。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All localities and departments must implement the decisions and arrangements of the central leadership effectively, and they may never go their own way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级行政机关及其公务员要自觉遵守宪法和法律，严格依法行政。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government agencies at all levels and their civil servants must conscientiously abide by the Constitution and laws and carry out their administrative duties in strict accordance with the law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实改进行政执法工作，努力做到规范执法、公正执法、文明执法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively improve law enforcement in government administration and work to ensure that laws are enforced in a standard, fair and civil manner. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建立健全决策、执行、监督相互制约又相互协调的行政运行机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the establishment of a sound operating mechanism for government administration, one that allows decision making, enforcement, and oversight departments to restrain and coordinate with each other.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要把反腐倡廉建设摆在重要位置，这直接关系政权的巩固。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give high priority to fighting corruption and encouraging integrity. This has a direct bearing on the firmness of our grip on political power. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级领导干部特别是高级干部要坚决执行中央关于报告个人经济和财产，包括收入、住房、投资，以及配偶子女从业等重大事项的规定，并自觉接受纪检部门的监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Leading cadres at all levels, especially high-ranking ones, must resolutely implement the central leadership's regulations on reporting the main facts concerning their personal financial situations and property, including their incomes, housing and investments, as well as the jobs of their spouses and children, and willingly accept the oversight of departments for discipline inspection. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要把查处违法违纪大案要案，作为反腐败的重要任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make investigating and prosecuting major violations of the law and discipline an important task in the fight against corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分发挥监察、审计部门的作用，加强对行政权力运行的监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will get supervision and auditing departments to fully play their role in strengthening oversight of the exercise of administrative power. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要建立健全惩治和预防腐败体系的各项制度，特别要健全公共资源配置、公共资产交易、公共产品生产等领域的管理制度，增强制度约束力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create a sound body of regulations to prevent and punish corruption, particularly administrative regulations concerning the allocation of public resources, trade in public assets, and the production of public goods, and we will also enhance their binding force. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持勤俭行政，反对铺张浪费，不断降低行政成本。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will run the government diligently and frugally, oppose extravagance and waste, and constantly reduce administrative costs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格控制楼堂馆所建设，禁止高档装修办公楼，加快公务接待、公车使用等制度改革，从严控制公费出国出境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strictly control the construction of office buildings for Party and government bodies, prohibit extravagant remodeling of their office buildings, accelerate the reform of regulations concerning official receptions and the use of official cars, and firmly restrict the use of public funds for traveling abroad. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实精简会议和文件，特别要减少那些形式重于内容的会议、庆典和论坛。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively reduce the number of meetings and documents, particularly meetings, celebrations, and forums that are long on form and short on content. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要深入推进政务公开，完善各类公开办事制度和行政复议制度，创造条件让人民批评政府、监督政府，同时充分发挥新闻舆论的监督作用，让权力在阳光下运行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote transparency of administrative affairs, improve regulations for transparent governance and administrative review, create conditions for the people to criticize and oversee the government, let the news media fully play their oversight role, and exercise power openly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们所做的一切都是要让人民生活得更加幸福、更有尊严，让社会更加公正、更加和谐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Everything we do we do to ensure that the people live a happier life with more dignity and to make our society fairer and more harmonious.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进民族团结，实现共同进步，是中华民族的生命、力量和希望所在。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Chinese nation's life, strength and hope lie in promoting solidarity achieving common progress of our ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要巩固和发展平等、团结、互助、和谐的社会主义民族关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must consolidate and develop socialist ethnic relations based on equality, unity, mutual assistance, and harmony. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真落实中央支持少数民族和民族地区发展的政策措施，优先支持边疆民族地区加快发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will conscientiously implement the policies and measures of the central leadership to support development of ethic minorities and ethnic minority areas, and give high priority to supporting acceleration of the development of ethnic minority border areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快完成边境一线地区危旧房改造，实施游牧民定居工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate renovation of dilapidated buildings along our borders, and build permanent housing for nomads. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新型农村社会养老保险要优先在边境县、民族地区贫困县试点。加大扶持人口较少民族发展力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pilot programs for the new system of old-age insurance for rural residents need to be launched first in border counties and poverty-stricken counties in ethnic minority areas, will increase our support for the development of ethnic groups with small populations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进兴边富民行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to bring prosperity to border areas and the people who live there. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重视保护少数民族文化遗产和民族地区生态环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give high priority to protecting the cultural heritage of ethnic minorities and the ecosystems in ethnic minority areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实做好少数民族流动人口公共服务、就业和管理工作，保障他们的合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do a good job in our work concerning public services and employment for and supervision of floating populations from ethnic minorities, and protect their lawful rights and interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时，加强国家意识、公民意识教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addition, we will cultivate national consciousness and the sense of citizenship. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要旗帜鲜明地反对民族分裂，维护祖国统一，让少数民族和民族地区各族群众充分感受到祖国大家庭的温暖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to take a clear-cut stand against attempts to split the nation, safeguard national unity, and get ethnic minorities and the people of all ethnic groups who live in ethnic minority areas to feel the warmth of the motherland as one large family.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要全面贯彻党的宗教工作基本方针，依法管理宗教事务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the Party's basic policies on religious work, and manage religious affairs in accordance with the law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥宗教界人士和信教群众在促进经济发展和社会和谐中的积极作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will get religious figures and religious believers to fully play their role in promoting economic development and social harmony.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要认真贯彻党的侨务政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will earnestly implement the Party's policy on overseas Chinese affairs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>维护海外侨胞、归侨侨眷的合法权益，支持他们传承中华文化，参与祖国现代化建设和促进和平统一大业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will safeguard the lawful rights and interests of overseas Chinese and returned overseas Chinese and their relatives, and support them in passing on Chinese culture, participating in the motherland's modernization, and promoting the great cause of peaceful reunification.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，国防和军队现代化建设取得新的成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year further achievements were made in the modernization of national defense mid the People's Liberation Army (PLA). </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民解放军和武警部队圆满完成国庆首都阅兵、重点地区维稳等重大任务，为维护国家安全和发展利益发挥了重要作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The PLA and the People's Armed Police Force completed the major tasks of staging the National Day military parade in the capital and safeguarding stability in key areas, and played an important role in safeguarding the country's security and development interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，要紧紧围绕党和国家工作大局，着眼全面履行新世纪新阶段军队历史使命，按照革命化现代化正规化相统一的原则，加强军队全面建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we need to focus on the overall work of the Party and government and strengthen all aspects of the army in accordance with the principle of making it more revolutionary, modem, and standardized, so that it can complete its missions in this new stage and this new century. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以增强打赢信息化条件下局部战争能力为核心，提高应对多种安全威胁、完成多样化军事任务的能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will concentrate on making the army better able to win informationized local wars, and will enhance its ability to respond to multiple security threats and accomplish a diverse array of military tasks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力加强军队思想政治建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to strengthen the army ideologically and politically. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快全面建设现代后勤步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the comprehensive development of a modem military logistics system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强国防科研和武器装备建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify R&amp;D on national defense and the development of weapons and equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法治军、从严治军，提高军队正规化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will run the army strictly and in accordance with the law and make it more standardized. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极稳妥地深化国防和军队改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively yet prudently deepen reform of national defense and the army. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强武警部队现代化建设，增强执勤、处置突发事件、反恐、维稳能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will modernize improve the armed police force, and make it better able to carry out its duties, respond to emergencies, combat terrorism and safeguard stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强国防动员和后备力量建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen our national defense mobilization and reserve forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要一如既往地关心支持国防和军队建设，巩固和发展军政军民团结。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels should, as always, care about and support the strengthening of national defense and the army, and consolidate and develop unity between the army and the government as well as between the army and the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们将坚定不移地贯彻“一国两制”、“港人治港”、“澳人治澳”、高度自治的方针，全力支持香港、澳门保持长期繁荣稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will unswervingly implement the principle of "one country, two systems," under which the people of Hong Kong administer Hong Kong, and the people of Macao administer Macao both with a high degree of autonomy, and fully support Hong Kong and Macao in maintaining long-term prosperity and stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持香港巩固并提升国际金融、贸易、航运中心地位，发展优势产业，培育新的经济增长点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support Hong Kong in consolidating and elevating its position as an international financial, trade, and shipping center; developing industries with local advantages; and fostering new areas of economic growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持澳门发展旅游休闲产业，促进经济适度多元化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support Macao in developing its tourism and leisure industry and appropriately diversifying its economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要认真实施珠江三角洲地区改革发展规划纲要，积极推进港珠澳大桥等大型跨境基础设施建设和珠海横琴岛开发，深化粤港澳合作，密切内地与港澳的经济联系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will conscientiously implement the Outline of the Program for Reform and Development of the Pearl River Delta, vigorously promote the construction of the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge and other major cross-boundary infrastructure projects as well as the development of Zhuhai's Hengqin Island, deepen cooperation between Guangdong and the Hong Kong and Macao regions, and increase economic ties between the mainland and these two regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>伟大祖国永远是香港、澳门的坚强后盾。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The great motherland will remain a staunch supporter of Hong Kong and Macao forever. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>只要特别行政区政府与各界人士同心协力，包容共济，共同维护繁荣稳定发展的大局，香港、澳门的明天一定会更加美好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As long as the governments of the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions and their people from all walks of life work together; accommodate and help each other; and jointly safeguard overall prosperity, stability, and development, Hong Kong and Macao will enjoy a brighter future.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去的一年，两岸关系在新的历史起点上取得重要进展，呈现和平发展良好势头。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year relations between the two sides of the Taiwan Straits made important progress from a historic new starting point, and a positive trend toward peaceful development emerged. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>两岸交流合作不断深入，全面直接双向“三通”得以实现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Cross-Straits exchanges and cooperation constantly deepened, and complete, direct, two-way mail, transport and trade links were established. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济关系正常化迈出重要步伐，经济合作制度化建设逐步推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took important steps to normalize cross-Straits economic relations, and economic cooperation between the two sides gradually became institutionalized. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>两岸关系持续改善和发展，给两岸同胞带来了实实在在的利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The constant improvement and development of cross-Straits relations brought real benefits to our compatriots on both sides.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在新的一年里，我们要继续坚持发展两岸关系、促进祖国和平统一的大政方针，牢牢把握两岸关系和平发展的主题，不断开创两岸关系和平发展新局面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the new year, we will continue to adhere to the principle of developing cross-Straits relations and promoting peaceful reunification of the motherland, firmly embrace the theme of peaceful development of cross-Straits relations and constantly create new conditions for it. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>密切两岸经贸金融交往，深化产业合作，支持在大陆的台资企业发展，维护台胞合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen economic, trade, and financial contacts between the two sides; deepen industrial cooperation; support the development of Taiwan-funded enterprises on the mainland; and safeguard the lawful rights and interests of our Taiwan compatriots. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励有条件的大陆企业赴台投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage qualified mainland enterprises to invest in Taiwan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持海峡西岸经济区在两岸交流合作中发挥先行先试作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the economic zone in Fujian Province on the west coast of the Straits in playing its role in pioneering new approaches to exchanges and cooperation between the two sides. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>通过商签两岸经济合作框架协议，促进互利共赢，建立具有两岸特色的经济合作机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote a win-win situation, set up an economic cooperation mechanism that reflects the characteristics of both sides by negotiating and signing an economic cooperation framework agreement (ECEA). </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓展文化教育交流，共同弘扬中华文化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand cultural and educational exchanges, and work with Taiwan to promote Chinese culture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强两岸民众和社会各界交流，共同分享两岸关系和平发展成果，进一步凝聚推动两岸关系和平发展的共识。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase exchanges between people from all sectors of society on both sides, so that everyone can share in the fruits of the peaceful development of cross-Straits relations and more fully realize the importance of promoting peaceful development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持大陆和台湾同属一个中国，巩固两岸关系和平发展的政治基础，增强两岸政治互信。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold the principle that the mainland and Taiwan belong to one and the same China, strengthen the political foundation for the peaceful development of cross-Straits relations, and enhance mutual political trust between the two sides. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们坚信，全体中华儿女同心协力，祖国完全统一的宏伟大业一定能够实现！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We firmly believe that with the concerted efforts of the Chinese people, we will achieve the complete reunification of the motherland.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去的一年，外交工作取得新的重大成绩。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We achieved new, important results in our diplomatic work last year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国积极参加应对国际金融危机、气候变化等国际合作，在一系列重大多边会议上发挥了独特的建设性作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We actively participated in international cooperation to respond to the global financial crisis and climate change, and played a unique, constructive role in a series of major multilateral conferences. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们积极开展全方位外交，与各大国、周边国家和广大发展中国家的对话合作稳步推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We energetically carried out all-round diplomacy, and made steady progress in dialogue and cooperation with major powers, neighboring countries, and developing countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力加强人文等领域外交。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We greatly strengthened diplomacy in all fields, including cultural diplomacy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有效维护我国公民和法人在海外的合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We effectively safeguarded the lawful rights and interests of Chinese nationals and corporations overseas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新中国外交走过了60年光辉历程，在国际舞台上留下了闪光足迹。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With a splendid, 60-year diplomatic history, New China has left shining footprints on the international stage. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们将继续发扬光荣传统，始终高举和平、发展、合作旗帜，坚持独立自主的和平外交政策，坚持走和平发展道路，奉行互利共赢的开放战略，推动建设持久和平、共同繁荣的和谐世界，为我国现代化建设创造良好的外部环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry forward our fine traditions; always hold high the banner of peace, development, and cooperation; adhere to an independent foreign policy of peace and the path of peaceful development; pursue an open strategy of mutual benefit; promote the building of a harmonious world with durable peace and common prosperity; and create a favorable external environment for China's modernization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，我们将继续以20国集团金融峰会等重大多边活动为主要平台，积极参与国际体系变革进程，维护发展中国家利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the new year, we will continue to use the G20 financial summit and other major multilateral activities as our main platforms for actively participating in the process of change in the international system and safeguarding the interests of developing countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹协调好双边外交与多边外交、国别区域外交与各领域外交工作，推动我国与各大国、周边国家和发展中国家的关系全面深入发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make overall plans for coordinating bilateral and multilateral diplomacy as well as diplomacy with individual countries and regions and in various fields, and promote further, comprehensive development of our relations with major powers, neighboring countries, and developing countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>紧紧抓住中国－东盟自贸区全面建成、上海合作组织召开峰会等契机，积极推进区域合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take advantage of the opportunities offered by the completion of the ASEAN-China free trade zone and the Shanghai Cooperation Organization summit to actively promote regional cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步做好应对气候变化、能源资源合作等方面的对外工作，在妥善解决热点问题和全球性问题中发挥建设性作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to carry out diplomatic work in climate change, energy and resource cooperation, and other areas, and play a constructive role in finding proper solutions to hot issues and global problems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国政府和人民愿与国际社会携手努力，共同应对风险挑战，共同分享发展机遇，为世界和平与发展作出新贡献！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Chinese government and people stand ready to work with the international community to respond to risks and challenges, share development opportunities, and make new contributions to world peace and development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>艰辛成就伟业，奋斗创造辉煌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Hardship gives birth to great causes, and arduous struggle results in glorious achievements. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>让我们在以胡锦涛同志为总书记的党中央领导下，凝聚起亿万人民的智慧和力量，再接再厉，开拓进取，全面完成“十一五”规划的各项任务，不断夺取改革开放和社会主义现代化建设事业的新胜利！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Under the leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Hu Jintao as General Secretary, let us pool the wisdom and strength of the hundreds of millions of our people; redouble our efforts to break fresh ground; complete all the tasks set forth in the Eleventh Five-Year Plan; and constantly win new victories in reform, opening up, and socialist modernization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>