<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<tmx version="1.4">
<header creationtool="ABBYY Aligner" creationtoolversion="1.0" segtype="sentence" o-tmf="ATM" adminlang="en-US" srclang="en-US" datatype="plaintext">
</header>
<body>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作报告</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>REPORT ON THE WORK OF THE GOVERNMENT</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——2021年3月5日在第十三届全国人民代表大会第四次会议上</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Delivered at the Fourth Session of the 13th National People's Congress of the People's Republic of China on March 5, 2021</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院总理 李克强</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Li Keqiang Premier of the State Council</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现在，我代表国务院，向大会报告政府工作，请予审议，并请全国政协委员提出意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I will now report to you on the work of the government and ask for your deliberation and approval. I also ask members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC) for their comments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一、2020年工作回顾</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I. A review of Our Work in 2020</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，在新中国历史上极不平凡。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year was an extraordinary year in the history of the People's Republic of China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对突如其来的新冠肺炎疫情、世界经济深度衰退等多重严重冲击，在以习近平同志为核心的党中央坚强领导下，全国各族人民顽强拼搏，疫情防控取得重大战略成果，在全球主要经济体中唯一实现经济正增长，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Facing the severe combined impact of a sudden coronavirus epidemic and a deep global economic recession, we the Chinese people of all ethnic groups, under the strong leadership of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, responded with tremendous tenacity. We achieved major strategic success in our response to Covid-19 and China was the world's only major economy to achieve growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>脱贫攻坚战取得全面胜利，决胜全面建成小康社会取得决定性成就，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We attained a complete victory in the fight against poverty, and we scored decisive achievements in securing a full victory in building a moderately prosperous society in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>交出一份人民满意、世界瞩目、可以载入史册的答卷。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Indeed, our achievements, which have won the approval of our people and global recognition, will be remembered in history. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年发展主要目标任务较好完成，我国改革开放和社会主义现代化建设又取得新的重大进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our development goals and tasks for the year were accomplished, and major headway has been made in China's reform, opening up, and socialist modernization drive.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在艰辛的抗疫历程中，党中央始终坚持人民至上、生命至上，习近平总书记亲自指挥、亲自部署，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Throughout this fierce battle against Covid-19, the CPC Central Committee put protecting the people and human life above everything else, with General Secretary Xi Jinping personally taking charge and making response decisions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各方面持续努力，不断巩固防控成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Thanks to the tireless efforts of all of us, our gains in controlling Covid-19 were continuously consolidated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们针对疫情形势变化，及时调整防控策略，健全常态化防控机制，有效处置局部地区聚集性疫情，最大限度保护了人民生命安全和身体健康，为恢复生产生活秩序创造必要条件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In response to evolving epidemic dynamics, we made well-timed adjustments to our response approaches. We improved routine control mechanisms and effectively suppressed several local outbreaks of the epidemic. With these actions, we protected the health and safety of the people to the greatest extent possible, and created the conditions for returning to normal life and work.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们贯彻党中央决策部署，统筹推进疫情防控和经济社会发展，主要做了以下工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year, we carried out the following work in implementing the decisions and plans of the Party Central Committee, and to respond to Covid-19 and advance economic and social development:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是围绕市场主体的急需制定和实施宏观政策，稳住了经济基本盘。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. We formulated and implemented macro policies to meet the urgent needs of market entities and kept the fundamentals of the economy stable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对历史罕见的冲击，我们在“六稳”工作基础上，明确提出“六保”任务，特别是保就业保民生保市场主体，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Facing shocks of a severity rarely seen before, based on what we had done to ensure stability on six key fronts, we carried out the task of maintaining security in six key areas—particularly job security, basic living needs, and the operations of market entities. [The six fronts refer to employment, the financial sector, foreign trade, foreign investment, domestic investment, and expectations. The six areas refer to job security, basic living needs, operations of market entities, food and energy security, stable industrial and supply chains, and the normal functioning of primary-level governments.]</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以保促稳、稳中求进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By maintaining security, we were able to deliver stability while also pursuing progress. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>立足国情实际，既及时果断又保持定力，坚持不搞“大水漫灌”，科学把握规模性政策的平衡点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Based on China's realities, we refrained from adopting a deluge of strong stimulus policies but took swift, decisive and well-considered steps, thus maintaining a desired balance between various macro policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>注重用改革和创新办法，助企纾困和激发活力并举，帮助受冲击最直接且量大面广的中小微企业和个体工商户渡难关。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Using approaches of reform and innovation, we eased the difficulties of our enterprises and energized them. And we helped micro, small, and medium enterprises (MSMEs) and self-employed individuals, which are large in number, extensive in scope and took the most direct hit from Covid-19, weather what was a very tough time. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施阶段性大规模减税降费，与制度性安排相结合，全年为市场主体减负超过2.6万亿元，其中减免社保费1.7万亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By making both time-limited large-scale tax and fee cuts and institutional arrangements, we reduced the burden on market entities by more than 2.6 trillion yuan for the year, including 1.7 trillion yuan in social insurance premium cuts and exemptions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新宏观政策实施方式，对新增2万亿元中央财政资金建立直达机制，省级财政加大资金下沉力度，共同为市县基层落实惠企利民政策及时补充财力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We adopted new approaches in implementing macro policies. The central government established a mechanism to directly allocate two trillion yuan of new funding to prefecture- and county-level governments, while provincial-level governments also increased their funding allocations to governments at these levels. With these two steps, we provided prefecture- and county-level governments with additional and timely fiscal resources to assist local businesses and residents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持银行定向增加贷款并降低利率水平，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Banks were given support to increase loans to businesses and lower interest rates in a targeted way.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对中小微企业贷款延期还本付息，大型商业银行普惠小微企业贷款增长50%以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>MSMEs were allowed to postpone principal and interest repayments on their loans, and inclusive finance lending by large commercial banks to micro and small businesses increased by more than 50 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>金融系统向实体经济让利1.5万亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The real economy thus received an infusion of 1.5 trillion yuan from financial institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对大企业复工复产加强“点对点”服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Point-to-point transportation services were provided to large enterprises to help them resume operations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经过艰苦努力，我们率先实现复工复产，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Thanks to all these arduous efforts, China was able to take the lead in reopening its economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济恢复好于预期，全年国内生产总值增长2.3%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With gross domestic product (GDP) for the year growing by 2.3 percent, a better-than-expected recovery was achieved.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>宏观调控积累了新的经验，以合理代价取得较大成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We thus not only gained fresh experience in macro regulation, but also delivered the best possible outcome at an acceptable cost.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是优先稳就业保民生，人民生活得到切实保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2. We gave top priority to stabilizing employment and ensuring living standards and effectively safeguarded people's wellbeing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>就业是最大的民生，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Employment is pivotal to people's wellbeing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保市场主体也是为稳就业保民生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our efforts to keep market entities afloat are aimed at maintaining stable employment and meeting basic living needs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地加大稳岗扩岗激励力度，企业和员工共同克服困难。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local governments across the country provided more incentives to stabilize and expand employment, thus enabling businesses and their employees to work hand-in-hand to overcome their difficulties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>多渠道做好重点群体就业工作，支持大众创业万众创新带动就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Multiple channels were tapped to ensure employment for key groups, and startups and innovation were encouraged as a way to create jobs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新增市场主体恢复快速增长，创造了大量就业岗位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of new market entities began growing rapidly again, leading to the creation of a large number of new jobs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业1186万人，年末全国城镇调查失业率降到5.2%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 11.86 million urban jobs were added, and the year-end surveyed urban unemployment rate dropped to 5.2 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>作为最大发展中国家，在巨大冲击下能够保持就业大局稳定，尤为难能可贵。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It is truly remarkable that China, the largest developing country in the world, has kept overall employment stable in the face of such an enormous shock. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强生活必需品保供稳价，居民消费价格上涨2.5%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The supply and price stability of daily necessities was ensured; the consumer price index (CPI) posted a 2.5 percent growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>线上办公、网络购物、无接触配送等广泛开展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Practices like working from home, online shopping, and contactless delivery were widely adopted. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大幅度扩大失业保险保障范围。对因疫情遇困群众及时给予救助，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We expanded the coverage of unemployment insurance schemes, and extended timely assistance to those who were hit particularly hard by Covid-19. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新纳入低保、特困供养近600万人，实施临时救助超过800万人次。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Close to six million additional people received subsistence allowances or extreme poverty aid, and more than eight million temporary assistance grants were disbursed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抵御严重洪涝、台风等自然灾害，全力应急抢险救援，妥善安置受灾群众，保障了人民群众生命财产安全和基本生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We fought against severe floods, typhoons, and other natural disasters and spared no effort to provide rescue and relief to disaster victims and make appropriate arrangements for them, thus protecting people's lives and property and ensuring their basic living needs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是坚决打好三大攻坚战，主要目标任务如期完成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. We made decisive progress in the three critical battles against poverty, pollution and potential risk, achieving major targets and tasks as planned.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>较大幅度增加财政扶贫资金投入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased funding for poverty alleviation by a considerable sum. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对工作难度大的贫困县和贫困村挂牌督战，精准落实各项帮扶措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Counties and villages facing difficulty in poverty eradication were placed under special supervision to see they fully implemented all assistance and support policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优先支持贫困劳动力稳岗就业，帮助返乡贫困劳动力再就业，努力稳住务工收入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We assisted on a priority basis poor workers in securing jobs and poor rural migrant workers who had returned home in finding new jobs, thus keeping rural residents' incomes from nonagricultural work stable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大产业扶贫力度，深入开展消费扶贫。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We worked harder to reduce poverty through the development of local industries and promote consumer spending on products from poor areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强易返贫致贫人口监测和帮扶。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened monitoring for groups who are liable to return to, or fall into, poverty, and provided them with assistance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>年初剩余的551万农村贫困人口全部脱贫、52个贫困县全部摘帽。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All remaining poor rural residents, totaling 5.51 million in early 2020, were lifted from poverty, as were all of China's remaining 52 poor counties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续打好蓝天、碧水、净土保卫战，完成污染防治攻坚战阶段性目标任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued working to keep our skies blue, our waters clear, and our lands pollution-free, and accomplished the objectives for pollution prevention and control for the current stage. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>长江、黄河、海岸带等重要生态系统保护和修复重大工程深入实施，生态建设得到加强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We carried out major projects for protecting and restoring key ecosystems in the Yangtze River and Yellow River basins and along coastlines, and stepped up our ecological conservation endeavors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳妥化解地方政府债务风险，及时处置一批重大金融风险隐患。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took prudent steps to defuse local government debt risks and acted swiftly to defuse a number of major financial risks and potential dangers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是坚定不移推进改革开放，发展活力和内生动力进一步增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. We continued to advance reform and opening up and further boosted the vitality and momentum of development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善要素市场化配置体制机制。加强产权保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved the systems and mechanisms for the market allocation of production factors and strengthened the protection of property rights. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进“放管服”改革，实施优化营商环境条例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We furthered reforms to streamline administration and delegate power, improve regulation, and upgrade services; and the Regulations on Improving the Business Environment were implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>出台国企改革三年行动方案。支持民营企业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We adopted a three-year action plan for SOE reform and supported the development of private businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善资本市场基础制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The underlying systems of the capital market were improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进农业农村、社会事业等领域改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made solid strides in reforms related to agriculture, rural development, and social programs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>共建“一带一路”稳步推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Steady progress was achieved in the joint pursuit of the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>海南自由贸易港建设等重大举措陆续推出。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Major measures to develop the Hainan Free Trade Port and other major initiatives were launched. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>成功举办第三届中国国际进口博览会、中国国际服务贸易交易会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The third China International Import Expo and the China International Fair for Trade in Services were hosted successfully. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动区域全面经济伙伴关系协定签署。完成中欧投资协定谈判。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China played an important role in the signing of the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement, and it concluded negotiations on an investment agreement with the European Union. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>维护产业链供应链稳定，对外贸易和利用外资保持增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's industrial chains and supply chains were kept stable. And its foreign trade and utilized foreign investment posted steady growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是大力促进科技创新，产业转型升级步伐加快。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>5. We vigorously promoted innovation in science and technology and accelerated industrial transformation and upgrading. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设国际科技创新中心和综合性国家科学中心，成功组建首批国家实验室。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We developed China's international centers for science and technology innovation and comprehensive national science centers, and set up the country's first group of national laboratories. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“天问一号”、“嫦娥五号”、“奋斗者”号等突破性成果不断涌现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year saw a stream of scientific and technological breakthroughs, like the Tianwen-1 Mars mission, the Chang'e-5 lunar mission, and the Fendouzhe (Striver) deep-sea manned submersible. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强关键核心技术攻关。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We intensified efforts to make major breakthroughs in core technologies in key fields. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大知识产权保护力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Intellectual property protection was strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持科技成果转化应用，促进大中小企业融通创新，推广全面创新改革试验相关举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We supported the application of scientific and technological advances, encouraged collaborative innovation among small, medium, and large enterprises, and promoted pilot reforms on all-around innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动产业数字化智能化改造，战略性新兴产业保持快速发展势头。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More was done to upgrade the industrial sector with digital and smart technologies; and strategic emerging industries maintained rapid development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>六是推进新型城镇化和乡村振兴，城乡区域发展格局不断优化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>6. We advanced new urbanization and rural revitalization and improved the layout of urban-rural development and development among regions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大城镇老旧小区改造力度，因城施策促进房地产市场平稳健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts were intensified to rebuild old urban residential areas. By adopting city-specific policies, we promoted the stable and healthy development of the housing market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食实现增产，生猪产能加快恢复，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Grain output continued to increase, and hog production rebounded at a faster rate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>乡村建设稳步展开，农村人居环境整治成效明显。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took solid steps in advancing rural development, and markedly improved rural living environments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进煤电油气产供储销体系建设，提升能源安全保障能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued to build up the production, supply, storage, and marketing systems for coal, petroleum, natural gas, and electricity, and enhanced our capacity to ensure energy security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全区域协调发展体制机制，在实施重大区域发展战略方面出台一批新举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved mechanisms for promoting coordinated development between regions, and introduced a range of new measures to implement major strategies for regional development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>七是加强依法行政和社会建设，社会保持和谐稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>7. We stepped up law-based administration, promoted social advancement, and safeguarded social harmony and stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提请全国人大常委会审议法律议案9件，制定修订行政法规37部。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We submitted nine legislative proposals to the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress for deliberation, and formulated or revised 37 sets of administrative regulations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真办理人大代表建议和政协委员提案。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We worked with keen attention to handle the suggestions and proposals of NPC deputies and CPPCC National Committee members. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广泛开展线上教学，秋季学期实现全面复学，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Online school teaching was introduced nationwide, and students returned to school for the autumn semester.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>1000多万高中毕业生顺利完成高考。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over 10 million high school graduates successfully completed the college entrance examination. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面深化教育领域综合改革。实现高职院校扩招100万人目标。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We pushed ahead with the comprehensive reform of education, and we achieved the goal of increasing student enrollments in vocational colleges by one million. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大公共卫生体系建设力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts were redoubled to strengthen the public health system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升大规模核酸检测能力，新冠肺炎患者治疗费用全部由国家承担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We scaled up the capacity for conducting large-scale nucleic acid testing, and all the medical bills for treating Covid-19 patients were covered by the government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高退休人员基本养老金，上调城乡居民基础养老金最低标准，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Basic pension payments for retirees and minimum basic pension benefits for rural and urban non-working residents were both raised.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障养老金按时足额发放，实现企业养老保险基金省级统收统支。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pension benefits were paid on time and in full, and provincial-level collection and payout of enterprise workers' old-age insurance funds was realized. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强公共文化服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Better public cultural services were provided. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善城乡基层治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Primary-level governance in urban and rural areas was enhanced. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实做好信访工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Solid steps were taken to address public complaints. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥审计监督作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Audit-based oversight was vigorously conducted,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展国务院大督查。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and State Council accountability inspections were carried out. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好第七次全国人口普查、国家脱贫攻坚普查。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We conducted the seventh population census and the poverty reduction survey. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强生产安全事故防范和处置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We intensified efforts to prevent and handle workplace accidents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格食品药品疫苗监管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Supervision of food, drugs, and vaccines was tightened up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化社会治安综合治理，持续推进扫黑除恶专项斗争，平安中国建设取得新成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took a full range of measures to maintain law and order, and continued to combat organized crime and root out local criminal gangs, thus making further headway in pursuing the Peaceful China initiative.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>贯彻落实党中央全面从严治党战略部署，加强党风廉政建设和反腐败斗争。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We implemented the Party Central Committee's strategic plan for exercising full and strict Party self-governance, and did more to improve Party conduct, build a clean government, and fight corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>巩固深化“不忘初心、牢记使命”主题教育成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We consolidated the gains from the initiative to raise awareness of the need to stay true to the Party's founding mission. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格落实中央八项规定精神，持续为基层减负。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strictly complied with the central Party leadership's eight-point decision on improving work conduct, and we made sustained efforts to ease the burdens of those working on the ground.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国特色大国外交卓有成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We were successful in pursuing China's major country diplomacy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>习近平主席等党和国家领导人通过视频方式主持中非团结抗疫特别峰会，出席联合国成立75周年系列高级别会议、世界卫生大会、二十国集团领导人峰会、亚太经合组织领导人非正式会议、中国－欧盟领导人会晤、东亚合作领导人系列会议等重大活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>President Xi Jinping and other Party and state leaders hosted or attended, via video link, major diplomatic events, including the Extraordinary China-Africa Summit on Solidarity against Covid-19, high-level meetings commemorating the 75th anniversary of the United Nations, the 73rd World Health Assembly, the G20 Leaders' Summit in Riyadh, the APEC Economic Leaders' Meeting, the 22nd China-EU Leaders' Meeting, and the East Asia leaders' meetings on cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持多边主义，推动构建人类命运共同体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We upheld multilateralism and endeavored to build a human community with a shared future. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持国际抗疫合作，倡导建设人类卫生健康共同体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We supported global cooperation on combating Covid-19 and called for building a global health community. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国为促进世界和平与发展作出了重要贡献。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China thus made important contributions to advancing global peace and development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来的工作殊为不易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our work last year was truly challenging. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地区各部门顾全大局、尽责担当，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Yet, local authorities and government departments across the country kept in mind the big picture and shouldered their responsibilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>上亿市场主体在应对冲击中展现出坚强韧性，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Market entities, over one hundred million in number, responded to shocks with fortitude and resilience. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广大人民群众勤劳付出、共克时艰，诠释了百折不挠的民族精神，彰显了人民是真正的英雄，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our people worked hard and fought adversity in close solidarity and with the unyielding spirit of the Chinese nation, thus proving themselves true heroes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是我们战胜一切困难挑战的力量源泉。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is the well of strength that enables us to rise to every challenge and overcome every difficulty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年取得的成绩，是以习近平同志为核心的党中央坚强领导的结果，是习近平新时代中国特色社会主义思想科学指引的结果，是全党全军全国各族人民团结奋斗的结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We owe our achievements last year to the strong leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, to the sound guidance of Xi Jinping Thought on Socialism with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era, and to the concerted efforts of the Party, the armed forces, and the Chinese people of all ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我代表国务院，向全国各族人民，向各民主党派、各人民团体和各界人士，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I wish to express sincere gratitude to all our people, and to all other political parties, people's organizations, and public figures from all sectors of society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向香港特别行政区同胞、澳门特别行政区同胞、台湾同胞和海外侨胞，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I express sincere appreciation to our fellow countrymen and women in the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions, in Taiwan, and overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向关心和支持中国现代化建设的各国政府、国际组织和各国朋友，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I also wish to express heartfelt thanks to the governments of other countries, international organizations, and friends across the world who have shown understanding and support for us in China as we pursue modernization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在肯定成绩的同时，我们也清醒看到面临的困难和挑战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While recognizing our achievements, we are also keenly aware of the difficulties and challenges before us. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新冠肺炎疫情仍在全球蔓延，国际形势中不稳定不确定因素增多，世界经济形势复杂严峻。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As the coronavirus continues to spread around the world, instability and uncertainty are mounting on the international landscape, and the global economy continues to face grave challenges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内疫情防控仍有薄弱环节，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Domestically, there are still weak links in our work to control Covid-19. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济恢复基础尚不牢固，居民消费仍受制约，投资增长后劲不足，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The foundation for achieving our country's economic recovery needs to be further consolidated, impediments to consumer spending remain, and investment growth lacks sustainability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中小微企业和个体工商户困难较多，稳就业压力较大。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our MSMEs and self-employed individuals are still finding the going tough, and the pressure in maintaining stable employment is mounting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>关键领域创新能力不强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our innovation capacity in key areas needs to be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些地方财政收支矛盾突出，防范化解金融等领域风险任务依然艰巨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some local governments have serious budgetary deficits. In forestalling and defusing risks in the financial sector and other areas, we face formidable tasks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>生态环保任重道远。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We still have a long way to go in protecting the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>民生领域还有不少短板。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>And many weaknesses in areas that are important to people's basic needs wait to be addressed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作存在不足，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There is also room for improvement in the work of the government.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>形式主义、官僚主义不同程度存在，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Both pointless formalities and bureaucratism persist to varying degrees. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>少数干部不担当不作为不善为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A small number of officials fail to fulfill their responsibilities and are unwilling or unable to carry out their duties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些领域腐败问题仍有发生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Instances of corruption still occur in some sectors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们一定要直面问题和挑战，尽心竭力改进工作，决不辜负人民期待！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will face these problems and challenges squarely, make every effort to make improvements, and do all we can to live up to our people's expectations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二、“十三五”时期发展成就和“十四五”时期主要目标任务</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>II. Achievements in the 13th Five-Year Plan Period and Major Targets and Tasks for the 14th Five-Year Plan Period</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去五年，我国经济社会发展取得新的历史性成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the past five years, China has scored historic new achievements in economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济运行总体平稳，经济结构持续优化，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The economy performed stably overall, and its structure was continuously improved.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值从不到70万亿元增加到超过100万亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>GDP increased from less than 70 trillion yuan to over 100 trillion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新型国家建设成果丰硕，在载人航天、探月工程、深海工程、超级计算、量子信息等领域取得一批重大科技成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Much was accomplished toward making China a country of innovators, with major advances in manned spaceflight, lunar exploration, deep-sea engineering, supercomputing, quantum information, and other areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>脱贫攻坚成果举世瞩目，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's success in poverty alleviation has been recognized by the international community. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>5575万农村贫困人口实现脱贫，960多万建档立卡贫困人口通过易地扶贫搬迁摆脱了“一方水土难养一方人”的困境，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Its entire rural poor population, 55.75 million in number, was lifted out of poverty, including more than 9.6 million registered poor people who were relocated from inhospitable areas;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>区域性整体贫困得到解决，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and regional poverty was successfully eradicated.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完成了消除绝对贫困的艰巨任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The daunting task we set ourselves to eliminate absolute poverty has thus been successfully accomplished. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农业现代化稳步推进，粮食生产连年丰收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Agricultural modernization was steadily advanced, and good harvests were recorded for five years running. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>1亿农业转移人口和其他常住人口在城镇落户目标顺利实现，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The goal of granting urban residency to 100 million people from rural areas and other permanent residents without local household registration was met.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇棚户区住房改造超过2100万套。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More than 21 million housing units in run-down urban areas were rebuilt. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>区域重大战略扎实推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Solid steps were taken to implement major regional development strategies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>污染防治力度加大，资源能源利用效率显著提升，生态环境明显改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pollution prevention and control efforts were intensified, resources and energy were used more efficiently, and there was a notable improvement in the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>金融风险处置取得重要阶段性成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Important progress was made in addressing financial risks in this period. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面深化改革取得重大突破，供给侧结构性改革持续推进，“放管服”改革不断深入，营商环境持续改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Major breakthroughs were achieved in deepening reform across the board.Supply-side structural reform was steadily advanced, as were reforms to streamline administration and delegate power, improve regulation, and upgrade services. Thanks to these efforts, the business environment kept improving. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对外开放持续扩大，共建“一带一路”成果丰硕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China continued to open its door wider to the world; the joint pursuit of the Belt and Road Initiative yielded solid outcomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民生活水平显著提高，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The living standards of our people rose significantly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业超过6000万人，建成世界上规模最大的社会保障体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over 60 million urban jobs were added, and the world's largest social security system was established. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面建立实施困难残疾人生活补贴和重度残疾人护理补贴制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The system for granting living allowances to people with disabilities in financial difficulty and nursing care subsidies to people with serious disabilities was set up and implemented across the country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育、卫生、文化等领域发展取得新成就，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New achievements were made in education, healthcare, culture and other sectors.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育公平和质量较大提升，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Education became much more equitable, and its quality was markedly improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>医疗卫生事业加快发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The healthcare sector registered accelerated development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>文化事业和文化产业繁荣发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The cultural sector flourished. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国防和军队建设水平大幅提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Notable advances were made in the development of national defense and the armed forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家安全全面加强，社会保持和谐稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's national security was enhanced on all fronts, and social harmony and stability were maintained across the country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经过五年持续奋斗，“十三五”规划主要目标任务胜利完成，中华民族伟大复兴向前迈出了新的一大步。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Thanks to our hard work in these five years, we accomplished the major goals and tasks of the 13th Five-Year Plan, and made a giant stride toward the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“十四五”时期是开启全面建设社会主义现代化国家新征程的第一个五年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The period covered by the 14th Five-Year Plan will be the first five years in which we embark on a new journey to build China into a modern socialist country in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国发展仍然处于重要战略机遇期，但机遇和挑战都有新的发展变化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China remains in an important period of strategic opportunity for development. Yet, there are changes in both the opportunities and challenges we face. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要准确把握新发展阶段，深入贯彻新发展理念，加快构建新发展格局，推动高质量发展，为全面建设社会主义现代化国家开好局起好步。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should have an accurate understanding of this new stage of development, fully apply the new development philosophy, and accelerate our efforts to create a new development pattern to promote high-quality development. By doing so, we will set the stage for building a modern socialist country in all respects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>根据《中共中央关于制定国民经济和社会发展第十四个五年规划和二〇三五年远景目标的建议》，国务院编制了《国民经济和社会发展第十四个五年规划和2035年远景目标纲要（草案）》。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The State Council, acting in accordance with the Recommendations of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China for Formulating the 14th Five-Year Plan for Economic and Social Development and Long-Range Objectives through the Year 2035, has drawn up the draft Outline for the 14th Five-Year Plan for Economic and Social Development and Long-Range Objectives through the Year 2035. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>《纲要草案》坚持以习近平新时代中国特色社会主义思想为指导，实化量化“十四五”时期经济社会发展主要目标和重大任务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The draft Outline, which was formulated under the guidance of Xi Jinping Thought on Socialism with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era, sets major quantified objectives and tasks for economic and social development during the 14th Five-Year Plan period.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全文提交大会审查，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The full draft has been submitted to this session for your deliberation and approval. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这里概述几个方面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The highlights of the draft Outline are as follows:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——着力提升发展质量效益，保持经济持续健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Improving the quality and effectiveness of development and maintaining sustained and healthy economic growth</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展是解决我国一切问题的基础和关键。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Development is the foundation, and it holds the key, for addressing all the issues our country faces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持新发展理念，把新发展理念完整、准确、全面贯穿发展全过程和各领域，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must stay true to the new development philosophy, and ensure it is applied in full, in both letter and spirit, in every stage and aspect of development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导各方面把工作重点放在提高发展质量和效益上，促进增长潜力充分发挥。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should encourage people working in all sectors to give high priority to improving the quality and effectiveness of development to fully tap China's growth potential. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济运行保持在合理区间，各年度视情提出经济增长预期目标，全员劳动生产率增长高于国内生产总值增长，城镇调查失业率控制在5.5%以内，物价水平保持总体平稳，实现更高质量、更有效率、更加公平、更可持续、更为安全的发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep major economic indicators within an appropriate range, set annual targets for economic growth in light of actual conditions, ensure that overall labor productivity grows faster than GDP, keep the surveyed urban unemployment rate within 5.5 percent, and keep prices generally stable. Doing so will enable us to achieve higher-quality development that is more efficient, equitable, sustainable, and secure.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——坚持创新驱动发展，加快发展现代产业体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Pursuing innovation-driven development and accelerating modernization of the industrial system</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持创新在我国现代化建设全局中的核心地位，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Innovation remains at the heart of China's modernization drive.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把科技自立自强作为国家发展的战略支撑。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen our science and technology to provide strategic support for China's development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善国家创新体系，加快构建以国家实验室为引领的战略科技力量，打好关键核心技术攻坚战，制定实施基础研究十年行动方案，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To improve China's innovation system, we will work faster to enhance our strategic scientific and technological capability underpinned by the development of national laboratories, strive to make major breakthroughs in core technologies in key fields, and formulate and implement a ten-year action plan for basic research.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升企业技术创新能力，激发人才创新活力，完善科技创新体制机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance the capacity of enterprises to make technological innovation, unlock the creativity of talent, and improve the systems and mechanisms for making scientific and technological innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全社会研发经费投入年均增长7%以上、力争投入强度高于“十三五”时期实际。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's R&amp;D spending will increase by more than seven percent per year, which is expected to account for a higher percentage of GDP than that during the 13th Five-Year Plan period. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广泛开展科学普及活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Extensive activities will be conducted to help people learn more about science. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持把发展经济着力点放在实体经济上，推进产业基础高级化、产业链现代化，保持制造业比重基本稳定，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In pursuing economic growth, we will continue to prioritize the development of the real economy, upgrade the industrial base, modernize industrial chains, and keep the share of manufacturing in the economy basically stable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改造提升传统产业，发展壮大战略性新兴产业，促进服务业繁荣发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will transform and upgrade traditional industries, strengthen strategic emerging industries, and promote the vigorous development of the service sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹推进传统基础设施和新型基础设施建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Coordinated development of traditional and new forms of infrastructure will be promoted. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快数字化发展，打造数字经济新优势，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Digitalization will be sped up to create new strengths for the digital economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>协同推进数字产业化和产业数字化转型，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will both develop digital industry and transform traditional industries with digital technologies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快数字社会建设步伐，提高数字政府建设水平，营造良好数字生态，建设数字中国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work faster to develop a digital society, digital government, and healthy digital ecosystem as we pursue the Digital China initiative.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——形成强大国内市场，构建新发展格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Creating a robust domestic market and fostering a new development pattern</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把实施扩大内需战略同深化供给侧结构性改革有机结合起来，以创新驱动、高质量供给引领和创造新需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will pursue the strategy of expanding domestic demand and intensify supply-side structural reform, and generate new demand with innovation-driven development and high-quality supply. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>破除制约要素合理流动的堵点，贯通生产、分配、流通、消费各环节，形成国民经济良性循环。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will remove impediments to the rational flow of production factors along all links of production, allocation, distribution, and consumption to facilitate favorable circulation in our economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>立足国内大循环，协同推进强大国内市场和贸易强国建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give priority to domestic circulation, and work to build a strong domestic market and turn China into a trader of quality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依托国内经济循环体系形成对全球要素资源的强大引力场，促进国内国际双循环。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will leverage the flows of the domestic economy to make China a major magnet for global production factors and resources, thereby promoting positive interplay between domestic circulation and international circulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立扩大内需的有效制度，全面促进消费，拓展投资空间，加快培育完整内需体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will put in place frameworks to effectively expand domestic demand, boost consumer spending across the board, and unlock the potential for investment, thus accelerating the establishment of a complete system of domestic demand.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——全面推进乡村振兴，完善新型城镇化战略。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Advancing rural revitalization across the board and improving the new urbanization strategy</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持农业农村优先发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The development of agriculture and rural areas remains at the top of our work agenda. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严守18亿亩耕地红线，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The total area of China's farmland must stay above the red line of 120 million hectares. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施高标准农田建设工程、黑土地保护工程，确保种源安全，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out projects to develop high-quality farmland and conserve chernozem soils, and ensure the security of our germplasm resources.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施乡村建设行动，健全城乡融合发展体制机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out rural development initiatives, and improve systems and mechanisms for promoting integrated urban-rural development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全巩固拓展脱贫攻坚成果长效机制，提升脱贫地区整体发展水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will set up a robust long-term mechanism for consolidating and expanding the achievements of the battle against poverty, and raise the overall performance of development in areas that have cast off poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进以人为核心的新型城镇化战略，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The strategy of new, people-centered urbanization will continue to be pursued. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快农业转移人口市民化，常住人口城镇化率提高到65%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to grant permanent urban residency to people who move to cities from rural areas, and raise the percentage of permanent urban residents to 65 percent of the population.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展壮大城市群和都市圈，推进以县城为重要载体的城镇化建设，实施城市更新行动，完善住房市场体系和住房保障体系，提升城镇化发展质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand city clusters and metropolitan areas, promote urbanization with a focus on county towns, implement an action plan for urban renewal, and improve the housing market and housing support system. These moves will enable us to achieve higher quality urbanization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——优化区域经济布局，促进区域协调发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Improving regional economic structures and promoting coordinated regional development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施区域重大战略、区域协调发展战略、主体功能区战略，构建高质量发展的区域经济布局和国土空间支撑体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement the major regional development strategies as well as the strategies for coordinated regional development and functional zoning, so as to create regional economic structures and a territorial space system that will sustain high-quality development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推动京津冀协同发展、长江经济带发展、粤港澳大湾区建设、长三角一体化发展、黄河流域生态保护和高质量发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take solid steps to promote the coordinated development of the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei region, the development of the Yangtze Economic Belt and the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, integrated development in the Yangtze River Delta, and ecological protection and high-quality development in the Yellow River basin.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高标准、高质量建设雄安新区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build Xiongan New Area to a high standard. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动西部大开发形成新格局，推动东北振兴取得新突破，促进中部地区加快崛起，鼓励东部地区加快推进现代化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will usher in a new stage in large-scale development in the western region, promote breakthroughs in the revitalization of northeast China, accelerate the rise of the central region, and encourage the eastern region to accelerate modernization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进成渝地区双城经济圈建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of the Chengdu-Chongqing economic zone. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持革命老区、民族地区加快发展，加强边疆地区建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support old revolutionary base areas and ethnic minority areas in speeding up development, and strengthen the development of border areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极拓展海洋经济发展空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to unlock the development potential of the maritime economy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——全面深化改革开放，持续增强发展动力和活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Advancing reform and opening up across the board and bolstering the momentum and vitality of development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建高水平社会主义市场经济体制，激发各类市场主体活力，加快国有经济布局优化和结构调整，优化民营经济发展环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To develop a high-standard socialist market economy, we will energize all market entities, improve the layout and structure of the state-owned sector at a faster pace, and create a better development environment for private businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设高标准市场体系，全面完善产权制度，推进要素市场化配置改革，强化竞争政策基础地位，完善竞争政策框架。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build a high-standard market system, effect an all-round improvement in the property rights system, carry out reforms to promote the market-based allocation of production factors, reinforce the foundational role of competition policies, and refine the competition policy framework. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立现代财税金融体制，提升政府经济治理能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will modernize fiscal, taxation, and financial systems, and improve government capacity to conduct economic governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化“放管服”改革，构建一流营商环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reforms to streamline administration and delegate powers, improve regulation, and upgrade services to foster a world-class business environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设更高水平开放型经济新体制，推动共建“一带一路”高质量发展，构建面向全球的高标准自由贸易区网络。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop new systems for a higher-standard open economy, promote the high-quality development of the BRI, and build a globally oriented network of high-standard free trade zones.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——推动绿色发展，促进人与自然和谐共生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Promoting green development and ensuring harmony between humanity and nature</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持绿水青山就是金山银山理念，加强山水林田湖草系统治理，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will stay true to the principle that lucid waters and lush mountains are invaluable assets and strengthen the conservation of mountain, river, forest, farmland, lake, and grassland ecosystems.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进重要生态屏障建设，构建以国家公园为主体的自然保护地体系，森林覆盖率达到24.1%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to build major ecological shields, develop a national park-based nature reserve system, and expand forest coverage to 24.1 percent of China's total land area. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续改善环境质量，基本消除重污染天气和城市黑臭水体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve the quality of the environment, and generally eliminate heavy air pollution and black, malodorous water bodies in cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实2030年应对气候变化国家自主贡献目标。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that China meets the targets for its intended nationally determined contributions in response to climate change by 2030. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快发展方式绿色转型，协同推进经济高质量发展和生态环境高水平保护，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expedite the transition of China's growth model to one of green development, and promote both high-quality economic growth and high-standard environmental protection.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗和二氧化碳排放分别降低13.5%、18%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Energy consumption per unit of GDP and carbon dioxide emissions per unit of GDP will be reduced by 13.5 percent and 18 percent, respectively.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——持续增进民生福祉，扎实推动共同富裕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Improving people's wellbeing and striving for common prosperity</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持尽力而为、量力而行，加强普惠性、基础性、兜底性民生建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do everything within our capacity to improve the wellbeing of our people, and ensure that public services are inclusive, meet essential needs, and ensure basic living standards for people in difficulty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定促进共同富裕行动纲要，让发展成果更多更公平惠及全体人民。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>An action plan will be adopted to promote common prosperity to see that our people share more fully and fairly in the gains of development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施就业优先战略，扩大就业容量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the employment-first strategy and increase employment opportunities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力提高低收入群体收入，扩大中等收入群体，居民人均可支配收入增长与国内生产总值增长基本同步。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to raise the income of the low-income group and expand the size of the middle-income group. Per capita disposable income will generally grow in step with GDP growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设高质量教育体系，建设高素质专业化教师队伍，深化教育改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build a high-quality education system and foster a contingent of top-performing teachers with strong professional expertise by deepening educational reforms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施教育提质扩容工程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out an initiative to raise the quality of education and expand its capacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>劳动年龄人口平均受教育年限提高到11.3年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We expect that the average number of years of schooling among the working-age population will rise to 11.3. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推进健康中国建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make all-round efforts to build a Healthy China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建强大公共卫生体系，完善城乡医疗服务网络，广泛开展全民健身运动，人均预期寿命再提高1岁。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop a strong public health system, refine medical service networks in both urban and rural areas, carry out extensive public fitness activities, and raise the average life expectancy by one year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施积极应对人口老龄化国家战略，以“一老一小”为重点完善人口服务体系，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the national strategy for addressing population aging, and improve the population services system with a focus on elderly care and child care.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化生育政策，推动实现适度生育水平，发展普惠托育和基本养老服务体系，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will refine the childbirth policy, work to achieve an appropriate birth rate, and develop the systems for public-interest child care and basic elderly care services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>逐步延迟法定退休年龄。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The statutory retirement age will be raised in a phased manner. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全多层次社会保障体系，基本养老保险参保率提高到95%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The multi-tiered social security system will be improved, with coverage of basic old-age insurance reaching 95 percent of the population. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化社会救助和慈善制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Social assistance and charity systems will also be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展社会主义先进文化，提高社会文明程度，弘扬诚信文化，建设诚信社会，提升公共文化服务水平，健全现代文化产业体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop advanced socialist culture, raise standards of public civility, promote integrity and trustworthiness throughout society, improve public cultural services, and improve modern systems for cultural industries.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——统筹发展和安全，建设更高水平的平安中国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>—Ensuring both development and security and ushering in a new stage in building a Peaceful China</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持总体国家安全观，加强国家安全体系和能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will pursue a holistic approach to national security and strengthen our national security system and capacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化国家经济安全保障，实施粮食、能源资源、金融安全战略，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To ensure national economic security, we will carry out strategies for safeguarding food, energy and resource, and financial security.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食综合生产能力保持在1.3万亿斤以上，提高能源综合生产能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep overall grain output above 650 million metric tons, and enhance our overall energy production capacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面提高公共安全保障能力，维护社会稳定和安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase our public security capacity across the board to maintain social stability and public safety.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>展望未来，我们有信心有能力战胜前进道路上的艰难险阻，完成“十四五”规划目标任务，奋力谱写中国特色社会主义事业新篇章！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Looking to the future, we have the confidence and the ability to overcome all difficulties and obstacles on our road ahead and fulfill the goals and tasks in the 14th Five-Year Plan for Economic and Social Development (2021-2025), thus opening a new page in the development of socialism with Chinese characteristics.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三、2021年重点工作</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>III. Major tasks for 2021</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年是我国现代化建设进程中具有特殊重要性的一年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The year 2021 is of particular importance to China as it pursues the modernization drive. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好政府工作，要在以习近平同志为核心的党中央坚强领导下，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To accomplish the government's work for the year, we must, under the strong leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, do the following:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以习近平新时代中国特色社会主义思想为指导，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>follow the guidance of Xi Jinping Thought on Socialism with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面贯彻党的十九大和十九届二中、三中、四中、五中全会精神，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>implement the guiding principles of the Party's 19th National Congress and the second through fifth plenary sessions of the 19th Party Central Committee in full;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持稳中求进工作总基调，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>act on the general principle of pursuing progress while ensuring stability;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>立足新发展阶段，贯彻新发展理念，构建新发展格局，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>ground our efforts in the new development stage, apply the new development philosophy, and create a new pattern of development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以推动高质量发展为主题，以深化供给侧结构性改革为主线，以改革创新为根本动力，以满足人民日益增长的美好生活需要为根本目的，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>pursue high-quality development as the general aim, advance supply-side structural reform as the main task, and harness reform and innovation as the key source of momentum in our endeavor to meet the fundamental goal of satisfying the people's growing needs for a better life;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持系统观念，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>apply systems thinking;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>巩固拓展疫情防控和经济社会发展成果，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>consolidate and expand the achievements of the Covid-19 response and economic and social development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更好统筹发展和安全，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>ensure better coordination in pursuing development and upholding security;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实做好“六稳”工作、全面落实“六保”任务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>ensure stability on six key fronts and maintain security in six key areas;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>科学精准实施宏观政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>implement macro policies in a systemic and targeted way;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力保持经济运行在合理区间，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>keep major economic indicators within an appropriate range;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持扩大内需战略，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>continue to expand domestic demand;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化科技战略支撑，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>strengthen science and technology to provide strategic support for development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大高水平对外开放，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>pursue higher-standard opening up;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持社会和谐稳定，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>maintain social harmony and stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>确保“十四五”开好局起好步，以优异成绩庆祝中国共产党成立100周年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These efforts will enable us to get off to a good start in the 14th Five-Year Plan period and commemorate the centenary of the CPC with outstanding achievements in development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年我国发展仍面临不少风险挑战，但经济长期向好的基本面没有改变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In 2021, China will continue to face many development risks and challenges, but the economic fundamentals that will sustain long-term growth remain unchanged. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要坚定信心，攻坚克难，巩固恢复性增长基础，努力保持经济社会持续健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should stay confident, meet challenges head-on, and consolidate the foundation for economic recovery to ensure sustained and healthy economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年发展主要预期目标是：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The main projected targets for development this year are as follows:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值增长6%以上；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>GDP growth of over 6 percent</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业1100万人以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>over 11 million new urban jobs</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇调查失业率5.5%左右；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a surveyed urban unemployment rate of around 5.5 percent</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民消费价格涨幅3%左右；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>CPI increase of around 3 percent</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进出口量稳质升，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>steady increases in both the volume and quality of imports and exports</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国际收支基本平衡；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a basic equilibrium in the balance of payments</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民收入稳步增长；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>steady growth in personal income</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>生态环境质量进一步改善，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a further improvement in the environment</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗降低3%左右，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a drop of around 3 percent in energy consumption per unit of GDP</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>主要污染物排放量继续下降；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a continued reduction in the discharge of major pollutants</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食产量保持在1.3万亿斤以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>grain output of over 650 million metric tons</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济增速是综合性指标，今年预期目标设定为6%以上，考虑了经济运行恢复情况，有利于引导各方面集中精力推进改革创新、推动高质量发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As a general target, China's growth rate has been set at over 6 percent for this year. In setting this target, we have taken into account the recovery of economic activity. A target of over 6 percent will enable all of us to devote full energy to promoting reform, innovation, and high-quality development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济增速、就业、物价等预期目标，体现了保持经济运行在合理区间的要求，与今后目标平稳衔接，有利于实现可持续健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The projected targets for growth, employment, and CPI should keep the economy performing within the appropriate range. These targets are also well-aligned with the annual goals of subsequent years in the 14th Five-Year Plan period, and they will help sustain healthy economic growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好今年工作，要更好统筹疫情防控和经济社会发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For the government to deliver this year, we need to carry out Covid-19 prevention and control and pursue economic and social development in a more coordinated way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持常态化防控和局部应急处置有机结合，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will maintain control measures on a continuing basis and be ready to address isolated emergencies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续毫不放松做好外防输入、内防反弹工作，抓好重点区域和关键环节防控，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will maintain constant vigilance in guarding against inbound cases and domestic resurgences, and ensure effective epidemic control in key areas and at key links. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>补上短板漏洞，严防出现聚集性疫情和散发病例传播扩散，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively address all weaknesses in Covid-19 work, and take strict measures to prevent clusters of infection and transmission caused by isolated cases.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有序推进疫苗研制和加快免费接种，提高科学精准防控能力和水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The development of vaccines will be steadily advanced, free vaccine programs will be conducted at a faster pace, and efforts will be intensified to boost our capacity to control Covid-19 with targeted and science-based measures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要重点做好以下几方面工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will carry out the following tasks:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（一）保持宏观政策连续性稳定性可持续性，促进经济运行在合理区间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. Ensuring the continuity, consistency, and sustainability of macro policies to keep major economic indicators within an appropriate range</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在区间调控基础上加强定向调控、相机调控、精准调控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the basis of range-based regulation, we will enhance targeted, well-timed, and precision regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>宏观政策要继续为市场主体纾困，保持必要支持力度，不急转弯，根据形势变化适时调整完善，进一步巩固经济基本盘。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to ensure macro policies alleviate the difficulties of market entities and maintain necessary policy support for achieving this goal. We will avoid sharp turns in policy; instead, we should make adjustments and improvements based on new developments to reinforce the fundamentals of the economy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极的财政政策要提质增效、更可持续。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance the quality, efficiency, and sustainability of our proactive fiscal policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>考虑到疫情得到有效控制和经济逐步恢复，今年赤字率拟按3.2%左右安排、比去年有所下调，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In view of the effective containment of Covid-19 and gradual economic recovery, we have set the deficit-to-GDP ratio for the year at around 3.2 percent, slightly lower than that of last year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>不再发行抗疫特别国债。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>No Covid-19 bonds will be issued. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>因财政收入恢复性增长，财政支出总规模比去年增加，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As government revenue rebounds, total government expenditures will be higher this year than last. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点仍是加大对保就业保民生保市场主体的支持力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to give priority to increasing support for efforts to ensure employment, living standards, and the operations of market entities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央本级支出继续安排负增长，进一步大幅压减非急需非刚性支出，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Continued cuts will be made in central government expenditures, including considerable reductions to outlays on non-essential and non-obligatory items. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对地方一般性转移支付增长7.8%、增幅明显高于去年，其中均衡性转移支付、县级基本财力保障机制奖补资金等增幅均超过10%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>General transfer payments to local governments will be increased by 7.8 percent, which is significantly higher than last year. This will include growth of more than 10 percent in both transfer payments for equalizing access to basic public services and rewards and subsidies to ensure basic funding for county-level governments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立常态化财政资金直达机制并扩大范围，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make it a normal practice to directly allocate budgetary funds to prefecture- and county-level governments and place more funds under this mechanism.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>将2.8万亿元中央财政资金纳入直达机制、规模明显大于去年，为市县基层惠企利民提供更加及时有力的财力支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, 2.8 trillion yuan of central government funding, a figure much larger than last year, will be allocated in this way to provide timely and strong fiscal support to these local governments to benefit businesses and people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府都要节用为民、坚持过紧日子，确保基本民生支出只增不减，助力市场主体青山常在、生机盎然。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We at every level of government should practice fiscal frugality in the interests of the people. We should continue to tighten our belts, ensure continued increases in spending to meet basic living needs, and help sustain and energize market entities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化和落实减税政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement and improve tax reduction policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>市场主体恢复元气、增强活力，需要再帮一把。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to do more to help market entities stand firmly on their feet and thrive. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续执行制度性减税政策，延长小规模纳税人增值税优惠等部分阶段性政策执行期限，实施新的结构性减税举措，对冲部分政策调整带来的影响。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement systematic tax cut policies, extend the duration of several temporary policies such as VAT relief for small-scale taxpayers, and adopt new policies on structural tax reductions to offset the impact of some policy adjustments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>将小规模纳税人增值税起征点从月销售额10万元提高到15万元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The VAT threshold for small-scale taxpayers will be raised from 100,000 yuan to 150,000 yuan in monthly sales. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对小微企业和个体工商户年应纳税所得额不到100万元的部分，在现行优惠政策基础上，再减半征收所得税。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the basis of preferential policies already in force, we will halve the income tax of micro and small enterprises and self-employed individuals on annual taxable income below one million yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地要把减税政策及时落实到位，确保市场主体应享尽享。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All local governments should implement tax reduction policies fully and on a timely basis and see that market entities all enjoy these tax reduction benefits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳健的货币政策要灵活精准、合理适度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep our prudent monetary policy flexible and targeted and at a reasonable and appropriate level. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把服务实体经济放到更加突出的位置，处理好恢复经济与防范风险的关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give even greater priority to serving the real economy, and balance the needs of promoting economic recovery and preventing risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>货币供应量和社会融资规模增速与名义经济增速基本匹配，保持流动性合理充裕，保持宏观杠杆率基本稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that increases in money supply and aggregate financing are generally in step with economic growth in nominal terms, maintain a proper and adequate level of liquidity supply, and keep the macro leverage ratio generally stable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持人民币汇率在合理均衡水平上的基本稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also keep the RMB exchange rate generally stable at an adaptive, balanced level. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步解决中小微企业融资难题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Further steps will be taken to address the financing difficulties of MSMEs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>延续普惠小微企业贷款延期还本付息政策，加大再贷款再贴现支持普惠金融力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue the policy of allowing micro and small enterprises to defer principal and interest repayments on inclusive-finance loans, and increase support for inclusive finance via re-lending and rediscounting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>延长小微企业融资担保降费奖补政策，完善贷款风险分担补偿机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue the policy of providing rewards and subsidies to reduce financing guaranty fees for micro and small businesses, and improve mechanisms for risk sharing and compensation for loan defaults. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快信用信息共享步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to promote the sharing of credit information. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善金融机构考核、评价和尽职免责制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The assessment and evaluation of the performance of financial institutions will be improved, and we will ensure that those who have fulfilled their duties are not held accountable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导银行扩大信用贷款、持续增加首贷户，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Banks will be encouraged to increase credit loans and first-time loans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推广随借随还贷款，使资金更多流向科技创新、绿色发展，更多流向小微企业、个体工商户、新型农业经营主体，对受疫情持续影响行业企业给予定向支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will extend the pay-as-you-go lending model, channel more funds into scientific and technological innovation, green development initiatives, micro and small enterprises, self-employed individuals, and new types of agribusiness, and provide targeted support for enterprises and industries enduring a sustained hit from Covid-19. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大型商业银行普惠小微企业贷款增长30%以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Inclusive loans to micro and small businesses by large commercial banks will increase by over 30 percent this year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新供应链金融服务模式。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New models for providing supply chain financial services will be developed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适当降低小微企业支付手续费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Appropriate reductions will be made to transaction fees levied on micro and small businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化存款利率监管，推动实际贷款利率进一步降低，继续引导金融系统向实体经济让利。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve regulation over deposit rates, further lower loan interest rates in real terms, and continue to guide the financial sector in giving more to the real economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年务必做到小微企业融资更便利、综合融资成本稳中有降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we must see that micro and small businesses have easier access to financing, and that their overall financing costs steadily drop.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>就业优先政策要继续强化、聚力增效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve the employment-first policy to enhance its performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力稳定现有岗位，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to keep the employment situation stable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对不裁员少裁员的企业，继续给予必要的财税、金融等政策支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to provide adequate fiscal, tax, and financial policy support to businesses that do not cut jobs or only cut a small number of them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>延续降低失业和工伤保险费率，扩大失业保险返还等阶段性稳岗政策惠及范围，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reduce premiums for unemployment insurance and workers' compensation, and expand the scope of time-limited policies aimed at helping businesses maintain payrolls, such as the refunding of unemployment insurance premiums.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>延长以工代训政策实施期限。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The duration of policies on work-based training organized by companies will be extended. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓宽市场化就业渠道，促进创业带动就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will broaden channels for creating market-based employment, and leverage the role of business startups in boosting employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动降低就业门槛，动态优化国家职业资格目录，降低或取消部分准入类职业资格考试工作年限要求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The thresholds for obtaining employment will be lowered, and we will improve the national catalog of professional qualifications on a continuing basis, and relax or lift the years-of-experience requirements for taking qualification examinations for some license based professions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持和规范发展新就业形态，加快推进职业伤害保障试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of new forms of employment and keep such employment well-regulated, and we will move faster to advance trials of occupational injury insurance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续对灵活就业人员给予社保补贴，推动放开在就业地参加社会保险的户籍限制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to subsidize contributions to social insurance made by workers in flexible employment, and allow people to access social security in the locality where they work even if they do not hold local residency. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好高校毕业生、退役军人、农民工等重点群体就业工作，完善残疾人、零就业家庭成员等困难人员就业帮扶政策，促进失业人员再就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure employment for key groups such as college graduates, ex-service members, and rural migrant workers, improve policies on employment support for people facing difficulties like those with disabilities and members of zero-employment families, and help unemployed people find work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓宽职业技能培训资金使用范围，开展大规模、多层次职业技能培训，完成职业技能提升和高职扩招三年行动目标，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the scope of use for vocational skills training funds, launch large-scale, multi-level vocational skills training programs, and complete the goals of the three-year initiative on providing vocational skills training and expanding enrollment in vocational colleges.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设一批高技能人才培训基地。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A number of bases for training highly-skilled personnel will be opened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全就业公共服务体系，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The public employment services system will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施提升就业服务质量工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>An initiative will be carried out to boost the quality of employment services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>运用就业专项补助等资金，支持各类劳动力市场、人才市场、零工市场建设，广开就业门路，为有意愿有能力的人创造更多公平就业机会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use employment subsidies and other funds to support the development of labor, talent, and casual labor markets, so as to widen the avenues of employment and enable people who are willing and able to work to find more equitable job opportunities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（二）深入推进重点领域改革，更大激发市场主体活力。在落实助企纾困政策的同时，加大力度推动相关改革，培育更加活跃更有创造力的市场主体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2. Advancing reforms in key areas and further energizing market entities  While implementing policies to ease enterprises' difficulties, we will also intensify reforms to foster more dynamic and innovative market entities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步转变政府职能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further transform the functions of government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分发挥市场在资源配置中的决定性作用，更好发挥政府作用，推动有效市场和有为政府更好结合。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully leverage the decisive role of the market in allocating resources and give better play to the role of government, to ensure better alignment between an efficient market and a well-functioning government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续放宽市场准入，开展要素市场化配置综合改革试点，依法平等保护各类市场主体产权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to expand market access, pilot a comprehensive reform on the market-based allocation of production factors, and ensure equal protection for the property rights of various market entities in accordance with the law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>纵深推进“放管服”改革，加快营造市场化、法治化、国际化营商环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reforms to streamline administration and delegate power, improve regulation, and upgrade services and, move faster to create a market-oriented, law-based, and internationalized business environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>将行政许可事项全部纳入清单管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will practice list-based management for all items requiring administrative approval. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化“证照分离”改革，大力推进涉企审批减环节、减材料、减时限、减费用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will advance the reform for separating operating permits from business licenses, and devote major efforts to reducing the procedures, documents, time, and expenses required for government review of applications by enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善市场主体退出机制，实行中小微企业简易注销制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The mechanism for market entities to exit the market will be refined, and the system for deregistering MSMEs with simplified procedures will be implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施工业产品准入制度改革，推进汽车、电子电器等行业生产准入和流通管理全流程改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform the system of market access for industrial products, and advance reform of the entire management process, from production access to marketing, for several industries such as the automobile, electronic, and electric appliances industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把有效监管作为简政放权的必要保障，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Effective regulation is necessary for our efforts to streamline administration and delegate power. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面落实监管责任，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that all regulatory responsibilities of government are fulfilled. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对取消或下放审批事项的事中事后监管，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen ongoing and ex post oversight of items for which approval has been cancelled or delegated to lower-level authorities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善分级分类监管政策，健全跨部门综合监管制度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will refine regulatory policies covering different levels and categories, and improve the system of comprehensive inter-agency regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推行“互联网+监管”，提升监管能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also advance the Internet plus regulation model to enhance our capacity for conducting regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大失信惩处力度，以公正监管促进优胜劣汰。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will impose stiffer penalties on acts of bad faith, and carry out regulation in an impartial way to ensure that well-performing businesses succeed in market competition and those which are poorly run are eliminated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强数字政府建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to build a digital government.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全政务数据共享协调机制，推动电子证照扩大应用领域和全国互通互认，实现更多政务服务事项网上办、掌上办、一次办。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will set up a sound coordination mechanism for sharing government data, expand the application, and promote mutual nationwide recognition, of electronic licenses and certificates, and ensure more government services are accessible online and on cellphone applications with the need for only one application process. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>企业和群众经常办理的事项，今年要基本实现“跨省通办”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, high-demand government services should generally be provided on an inter-provincial basis.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>用改革办法推动降低企业生产经营成本。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to reduce enterprises' production and operating costs through reform.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进能源、交通、电信等基础性行业改革，提高服务效率，降低收费水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will advance the reform of basic sectors like energy, transportation and telecommunications to provide more efficient services and reduce charges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>允许所有制造业企业参与电力市场化交易，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All manufacturing enterprises will be allowed to engage in market-based electricity transactions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步清理用电不合理加价，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Further steps will be taken to cut unjustified surcharges on electricity use;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推动降低一般工商业电价。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>electricity rates for general industrial and commercial businesses will be further reduced. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中小企业宽带和专线平均资费再降10%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Average rates for broadband and dedicated internet access services for small and medium enterprises will be lowered by another 10 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推广高速公路差异化收费，坚决整治违规设置妨碍货车通行的道路限高限宽设施和检查卡点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will introduce differentiated pricing for expressway tolls nationwide and take firm measures to rectify irregular height and width limits and checkpoints that affect freight traffic. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>取消港口建设费，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The port development fee will be abolished.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>将民航发展基金航空公司征收标准降低20%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Airlines' contributions to the civil aviation development fund will be cut by 20 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励受疫情影响较大的地方对承租国有房屋的服务业小微企业和个体工商户减免租金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments in localities that were hit hard by Covid-19 will be encouraged to lower or waive rentals on state-owned property for micro and small businesses in the service sector and for self-employed individuals. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动各类中介机构公开服务条件、流程、时限和收费标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Various intermediary agencies will be urged to make public their terms of service, procedures, timeframes, and charges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要严控非税收入不合理增长，严厉整治乱收费、乱罚款、乱摊派，不得扰民渔利，让市场主体安心经营、轻装前行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Unjustified growth in non-tax government revenue will be strictly checked, tough steps will be taken to end arbitrary charges, fines, and quotas, and no action that seeks to make gains at the expense of our people and businesses will be tolerated. All these efforts will lighten the burden on market entities and enable them to focus on doing business free from undue concern.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进多种所有制经济共同发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the common development of enterprises under diverse forms of ownership. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持和完善社会主义基本经济制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to practice and improve the basic socialist economic system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>毫不动摇巩固和发展公有制经济，毫不动摇鼓励、支持、引导非公有制经济发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work unswervingly to both consolidate and develop the public sector and encourage, support, and guide the development of the non-public sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各类市场主体都是国家现代化的建设者，要一视同仁、平等对待。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All market entities, regardless of their type, are participants in China's modernization endeavors, and each and every one of them must be treated as equals. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施国企改革三年行动，做强做优做大国有资本和国有企业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement the three-year action plan for SOE reform, and work to strengthen, expand, and increase the returns on state capital and enhance the strength, quality, and size of SOEs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化国有企业混合所有制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also push ahead with mixed-ownership reform in SOEs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建亲清政商关系，破除制约民营企业发展的各种壁垒。健全防范和化解拖欠中小企业账款长效机制。弘扬企业家精神。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build a cordial and clean relationship between government and business, remove barriers to the development of private businesses, improve the long-term mechanism for preventing and resolving late payments to small and medium businesses, and promote an entrepreneurial spirit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家支持平台企业创新发展、增强国际竞争力，同时要依法规范发展，健全数字规则。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The state supports platform enterprises in pursuing innovative development and enhancing international competitiveness; it will ensure that their business operations are well-regulated in accordance with the law and take steps to refine digital rules. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化反垄断和防止资本无序扩张，坚决维护公平竞争市场环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up efforts against business monopolies and guard against unregulated expansion of capital, and ensure fair market competition.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化财税金融体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reforms of the fiscal, taxation, and financial systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化预算约束和绩效管理，加大预算公开力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen budget constraints and performance management, and promote greater budget transparency.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>精简享受税费优惠政策的办理流程和手续。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Procedures for accessing preferential tax and fee policies will be streamlined. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实中央与地方财政事权和支出责任划分改革方案。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The reform plan for defining the respective fiscal powers and expenditure responsibilities of central and local governments will be implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全地方税体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The local tax systems will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续多渠道补充中小银行资本、强化公司治理，深化农村信用社改革，推进政策性银行分类分账改革，提升保险保障和服务功能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to replenish capital and strengthen corporate governance of small and medium banks through multiple channels, deepen the reform of rural credit cooperatives, advance the reform on policy banks by carrying out category-based management for specific accounts, and strengthen the role of insurance in protecting against risks and providing services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推进注册制改革，完善常态化退市机制，加强债券市场建设，更好发挥多层次资本市场作用，拓展市场主体融资渠道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will steadily advance the reform to establish a registration-based IPO system, improve delisting as a normal practice, and step up development of the bond market, so as to better exert the role of multi-level capital markets and open up more financing channels for market entities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化金融控股公司和金融科技监管，确保金融创新在审慎监管的前提下进行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen regulation over financial holding companies and financial technology to ensure that financial innovations are made under prudent regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善金融风险处置工作机制，压实各方责任，坚决守住不发生系统性风险的底线。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the mechanism for managing financial risks, see responsibilities are fulfilled by all the stakeholders, and ensure that no systemic risks arise. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>金融机构要坚守服务实体经济的本分。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Financial institutions must serve the real economy as they should do.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（三）依靠创新推动实体经济高质量发展，培育壮大新动能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. Promoting high-quality development of the real economy through innovation and fostering new growth drivers</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进科技创新与实体经济深度融合，更好发挥创新驱动发展作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that scientific and technological innovations are fully applied in the real economy, and we will better leverage the role of innovation in driving development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升科技创新能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will raise our capacity for pursuing scientific and technological innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化国家战略科技力量，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve our strategic scientific and technological strength. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进国家实验室建设，完善科技项目和创新基地布局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The building of national laboratories will continue, and the layout of science and technology programs and innovation centers will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施好关键核心技术攻关工程，深入谋划推进“科技创新2030－重大项目”，改革科技重大专项实施方式，推广“揭榜挂帅”等机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure the success of projects launched to achieve breakthroughs in core technologies in key fields, further plan and implement the Sci-Tech Innovation 2030 Agenda, reform the way that major science and technology programs are implemented, and extend mechanisms, such as the open competition mechanism to select the best candidates to undertake key research projects, to more areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持有条件的地方建设国际和区域科技创新中心，增强国家自主创新示范区等带动作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We support localities with requisite conditions to develop international and regional centers for science and technology innovation, and better leverage the guiding role of institutions such as national innovation demonstration zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展疾病防治攻关等民生科技。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We encourage advances in science and technology that promote people's wellbeing, such as breakthroughs in the prevention and control of diseases. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进科技开放合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We also encourage opening up and international cooperation in the science and technology sector,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强知识产权保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we are firmly committed to protecting intellectual property. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强科研诚信建设，弘扬科学精神，营造良好创新生态。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will heighten awareness of research integrity, promote the spirit of science, and create a favorable ecosystem for innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>基础研究是科技创新的源头，要健全稳定支持机制，大幅增加投入，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Basic research is the wellspring of scientific and technological innovation. So we will ensure the stable functioning of funding mechanisms for basic research and boost spending in this area by a considerable sum. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央本级基础研究支出增长10.6%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government expenditures on basic research will increase by 10.6 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实扩大经费使用自主权政策，优化项目申报、评审、经费管理、人才评价和激励机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Research institutes will have more say about how funds should be used, and the mechanisms for project applications, assessments, fund management, and personnel evaluations and incentives will be refined.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力消除科研人员不合理负担，使他们能够沉下心来致力科学探索，以“十年磨一剑”精神在关键核心领域实现重大突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to help researchers get rid of undue burdens and enable them to fully devote their time and energy to making scientific explorations and major breakthroughs in key technologies, just as a blacksmith in the past would spend years forging the perfect sword.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>运用市场化机制激励企业创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will leverage market forces to encourage enterprises to engage in innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化企业创新主体地位，鼓励领军企业组建创新联合体，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost the principal role of enterprises in innovation, and encourage leading enterprises to establish innovation consortia.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓展产学研用融合通道，健全科技成果产权激励机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the channels that bring together enterprises, universities, research institutes and end-users, and refine the equity-based incentive mechanisms for scientific and technological advances. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善创业投资监管体制和发展政策，纵深推进大众创业万众创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the regulatory system and development policies for venture capital, and further promote business startups and innovation initiatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>延续执行企业研发费用加计扣除75%政策，将制造业企业加计扣除比例提高到100%，用税收优惠机制激励企业加大研发投入，着力推动企业以创新引领发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement the policy of granting an extra tax deduction of 75 percent on enterprises' R&amp;D costs, and we will raise this to 100 percent for manufacturing enterprises. By employing such mechanisms for preferential tax treatment, we can encourage enterprises to increase R&amp;D spending and pursue innovation-driven development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化和稳定产业链供应链。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure the stable operation of industrial and supply chains and improve them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续完成“三去一降一补”重要任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue working on the five priority tasks of cutting overcapacity, reducing excess housing inventory, deleveraging, lowering costs, and strengthening areas of weakness. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对先进制造业企业按月全额退还增值税增量留抵税额，提高制造业贷款比重，扩大制造业设备更新和技术改造投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will refund all due VAT credits to advanced manufacturing enterprises on a monthly basis, raise the proportion of loans to the manufacturing sector, and increase investment in the equipment upgrades and technology transformations of manufacturing enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增强产业链供应链自主可控能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that industrial and supply chains are more self-supporting and that their risks are better controlled.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施好产业基础再造工程，发挥大企业引领支撑和中小微企业协作配套作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement projects for upgrading foundational industrial infrastructure and give full play to large enterprises' capacity to provide leadership and support, and to the collaborative and supporting role of MSMEs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展工业互联网，促进产业链和创新链融合，搭建更多共性技术研发平台，提升中小微企业创新能力和专业化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further develop the industrial internet, promote the integration of industrial and innovation chains, and build additional platforms for generic technology R&amp;D to enhance the capacity of MSMEs for making innovations and engaging in specialized production. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大5G网络和千兆光网建设力度，丰富应用场景。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The development of the 5G networks and 1000M fiber optic networks will be stepped up and their application will be extended to more settings. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强网络安全、数据安全和个人信息保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Cybersecurity, data security, and personal information protection will be strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹新兴产业布局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The layout of emerging industries will be planned in a well-coordinated way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强质量基础设施建设，深入实施质量提升行动，完善标准体系，促进产业链上下游标准有效衔接，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's National Quality Infrastructure will be strengthened, intensified efforts will be made to enhance quality, and the system of standards will be improved to ensure standards are aligned throughout the industrial chain.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>弘扬工匠精神，以精工细作提升中国制造品质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will champion the pursuit of fine workmanship to boost the quality of Chinese manufacturing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（四）坚持扩大内需这个战略基点，充分挖掘国内市场潜力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. Expanding domestic demand as a strategic move and fully tapping the potential of the domestic market</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>紧紧围绕改善民生拓展需求，促进消费与投资有效结合，实现供需更高水平动态平衡。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With a focus on improving the people's wellbeing, we will expand demand, and promote better alignment between consumption and investment, so as to attain a more desirable and dynamic equilibrium between supply and demand.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定和扩大消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will stabilize and expand consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>多渠道增加居民收入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Personal incomes will be increased through multiple channels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全城乡流通体系，加快电商、快递进农村，扩大县乡消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Networks for the flow of goods and services in urban and rural areas will be improved, and rural e-commerce and express delivery services will be expanded to spur greater consumption at the county and township levels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定增加汽车、家电等大宗消费，取消对二手车交易不合理限制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage steady increases in spending on home appliances, automobiles, and other big-ticket items, and abolish excessive restrictions on sales of second-hand vehicles.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加停车场、充电桩、换电站等设施，加快建设动力电池回收利用体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More car parks and electric vehicle battery charging and swapping facilities will be built, and the system for recycling power batteries will be developed at a faster pace. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展健康、文化、旅游、体育等服务消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumption of services such as healthcare, culture, tourism, and sports will be promoted. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励企业创新产品和服务，便利新产品市场准入，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Enterprises are encouraged to develop new products and services, and better market access will be provided for new products.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进内外贸产品同线同标同质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that products sold domestically are produced on the same production lines, meet the same standards, and are of the same quality as exported products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障小店商铺等便民服务业有序运营。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that convenience stores, shops, and other neighborhood services are well-run. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>运用好“互联网+”，推进线上线下更广更深融合，发展新业态新模式，为消费者提供更多便捷舒心的服务和产品。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use the Internet Plus model to promote integrated development of online and offline businesses in more fields and create new forms and models of business, thus providing more convenient and satisfying services for consumers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导平台企业合理降低商户服务费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also encourage platform companies to reduce their service fees as appropriate. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步提高消费能力，改善消费环境，让居民能消费、愿消费，以促进民生改善和经济发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By taking these steps, we will steadily improve people's consumption capacity and the environment for consumption and ensure that our people have the ability and willingness to spend, thus improving their lives and driving economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大有效投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand effective investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年拟安排地方政府专项债券3.65万亿元，优化债券资金使用，优先支持在建工程，合理扩大使用范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, 3.65 trillion yuan of local government special-purpose bonds will be issued and the way funds from bond issues are used will be improved. The scope of use for such bonds will be expanded as appropriate, with priority given to funding for key projects already under construction. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央预算内投资安排6100亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will earmark a total of 610 billion yuan for investment in its budget. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续支持促进区域协调发展的重大工程，推进“两新一重”建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to support the construction of major projects that facilitate coordinated development among regions, and launch new infrastructure and new urbanization initiatives as well as major projects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施一批交通、能源、水利等重大工程项目，建设信息网络等新型基础设施，发展现代物流体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also launch a number of major transportation, energy, and water conservancy projects, develop information networks and other new types of infrastructure, and work to modernize the logistics system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府投资更多向惠及面广的民生项目倾斜，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government investment will be weighted toward projects which will help significantly improve the people's wellbeing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新开工改造城镇老旧小区5.3万个，提升县城公共服务水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Rebuilding and renovation of 53,000 old urban residential communities will begin, and the public service standards of county towns will be raised. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>简化投资审批程序，推进实施企业投资项目承诺制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Investment approval procedures will be streamlined, and the business-invested project commitment system will be put into practice. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化工程建设项目审批制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Reform of the system for construction project approval will be furthered. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善支持社会资本参与政策，进一步拆除妨碍民间投资的各种藩篱，在更多领域让社会资本进得来、能发展、有作为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve our policies for encouraging the participation of nongovernmental capital, and do more to remove barriers impeding private investment, so that such investment can enter, develop, and yield good returns in more fields.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（五）全面实施乡村振兴战略，促进农业稳定发展和农民增收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>5. Implementing the rural revitalization strategy across the board and promoting steady development of agriculture and growth in rural incomes</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>接续推进脱贫地区发展，抓好农业生产，改善农村生产生活条件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to promote the development of areas that have been lifted out of poverty, bolster agricultural production, and improve working and living conditions in rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好巩固拓展脱贫攻坚成果同乡村振兴有效衔接。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will align efforts to consolidate and expand the achievements in poverty alleviation with efforts to promote rural revitalization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对脱贫县从脱贫之日起设立5年过渡期，保持主要帮扶政策总体稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For counties lifted out of poverty, a five-year transition period will apply from the date poverty in their locality was eradicated, during which major assistance policies will remain unchanged for them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全防止返贫动态监测和帮扶机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Continuous monitoring and assistance mechanisms will be enhanced to prevent populations that have been lifted out of poverty from falling back into it again. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进脱贫人口稳定就业，加大技能培训力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Stable employment for these populations should be ensured, and more skills training will be made available to them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展壮大脱贫地区产业，做好易地搬迁后续扶持，分层分类加强对农村低收入人口常态化帮扶，确保不发生规模性返贫。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further develop industries in areas that are no longer in poverty, provide follow-up support for those who have been relocated from inhospitable areas, and enhance regular and tiered assistance of various types to low-income rural residents. These steps will forestall a large-scale reemergence of poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在西部地区脱贫县中集中支持一批乡村振兴重点帮扶县。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A number of counties lifted out of poverty in western China will be designated as key counties for receiving assistance for rural revitalization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持和完善东西部协作和对口支援机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The mechanisms for collaboration between the eastern and western regions and for providing paired assistance will remain in place and be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥中央单位和社会力量帮扶作用，继续支持脱贫地区增强内生发展能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central departments and organizations as well as non-governmental actors will continue to play their roles in providing assistance. All these efforts will help those areas which have been lifted out of poverty enhance their capacity for sustaining self-development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高粮食和重要农产品供给保障能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance our ability to ensure the supply of food and major agricultural products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障粮食安全的要害是种子和耕地。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Seeds and cropland are crucial for safeguarding China's food security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要加强种质资源保护利用和优良品种选育推广，开展农业关键核心技术攻关。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the protection and use of germplasm resources and the breeding and application of fine crop varieties, and strive to make key technological breakthroughs in agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高高标准农田建设标准和质量，完善灌溉设施，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The standards for maintaining high-quality farmland will be raised, and irrigation facilities will be improved.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化耕地保护，坚决遏制耕地“非农化”、防止“非粮化”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance the protection of cropland, and resolutely stop any attempt to use it for purposes other than agriculture and specifically grain production. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进农业机械化、智能化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote mechanization and digitalization of agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设国家粮食安全产业带和农业现代化示范区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Agricultural belts for national food security and demonstration zones for agricultural modernization will be developed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定种粮农民补贴，适度提高稻谷、小麦最低收购价，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Subsidies for grain growers will be maintained, and minimum purchase prices for rice and wheat will be increased as appropriate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大完全成本和收入保险试点范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pilot insurance programs covering total production costs and incomes will be expanded. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定粮食播种面积，提高单产和品质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Grain acreage will be kept stable, per unit crop yield will be increased, and the quality of grains will be raised. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>多措并举扩大油料生产。发展畜禽水产养殖，稳定和发展生猪生产。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adopt multiple measures to expand the production of oil-bearing crops, develop livestock, poultry, and aquaculture farming, and promote stable hog production. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强动植物疫病防控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Prevention and control of animal and plant diseases will be enhanced. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障农产品市场供应和价格基本稳定。开展粮食节约行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure stability in the supply and prices of agricultural products, and launch food saving initiatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>解决好吃饭问题始终是头等大事，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Ensuring that our people have enough food remains a top priority for our government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们一定要下力气也完全有能力保障好14亿人的粮食安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We are resolved to ensure food security for our 1.4 billion people, and we know we can achieve this.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进农村改革和乡村建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take solid steps in advancing rural reform and development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>巩固和完善农村基本经营制度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will consolidate and improve the system of basic rural operations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持土地承包关系稳定并长久不变，稳步推进多种形式适度规模经营，加快发展专业化社会化服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep rural land contract relationships unchanged over the long term, steadily promote appropriately scaled agribusiness operations of various types, and speed up the development of specialized and commercial services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳慎推进农村宅基地制度改革试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Trials for the reform of rural residential land will be advanced in a steady and prudent fashion. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展新型农村集体经济。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New rural collective economies will be developed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化供销社、集体林权、国有林区林场、农垦等改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Reforms of supply and marketing cooperatives, collective forest tenure, state forestry areas and farms, and state farms will be deepened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高土地出让收入用于农业农村比例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More of the revenue from land sales will be spent on agriculture and rural development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化农村基本公共服务和公共基础设施建设，促进县域内城乡融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen basic public services and infrastructure construction in rural areas and promote integrated urban-rural development in counties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动农村人居环境整治提升五年行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A five-year program to improve the rural living environment will be launched,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农村精神文明建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and cultural and ethical standards in rural areas will be raised. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障农民工工资及时足额支付。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that rural migrant workers receive their pay on time and in full. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快发展乡村产业，壮大县域经济，加强对返乡创业的支持，拓宽农民就业渠道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote faster development of rural industries, strengthen county economies, and provide more support for migrant workers to start businesses in their hometowns, so as to enable rural people to seek employment through more channels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>千方百计使亿万农民多增收、有奔头。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do our utmost to see that rural residents in their hundreds of millions can earn higher incomes and embrace a brighter future.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（六）实行高水平对外开放，促进外贸外资稳中提质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>6. Pursuing high-standard opening up and promoting stable and improved performance in foreign trade and investment</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施更大范围、更宽领域、更深层次对外开放，更好参与国际经济合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will open up more sectors of the economy in a more thorough fashion and participate more fully in international economic cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动进出口稳定发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote steady growth of imports and exports. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对中小外贸企业信贷支持，扩大出口信用保险覆盖面、优化承保和理赔条件，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase credit support to small and medium foreign trade firms, expand the coverage of export credit insurance and streamline the conditions for insurance acceptance and claims settlement.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化贸易外汇收支便利化试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Trials to facilitate foreign exchange settlement for trade firms will be advanced. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳定加工贸易，发展跨境电商等新业态新模式，支持企业开拓多元化市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep the processing trade stable, develop new forms and models of trade such as cross-border e-commerce, and support enterprises in diversifying their markets overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展边境贸易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also develop border trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新发展服务贸易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New approaches will be explored to develop trade in services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化调整进口税收政策，增加优质产品和服务进口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and adjust import tariff policies and increase imports of quality products and services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强贸易促进服务，办好进博会、广交会、服贸会及首届中国国际消费品博览会等重大展会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Trade promotion services will be improved, and good preparations will be made for holding major trade events such as the China International Import Expo, the China Import and Export Fair, the China International Fair for Trade in Services, and the first China International Consumer Products Expo. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动国际物流畅通，清理规范口岸收费，不断提升通关便利化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure smooth international logistics services, overhaul and standardize port charges, and further simplify customs clearance.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极有效利用外资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use foreign investment more effectively. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步缩减外资准入负面清单。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The negative list for foreign investment will be further cut. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动服务业有序开放，增设服务业扩大开放综合试点，制定跨境服务贸易负面清单。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will open the service sector in a well-regulated way, launch more comprehensive trials on its opening, and formulate a negative list for cross-border trade in services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进海南自由贸易港建设，加强自贸试验区改革开放创新，推动海关特殊监管区域与自贸试验区统筹发展，发挥好各类开发区开放平台作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further the development of the Hainan Free Trade Port, pursue reform, opening up, and innovation in pilot free trade zones, promote coordinated development of special customs regulation zones and pilot free trade zones, and fully leverage the role of economic development zones as platforms for opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进内外资企业公平竞争，依法保护外资企业合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote fair competition between domestic and foreign companies and protect the lawful rights and interests of foreign-invested enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>欢迎外商扩大在华投资，分享中国开放的大市场和发展机遇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Foreign investors are welcome to expand their investments in China and share in its vast open market and development opportunities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高质量共建“一带一路”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote high-quality Belt and Road cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持共商共建共享，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We are committed to the principle of achieving shared growth through consultation and collaboration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以企业为主体、遵循市场化原则，健全多元化投融资体系，强化法律服务保障，有序推动重大项目合作，推进基础设施互联互通。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, with enterprises as the main actors and acting on market principles, set up a sound, diversified investment and financing framework, provide better legal services and safeguards, and work to steadily advance cooperation on major projects and promote infrastructure connectivity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升对外投资合作质量效益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to improve the performance of China's outbound investment and international cooperation in this area.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化多双边和区域经济合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen multilateral, bilateral, and regional economic cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚定维护多边贸易体制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to uphold the multilateral trading regime. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动区域全面经济伙伴关系协定尽早生效实施、中欧投资协定签署，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work for the early entry into force and implementation of the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement and the signing of the China-EU Comprehensive Agreement on Investment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快中日韩自贸协定谈判进程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate China's free trade negotiations with Japan and the Republic of Korea. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极考虑加入全面与进步跨太平洋伙伴关系协定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China will actively consider joining the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在相互尊重基础上，推动中美平等互利经贸关系向前发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the growth of mutually beneficial China-US business relations on the basis of equality and mutual respect. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国愿与世界各国扩大相互开放，实现互利共赢。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China stands ready to work with other countries to achieve mutual benefits on the basis of greater mutual opening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（七）加强污染防治和生态建设，持续改善环境质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>7. Enhancing Pollution Prevention and Control and Ecological Conservation and Promoting Continuous Environmental Improvement</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施可持续发展战略，巩固蓝天、碧水、净土保卫战成果，促进生产生活方式绿色转型。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the sustainable development strategy, consolidate the gains in our endeavors to keep our skies blue, our waters clear, and our lands pollution-free, and transition to eco-friendly production and ways of life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续加大生态环境治理力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to intensify efforts to improve the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化大气污染综合治理和联防联控，加强细颗粒物和臭氧协同控制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen comprehensive measures and joint efforts on air pollution prevention and control, and step up coordination on the control of fine particulate matter and ozone pollution.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>北方地区清洁取暖率达到70%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Clean heating will account for 70 percent of all heating in northern China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>整治入河入海排污口和城市黑臭水体，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will clean up sewage outfalls into seas and rivers and black, malodorous water bodies in cities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高城镇生活污水收集和园区工业废水处置能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance our capacity to collect urban household sewage and to treat waste water from industrial parks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格土壤污染源头防控，加强农业面源污染治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take stringent measures to prevent soil pollution at the source, and take stronger action to address agricultural pollution from non-point sources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续严禁洋垃圾入境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The ban on the importation of solid waste will remain in place. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有序推进城镇生活垃圾分类处置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Urban household waste sorting will be promoted in a well-planned way,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动快递包装绿色转型。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the use of eco-friendly express delivery packaging will be encouraged,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强危险废物医疗废物收集处理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and the collection and treatment of hazardous waste and medical waste will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>研究制定生态保护补偿条例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The formulation of regulations on compensation for environmental conservation will be put on the agenda. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实长江十年禁渔，实施生物多样性保护重大工程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enforce a ten-year fishing ban in the waters of the Yangtze River, and carry out major biodiversity protection projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>科学推进荒漠化、石漠化、水土流失综合治理，持续开展大规模国土绿化行动，保护海洋生态环境，推进生态系统保护和修复，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will systematically promote comprehensive control of desertification, rocky desertification, and soil erosion, continue to launch large-scale land greening programs, protect the marine environment, and protect and restore ecosystems.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>让我们生活的家园拥有更多碧水蓝天。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We hope that our common home will have clearer waters and the skies above it will be bluer.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实做好碳达峰、碳中和各项工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take solid steps toward the goals of achieving peak carbon dioxide emissions and carbon neutrality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定2030年前碳排放达峰行动方案。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw up an action plan for carbon emissions to peak by 2030. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化产业结构和能源结构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's industrial structure and energy mix will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动煤炭清洁高效利用，大力发展新能源，在确保安全的前提下积极有序发展核电。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While promoting the clean and efficient use of coal, we will make a major push to develop new energy sources, and take active and well-ordered steps to develop nuclear energy on the basis of ensuring its safe use. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大环境保护、节能节水等企业所得税优惠目录范围，促进新型节能环保技术、装备和产品研发应用，培育壮大节能环保产业，推动资源节约高效利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the catalog of corporate income tax credits for environmental protection and the conservation of water and energy, and promote the development and application of new types of energy-efficient and eco-friendly technologies, equipment and products, and the cultivation of energy-saving and environmental protection industries to ensure the conservation and efficient use of resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建设全国用能权、碳排放权交易市场，完善能源消费双控制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of national markets for trading energy use rights and carbon emissions rights, and improve the system to control both the total amount and intensity of energy consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施金融支持绿色低碳发展专项政策，设立碳减排支持工具。提升生态系统碳汇能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will introduce special policies on providing financial support for green and low-carbon development, devise instruments for supporting the reduction of carbon emissions, and enhance the carbon absorption capacity of ecosystems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国作为地球村的一员，将以实际行动为全球应对气候变化作出应有贡献。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As a member of the global village, China will continue to take concrete action to play its part in the global response to climate change.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（八）切实增进民生福祉，不断提高社会建设水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>8. Improving living standards and steadily advancing social development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>注重解民忧、纾民困，及时回应群众关切，持续改善人民生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, with a focus on resolving the difficulties of our people, respond promptly to public concerns and continue working to improve people's lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展更加公平更高质量的教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop more equitable and higher-quality education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建德智体美劳全面培养的教育体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build an education system that ensures the well-rounded development of students in terms of moral grounding, intellectual and physical ability, aesthetic sensibility, and work skills. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动义务教育优质均衡发展和城乡一体化，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote high-quality, well-balanced, and integrated development of compulsory education in both urban and rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快补齐农村办学条件短板，健全教师工资保障长效机制，改善乡村教师待遇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work quickly to improve the basic conditions of rural schools, refine the long-term mechanism for ensuring salary payments to teachers, and improve the pay packages of teachers in rural schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步提高学前教育入园率，完善普惠性学前教育保障机制，支持社会力量办园。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will raise the preschool enrollment ratio, improve the mechanism to support public-interest pre-school education, and support private actors in running kindergartens. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励高中阶段学校多样化发展，加强县域高中建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the diversified development of senior secondary schools and the development of county high schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增强职业教育适应性，深化产教融合、校企合作，深入实施职业技能等级证书制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance the adaptability of vocational education, deepen industry-education integration and school-enterprise cooperation, and implement the system of vocational technical grade certificates. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>办好特殊教育、继续教育，支持和规范民办教育发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide high-quality special needs education and continuing education, and support the development of private schools in a well-regulated way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>分类建设一流大学和一流学科，加快优化学科专业结构，加强基础学科和前沿学科建设，促进新兴交叉学科发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop first-rate universities and academic disciplines on a categorized basis, move faster to improve the composition of disciplines and majors, and promote the development of foundational disciplines, cutting-edge disciplines, and emerging inter-disciplinary fields. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持中西部高等教育发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of higher education in the central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大国家通用语言文字推广力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts to promote standard spoken and written Chinese will be stepped up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥在线教育优势，完善终身学习体系。倡导全社会尊师重教。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give full play to the advantages of online education, improve the lifelong learning system, and encourage public respect for teachers and public support for education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化教育评价改革，健全学校家庭社会协同育人机制，规范校外培训。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further the reform of educational assessment, improve the mechanism of school-family-society cooperation in educating students, and keep off-campus training well-regulated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强师德师风建设。在教育公平上迈出更大步伐，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the professional ethics and competence of teachers, and make major strides in ensuring equitable education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更好解决进城务工人员子女就学问题，高校招生继续加大对中西部和农村地区倾斜力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will endeavor to provide better schooling for children of rural migrant workers in cities, and continue to have universities and colleges enroll more students from the central and western regions and rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力让广大学生健康快乐成长，让每个孩子都有人生出彩的机会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that students live healthy and happy lives and that every child has the opportunity to fulfill their potential.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进卫生健康体系建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the healthcare system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持预防为主，持续推进健康中国行动，深入开展爱国卫生运动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, with emphasis on prevention, continue to advance the Healthy China initiative and carry out extensive patriotic health campaigns. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化疾病预防控制体系改革，强化基层公共卫生体系，创新医防协同机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the system for disease prevention and control, strengthen community-level public health systems, and develop new mechanisms for enhancing coordination between disease prevention and control agencies and hospitals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全公共卫生应急处置和物资保障体系，建立稳定的公共卫生事业投入机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the system for responding to public health emergencies and providing emergency supplies, and put in place a mechanism for ensuring stable funding for public health institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强精神卫生和心理健康服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will attach greater importance to mental and psychological health. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化公立医院综合改革，扩大国家医学中心和区域医疗中心建设试点，加强全科医生和乡村医生队伍建设，提升县级医疗服务能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will advance the comprehensive reform of public hospitals, expand trials on setting up national medical centers and regional medical centers, strengthen the ranks of general practitioners and rural doctors, and improve the capacity of medical services at the county level.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建设分级诊疗体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The tiered diagnosis and treatment system will be developed at a faster pace. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持中西医并重，实施中医药振兴发展重大工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support both traditional Chinese medicine and Western medicine, and a major project will be launched to promote the development of traditional Chinese medicine. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持社会办医，促进“互联网+医疗健康”规范发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of private hospitals, and promote well-regulated growth of Internet Plus Healthcare initiatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化食品药品疫苗监管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will tighten regulation and supervision of food, drugs, and vaccines. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化预约诊疗等便民措施，努力让大病、急难病患者尽早得到治疗。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take steps to make medical treatment more accessible, such as simplifying medical appointment procedures, so as to ensure that patients with severe, acute, or hard-to-treat diseases receive treatment as soon as possible. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民医保和基本公共卫生服务经费人均财政补助标准分别再增加30元和5元，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government subsidies for basic medical insurance for rural and non-working urban residents will increase by an average of 30 yuan per person, and subsides for basic public health services will increase by 5 yuan per person.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动基本医保省级统筹、门诊费用跨省直接结算。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote provincial-level unified management of basic medical insurance funds and realize inter-provincial on-the-spot settlement of outpatient bills through individual accounts for basic medical insurance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全门诊共济保障机制，逐步将门诊费用纳入统筹基金报销，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also develop a general support mechanism for covering outpatient medical bills, and take gradual steps toward reimbursing outpatient bills through unified accounts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善短缺药品保供稳价机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the mechanism for ensuring provision of medicines in short supply and keeping their prices stable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>采取把更多慢性病、常见病药品和高值医用耗材纳入集中带量采购等办法，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More medicines for chronic and common illnesses and high-priced medical consumables will be covered by bulk government purchases. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步明显降低患者医药负担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These are all steps that will lighten the burden on patients by another considerable margin.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障好群众住房需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strive to meet people's housing needs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持房子是用来住的、不是用来炒的定位，稳地价、稳房价、稳预期。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Upholding the principle that housing is for living in, not for speculation, we will keep the prices of land and housing as well as market expectations stable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>解决好大城市住房突出问题，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will address prominent housing issues in large cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>通过增加土地供应、安排专项资金、集中建设等办法，切实增加保障性租赁住房和共有产权住房供给，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By increasing land supply, earmarking special funds, and carrying out concentrated development schemes, we will increase the supply of government-subsidized rental housing and shared ownership housing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>规范发展长租房市场，降低租赁住房税费负担，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure well-regulated development of the long-term rental housing market, and cut taxes and fees on rental housing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>尽最大努力帮助新市民、青年人等缓解住房困难。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make every effort to address the housing difficulties faced by our people, especially new urban residents and young people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强基本民生保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do more to meet people's basic living needs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高退休人员基本养老金、优抚对象抚恤和生活补助标准。推进基本养老保险全国统筹，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase the basic pension for retirees and the subsidies and living allowances for entitled groups, and work toward unified national management of basic old-age insurance funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>规范发展第三支柱养老保险。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As the third pillar, private pensions will develop in a well-regulated way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善全国统一的社会保险公共服务平台。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The national social insurance public service platform will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强军人军属、退役军人和其他优抚对象优待工作，健全退役军人工作体系和保障制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase the benefits for service members and their families, ex-service members, and other entitled groups, while also refining our work systems and support mechanisms for ex-service members. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施失业保险保障扩围政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The coverage of unemployment insurance will be further expanded. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进医养康养相结合，稳步推进长期护理保险制度试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the integration of medical care and health care, and steadily advance trials of long-term care insurance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展普惠型养老服务和互助性养老。发展婴幼儿照护服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop public-interest elderly care services and mutual-aid elderly care, as well as infant and child care services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展社区养老、托幼、用餐、保洁等多样化服务，加强配套设施和无障碍设施建设，实施更优惠政策，让社区生活更加便利。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop diversified community services, including elderly care, child care, dining services, and cleaning services, build more supporting facilities and barrier-free facilities, and introduce more preferential policies to make life more convenient for community residents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善传统服务保障措施，为老年人等群体提供更周全更贴心的服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve traditional services, and provide elderly people and other groups with more comprehensive and considerate services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进智能化服务要适应老年人、残疾人需求，并做到不让智能工具给他们日常生活造成障碍。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The rollout of smart services should also cater to elderly people and people with disabilities, so that smart devices do not become a barrier in their daily lives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全帮扶残疾人、孤儿等社会福利制度，加强残疾预防，提升残疾康复服务质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will refine the social welfare systems for orphans and people with disabilities, strengthen disability prevention, and provide quality rehabilitation services for people with disabilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>分层分类做好社会救助，及时帮扶受疫情灾情影响的困难群众，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide social assistance of different types at different levels and ensure timely help and support for people in difficulty due to Covid-19 or natural disasters. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决兜住民生底线。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We are fully determined to ensure that the basic living needs of all our people are met.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更好满足人民群众精神文化需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will better meet the intellectual and cultural needs of our people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>培育和践行社会主义核心价值观，弘扬伟大抗疫精神和脱贫攻坚精神，推进公民道德建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will cultivate and promote the core socialist values, carry forward the great spirit forged in the battle against Covid-19 and in the fight against poverty, and foster civic virtue. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>繁荣新闻出版、广播影视、文学艺术、哲学社会科学和档案等事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's press and publishing, radio, film, and television, literature and art, philosophy, social sciences, and archives will continue to flourish. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强互联网内容建设和管理，发展积极健康的网络文化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More efforts will be made to ensure the quality of online content through improved management, and to cultivate a positive and healthy online culture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>传承弘扬中华优秀传统文化，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fine traditional Chinese culture will be preserved and carried forward. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强文物保护利用和非物质文化遗产传承，建设国家文化公园。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's cultural and historical artifacts will be placed under effective protection and put to good use, and our intangible cultural heritage will be kept alive. We will build national cultural parks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进城乡公共文化服务体系一体建设，创新实施文化惠民工程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote integrated development of urban and rural public cultural services and launch new public cultural projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>倡导全民阅读。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A love of reading will be fostered among our people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化中外人文交流。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's cultural and people-to-people exchanges with other countries will be deepened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善全民健身公共服务体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The public service system for fitness and physical activity will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>精心筹办北京冬奥会、冬残奥会等综合性体育赛事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make meticulous preparations for the 2022 Winter Olympics and Paralympics in Beijing and other major sports events.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强和创新社会治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen social governance and develop new ways to conduct it. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>夯实基层社会治理基础，健全城乡社区治理和服务体系，推进市域社会治理现代化试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will consolidate the foundations of primary-level governance, improve the governance and service systems for urban and rural communities, and advance trials on modernizing municipal social governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强社会信用体系建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The social credit system will be improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展社会工作，支持社会组织、人道救助、志愿服务、公益慈善发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance social services, support the development of social organizations, humanitarian assistance, volunteer service, public-interest activities, and charity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障妇女、儿童、老年人、残疾人合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will protect the lawful rights and interests of women, children, the elderly, and people with disabilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续完善信访制度，推进矛盾纠纷多元化解。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The system for handling public complaints will be further refined and more efforts will be made to resolve social disputes through multiple channels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强法律援助工作，启动实施“八五”普法规划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The provision of legal aid will be strengthened and the eighth five-year plan for increasing public knowledge of the law will be launched. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强应急救援力量建设，提高防灾减灾抗灾救灾能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen our emergency rescue capacity and disaster prevention, mitigation, response, and relief capabilities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实做好洪涝干旱、森林草原火灾、地质灾害、地震等防御和气象服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make solid efforts to protect against floods, droughts, forest and grassland fires, geological disasters, and earthquakes, and provide quality meteorological services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善和落实安全生产责任制，深入开展安全生产专项整治三年行动，坚决遏制重特大事故发生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and implement the system of accountability for workplace safety, carry out a three-year campaign to promote workplace safety, and take firm measures to prevent serious and major accidents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善社会治安防控体系，常态化开展扫黑除恶斗争，防范打击各类犯罪，维护社会稳定和安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the crime prevention and control system, make efforts to combat organized crime and root out local criminal gangs on an ongoing basis, and prevent and punish crimes of all types to effectively safeguard social stability and public safety.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对新的任务和挑战，各级政府要增强“四个意识”、</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the face of new tasks and challenges, our governments at all levels must be keenly aware of the need to maintain political integrity, think in big-picture terms, follow the leadership core, and keep in alignment with the central Party leadership. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚定“四个自信”、</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should stay confident in the path, theory, system, and culture of socialism with Chinese characteristics;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做到“两个维护”，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we should uphold General Secretary Xi Jinping's core position on the Party Central Committee and in the Party as a whole, and uphold the Party Central Committee's authority and its centralized, unified leadership. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>自觉在思想上政治上行动上同以习近平同志为核心的党中央保持高度一致，践行以人民为中心的发展思想，不断提高政治判断力、政治领悟力、政治执行力，落实全面从严治党要求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will closely follow the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core in thinking, stance, and action, practice the people-centered development philosophy, keep enhancing our capacity for political judgment, thinking, and implementation, and enforce full and strict Party self-governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实开展党史学习教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out activities to study the history of the CPC. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强法治政府建设，切实依法行政。坚持政务公开。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost development of a government based on the rule of law, conduct administration in accordance with the law, and ensure transparency in all government affairs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格规范公正文明执法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure that law enforcement is strict, procedure-based, impartial, and civil. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法接受同级人大及其常委会的监督，自觉接受人民政协的民主监督，主动接受社会和舆论监督。强化审计监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, in compliance with the law, subject ourselves to the oversight of people's congresses and their standing committees at the corresponding level, and readily submit to the democratic oversight of the CPPCC, public oversight, and oversight through public opinion, while strengthening auditing-based oversight. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持工会、共青团、妇联等群团组织更好发挥作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support trade unions, Communist Youth League organizations, women's federations, and other people's organizations in better playing their roles. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进党风廉政建设和反腐败斗争，锲而不舍落实中央八项规定精神。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work harder to improve Party conduct, ensure clean government, and root out corruption, and continue to implement the central Party leadership's eight-point decision on conduct. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作人员要自觉接受法律监督、监察监督和人民监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We in government must readily subject ourselves to the oversight of the law, supervisory bodies, and the people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强廉洁政府建设，持续整治不正之风和腐败问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to build a clean government and continue to prevent misconduct and corruption.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国经济社会发展已经取得了辉煌的成就，但全面实现现代化还有相当长的路要走，仍要付出艰苦努力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Although remarkable achievements have been made in China's economic and social development, we still have quite a way to go and a lot of hard work to do before we can achieve modernization in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须立足社会主义初级阶段基本国情，着力办好自己的事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must bear in mind the reality that China is still in the primary stage of socialism and run our affairs well. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要始终把人民放在心中最高位置，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For all of us in government, the people must always be uppermost in our minds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持实事求是，求真务实谋发展、惠民生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must take a fact-based approach, and pursue development and improve people's lives in a realistic and pragmatic way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要力戒形式主义、官僚主义，切忌在工作中搞“一刀切”，切实为基层松绑减负。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must guard against pointless formalities and bureaucratism and one-size-fits-all approaches in our work, so as to truly lighten the burden on all those working on the ground. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要居安思危，增强忧患意识，事不畏难、责不避险，有效防范化解各种风险隐患。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to remain vigilant, be prepared for adversity, face difficulties squarely, and shoulder responsibility bravely to effectively prevent and defuse various risks and potential dangers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要调动一切可以调动的积极因素，推进改革开放，更大激发市场主体活力和社会创造力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should keep everyone motivated in advancing reform and opening up, and further energize market entities and unlock social creativity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>用发展的办法解决发展不平衡不充分问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the course of pursuing development, we will take steps to address imbalances and inadequacies in development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要担当作为，实干苦干，不断创造人民期待的发展业绩。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must take on responsibility, work hard, and continue creating achievements to meet the expectation of our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要坚持和完善民族区域自治制度，全面贯彻党的民族政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to apply and improve the system of regional ethnic autonomy, and fully implement the Party's policies on ethnic affairs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>铸牢中华民族共同体意识，促进各民族共同团结奋斗、共同繁荣发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will forge a strong sense of community among the Chinese people and encourage all China's ethnic groups to work in concert for common prosperity and development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面贯彻党的宗教工作基本方针，坚持我国宗教的中国化方向，积极引导宗教与社会主义社会相适应。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the Party's basic policy on religious affairs, uphold the principle that religions in China must be Chinese in orientation, and work to guide religions in adapting to socialist society. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面贯彻党的侨务政策，维护海外侨胞和归侨侨眷合法权益，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully carry out the Party's policies on overseas Chinese affairs, safeguard the lawful rights and interests of Chinese nationals residing abroad, returned overseas Chinese, and relatives of overseas Chinese nationals residing in China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更大凝聚中华儿女共创辉煌的磅礴力量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By doing so, we will pool the tremendous strengths of all the sons and daughters of the Chinese nation to accomplish remarkable achievements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，国防和军队建设取得新的重大成就，人民军队在维护国家安全和疫情防控中展示出过硬本领和优良作风。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year, major success was attained in the development of national defense and the armed forces. Our people's forces, with complete competence and fine conduct, safeguarded China's national security and participated in epidemic control. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，要深入贯彻习近平强军思想，贯彻新时代军事战略方针，坚持党对人民军队的绝对领导，严格落实军委主席负责制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will thoroughly implement Xi Jinping's thinking on strengthening the armed forces and the military strategy for the new era, ensure the Party's absolute leadership over the people's armed forces, and strictly implement the system of ultimate responsibility resting with the chairman of the Central Military Commission.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>聚焦建军一百年奋斗目标，推进政治建军、改革强军、科技强军、人才强军、依法治军，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, bearing in mind the goals set for the centenary of the People's Liberation Army, continue to enhance the political loyalty of the armed forces, strengthen them through reform, science and technology and the training of capable personnel, and run them in accordance with the law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快机械化信息化智能化融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The integration of mechanized, informatized, and intelligent development of the military will be accelerated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面加强练兵备战，统筹应对各方向各领域安全风险，提高捍卫国家主权、安全、发展利益的战略能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost military training and preparedness across the board, make overall plans for responding to security risks in all areas and for all situations, and enhance the military's strategic capacity to protect the sovereignty, security, and development interests of our country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化国防科技工业布局，完善国防动员体系，强化全民国防教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the layout of defense-related science, technology, and industry, enhance the defense mobilization system, and strengthen public awareness about national defense. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要大力支持国防和军队建设，深入开展“双拥”活动，谱写鱼水情深的时代华章。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We in government at all levels should vigorously support the development of national defense and the armed forces, and conduct extensive activities to promote mutual support between the civilians and the military, so as to forge an ever closer bond between the people and the military in the new era.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要继续全面准确贯彻“一国两制”、“港人治港”、“澳人治澳”、高度自治的方针，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will stay true to the letter and spirit of the principle of One Country, Two Systems, under which the people of Hong Kong administer Hong Kong and the people of Macao administer Macao, both with a high degree of autonomy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善特别行政区同宪法和基本法实施相关的制度和机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the relevant systems and mechanisms of the two special administrative regions for enforcing the Constitution and the basic laws;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实特别行政区维护国家安全的法律制度和执行机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>we will ensure the implementation of the laws and enforcement mechanisms for the two regions to safeguard national security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决防范和遏制外部势力干预港澳事务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will resolutely guard against and deter external forces' interference in the affairs of Hong Kong and Macao.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持港澳发展经济、改善民生，保持香港、澳门长期繁荣稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support both regions as they grow their economies and improve people's lives, so as to maintain the long-term prosperity and stability of Hong Kong and Macao.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要坚持对台工作大政方针，坚持一个中国原则和“九二共识”，推进两岸关系和平发展和祖国统一。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We remain committed to the major principles and policies on work related to Taiwan, to the one-China principle and the 1992 Consensus, and to promoting the peaceful growth of relations across the Taiwan Strait and China's reunification. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高度警惕和坚决遏制“台独”分裂活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will remain highly vigilant against and resolutely deter any separatist activity seeking “Taiwan Independence.” </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善保障台湾同胞福祉和在大陆享受同等待遇的制度和政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the systems and policies for safeguarding the wellbeing of our Taiwan compatriots and ensuring they enjoy the same treatment on China's mainland as local residents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进海峡两岸交流合作、融合发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote exchanges, cooperation, and integrated development across the Taiwan Strait. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同心共创民族复兴美好未来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Together, we can shape a bright future of rejuvenation for our great nation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要坚持独立自主的和平外交政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China will continue to pursue an independent foreign policy of peace. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极发展全球伙伴关系，推动构建新型国际关系和人类命运共同体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively work to develop global partnerships and promote the building of a new type of international relations and a human community with a shared future. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持开放合作，推动全球治理体系朝着更加公正合理的方向发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to pursue the policy of opening up and cooperation and work to make the system of global governance fairer and more equitable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续深化国际和地区合作，积极参与重大传染病防控国际合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to deepen international and regional cooperation, and actively participate in international cooperation to prevent and control major infectious diseases. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国愿同所有国家在相互尊重、平等互利基础上和平共处、共同发展，携手应对全球性挑战，为促进世界和平与繁荣不懈努力！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China remains committed to pursuing peaceful coexistence and common development with all other countries in accordance with the principle of mutual respect, equality, and mutual benefit. China will join hands with them to meet global challenges and work tirelessly to promote world peace and prosperity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fellow Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重任在肩，更须砥砺奋进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As we shoulder heavy responsibilities, we must forge ahead with even greater resolve. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>让我们更加紧密地团结在以习近平同志为核心的党中央周围，高举中国特色社会主义伟大旗帜，以习近平新时代中国特色社会主义思想为指导，齐心协力，开拓进取，努力完成全年目标任务，以优异成绩庆祝中国共产党百年华诞，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let us rally more closely around the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, hold high the great banner of socialism with Chinese characteristics, follow the guidance of Xi Jinping Thought on Socialism with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era, and push forward in a concerted effort to complete the objectives and tasks for this year and celebrate the centenary of the Communist Party of China with outstanding achievements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为把我国建设成为富强民主文明和谐美丽的社会主义现代化强国、实现中华民族伟大复兴的中国梦不懈奋斗！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let each and every of us keep making tireless efforts to build China into a great modern socialist country that is prosperous, strong, democratic, culturally advanced, harmonious and beautiful, and fulfill the Chinese Dream of national rejuvenation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>