<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<tmx version="1.4">
<header creationtool="ABBYY Aligner" creationtoolversion="1.0" segtype="sentence" o-tmf="ATM" adminlang="en-US" srclang="en-US" datatype="plaintext">
</header>
<body>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作报告</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Report on the Work of the Government</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——2016年3月5日在第十二届全国人民代表大会第四次会议上</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Delivered at the Fourth Session of the 12th National People's Congress of the People's Republic of China on March 5, 2016</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院总理 李克强</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Li Keqiang Premier of the State Council</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现在，我代表国务院，向大会报告政府工作，请予审议，并请全国政协各位委员提出意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I will now report to you on the work of the government for your deliberation and approval. I invite comments on my report from the members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC).</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一、2015年工作回顾</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let me start with a review of the work we did in 2015.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，我国发展面临多重困难和严峻挑战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the past year, China has encountered many difficulties and challenges in its development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在以习近平同志为总书记的党中央坚强领导下，全国各族人民以坚定的信心和非凡的勇气，攻坚克难，开拓进取，经济社会发展稳中有进、稳中有好，完成了全年主要目标任务，改革开放和社会主义现代化建设取得新的重大成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>However, under the leadership of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CPC) headed by General Secretary Xi Jinping, and with confidence and courage, all the people of China have worked to overcome obstacles and have pressed ahead with a pioneering spirit. As a result, progress has been achieved and stability ensured in economic and social development, the main tasks and targets for the year have been fulfilled, and major achievements have been made in reform, opening up, and socialist modernization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——经济运行保持在合理区间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- The economy operated within an appropriate range. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值达到67.7万亿元，增长6.9%，在世界主要经济体中位居前列。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>GDP reached 67.7 trillion yuan, representing an increase of 6.9% over the previous year-a growth rate faster than that of most other major economies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食产量实现“十二连增”，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Food crop production increased for the 12th year in a row. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民消费价格涨幅保持较低水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumer prices grew slowly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>特别是就业形势总体稳定，城镇新增就业1312万人，超过全年预期目标，成为经济运行的一大亮点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Of particular note, the employment situation overall remained stable, with 13.12 million new urban jobs created over the course of the year, surpassing the year's target and becoming an economic highlight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——结构调整取得积极进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Encouraging progress was made in structural adjustment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>服务业在国内生产总值中的比重上升到50.5%，首次占据“半壁江山”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The service sector as a proportion of GDP rose to 50.5%, accounting for more than half for the first time. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>消费对经济增长的贡献率达到66.4%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The contribution of consumption toward economic growth reached 66.4%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高技术产业和装备制造业增速快于一般工业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>High-tech industries and equipment manufacturing grew faster than other industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗下降5.6%。 </seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Energy consumption per unit of GDP fell by 5.6%.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——发展新动能加快成长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- New driving forces for development grew rapidly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新驱动发展战略持续推进，互联网与各行业加速融合，新兴产业快速增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Further progress was made in implementing the strategy of innovation-driven development,the penetration of the Internet into all industries picked up pace, and emerging industries grew rapidly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大众创业、万众创新蓬勃发展，全年新登记注册企业增长21.6%，平均每天新增1.2万户。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Business startups and innovations by the general public flourished, with the number of newly registered businesses rising by 21.6% in 2015, or an average of 12,000 new businesses per day. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新动能对稳就业、促升级发挥了突出作用，正在推动经济社会发生深刻变革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New driving forces played a major role in keeping employment stable and pushing ahead industry upgrading, and are now driving profound economic and social change in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——人民生活进一步改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Living standards improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全国居民人均可支配收入实际增长7.4%，快于经济增速。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Personal per capita disposable income increased by 7.4% in real terms, overtaking the growth rate of the economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年末居民储蓄存款余额增长8.5%，新增4万多亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By the end of last year, personal savings deposits had risen by 8.5%, an increase of more than four trillion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>又解决6434万农村人口饮水安全问题。扶贫攻坚力度加大，农村贫困人口减少1442万人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In rural areas, another 64.34 million people gained access to safe drinking water and greater alleviation efforts reduced the number of people living in poverty by 14.42 million.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>科技领域一批创新成果达到国际先进水平，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A number of world-class innovations were made in science and technology.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>第三代核电技术取得重大进展，国产C919大型客机总装下线，屠呦呦获得诺贝尔生理学或医学奖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Major headway was made in the development of 3G nuclear power technology, China's self-developed C919 large jetliner rolled off the assembly line, and Tu Youyou was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对我国发展取得的成就，全国各族人民倍感振奋和自豪！回顾过去一年，成绩来之不易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These achievements in China's development, a source of pride and motivation for our people, did not come easily.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这些成绩，是在极为复杂严峻的国际环境中取得的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>They were made in the context of an extremely complicated and challenging international environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年世界经济增速为6年来最低，国际贸易增速更低，大宗商品价格深度下跌，国际金融市场震荡加剧，对我国经济造成直接冲击和影响。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In 2015, world economic growth fell to its lowest rate in six years, growth in international trade slowed, commodity prices plummeted, and there was growing volatility in the global financial market. All this had a direct impact on China's economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这些成绩，是在国内深层次矛盾凸显、经济下行压力加大的情况下取得的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>They were made at the same time as deep-seated domestic problems were becoming prominent and downward pressure on the economy was mounting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对“三期叠加”的局面，经济工作遇到不少两难甚至多难问题，需要远近结合，趋利避害，有效应对。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While dealing with the slowdown in economic growth, making difficult structural adjustments, and absorbing the effects of previous economic stimulus policies, China was also confronted with many difficult problems and choices in the running of the economy, and this called for effective responses based on the need both to combine long-term and short-term considerations and to seek benefit and avoid harm. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这些成绩，是在我国经济总量超过60万亿元的高基数上取得的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Finally, they were made at a time when China's economic output had exceeded 60 trillion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现在国内生产总值每增长1个百分点的增量，相当于5年前1.5个百分点、10年前2.5个百分点的增量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Every percentage point of GDP growth today is equivalent to 1.5 percentage points of growth five years ago or 2.5 percentage points of growth ten years ago. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济规模越大，增长难度随之增加。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The larger the economy grows, the greater the difficulty of achieving growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在困难和压力面前，全国各族人民付出了极大辛劳，一步一步走了过来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the face of these difficulties and pressures, all our people have truly exerted themselves and progressed step by step to get us where we are today. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这再次表明，任何艰难险阻都挡不住中国发展前行的步伐！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This once again demonstrates that no difficulty or hardship will ever stop China from moving forward.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们主要做了以下工作：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I will now move on to discuss the main work we did last year:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是着力稳增长调结构防风险，创新宏观调控方式。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we maintained stable growth, made structural adjustments, guarded against risks, and developed new ways of conducting macro regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为应对持续加大的经济下行压力，我们在区间调控基础上，实施定向调控和相机调控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In responding to the mounting downward pressure on the economy, we exercised targeted and well-timed regulation on the basis of range-based regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极的财政政策注重加力增效，扩大结构性减税范围，实行普遍性降费，盘活财政存量资金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We adopted proactive fiscal policy that focused on increasing intensity and efficacy by expanding the scope of structural tax reductions, reducing fees across the board, and putting dormant budgetary funds to good use. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发行地方政府债券置换存量债务3.2万亿元，降低利息负担约2000亿元，减轻了地方政府偿债压力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local government bonds issued to replace outstanding debt reached 3.2 trillion yuan, lessening the interest payment burden of local governments by approximately 200 billion yuan while also reducing their debt repayment pressure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳健的货币政策注重松紧适度，多次降息降准，改革存贷比管理，创新货币政策工具，加大对实体经济支持力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We pursued prudent monetary policy with an appropriate amount of intensity, making several cuts to interest rates and required reserve ratios, reforming management of the loan-to-deposit ratio, creating new monetary policy tools, and increasing support for the real economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大有效投资，设立专项基金，加强水利、城镇棚户区和农村危房改造、中西部铁路和公路等薄弱环节建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Effective investment increased, special-purpose funds were established, and development was strengthened in areas in need of attention, including water conservancy, rundown urban areas and dilapidated rural housing, and railways and highways in the central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施重点领域消费促进工程，城乡居民旅游、网购、信息消费等快速增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumer spending was promoted in key areas, spurring rapid growth in spending on recreational travel, online shopping, and information goods and services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年还积极应对股市、汇市异常波动等金融领域的多种风险挑战，守住了不发生系统性区域性风险的底线，维护了国家经济金融安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In 2015, we also responded proactively to a variety of risks and challenges in the financial sector, such as unusual fluctuations in the stock market and the foreign exchange market, ensuring that no systemic or regional threats arose, thus safeguarding China's economic and financial security.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是围绕激发市场活力，加大改革开放力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we intensified reform and opening up to invigorate the market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们不搞“大水漫灌”式的强刺激，而是持续推动结构性改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Rather than adopting strong stimulus policies that would have an economy-wide impact, we continued to move forward with structural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进简政放权、放管结合、优化服务改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We intensified reform to streamline administration, delegate more powers, improve regulation, and provide better services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>取消和下放311项行政审批事项，取消123项职业资格许可和认定事项，彻底终结了非行政许可审批。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We delegated the power or cancelled the requirement for government review for 311 items, cancelled the requirement for verification or approval for 123 professional qualifications, and put a complete stop to the practice of non-administrative review. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>工商登记前置审批精简85%，全面实施三证合一、一照一码。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of items which require government approval for new businesses prior to registration was cut by 85%, and the system of a separate business license, organization code certificate, and taxation registration certificate was replaced by a unified business license with a unified social credit code. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强事中事后监管，优化公共服务流程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Both operational and post-operational oversight over businesses were strengthened, and public service procedures were improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>群众和企业办事更加方便，全社会创业创新热情日益高涨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government-related procedures for individuals and businesses were made much simpler, such that enthusiasm for stepping out into business and making innovations is rising by the day.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财税金融等重点改革深入推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal, tax, financial, and other key reforms were deepened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央对地方专项转移支付项目减少三分之一，一般性转移支付规模增加。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government cut, by one third, the number of items for which special transfer payments are permitted, while scaling up its general transfer payments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>营改增稳步实施，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Steady progress was made in replacing business tax with VAT. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>资源税从价计征范围扩大。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Ad valorem taxation was extended to cover more types of resource taxes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>取消存款利率浮动上限，推出存款保险制度，建立人民币跨境支付系统。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The upper limit of the floating band on deposit rates was removed, the deposit insurance system was introduced, and the RMB cross-border payment system was established. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>价格改革力度加大，中央政府定价项目减少80%，地方政府定价项目减少一半以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pricing reform was intensified, with the number of central government set prices reduced by 80% and the number of local government set prices cut by more than 50%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国有企业、农村、投融资、生态文明等领域改革有序推进，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We carried out state-owned enterprise (SOE) reforms, rural reforms, and investment and financing reforms, ecological management reforms, and others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面深化改革的成效正在显现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts to intensify reform in all respects are beginning to deliver results.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以开放促改革促发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Momentum was created for reform and development through opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力稳定对外贸易，调整出口退税负担机制，清理规范进出口环节收费，提高贸易便利化水平，出口结构发生积极变化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We worked hard to keep foreign trade stable by adjusting the mechanism for sharing the cost of export tax rebates between the central and local governments, overhauling and regulating charges for imports and exports, increasing trade facilitation, and making changes to the export mix. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>外商投资限制性条目减少一半，95%以上实行备案管理，实际使用外资1263亿美元，增长5.6%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of restrictions on overseas investment in China was cut by 50%, and over 95% of overseas-funded projects may now be undertaken on a simple reporting basis. China utilized US$126.3 billion of overseas investment, an increase of 5.6%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>非金融类对外直接投资1180亿美元，增长14.7%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Non-financial outward foreign direct investment reached $118 billion, up 14.7%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推广上海自贸试验区经验，新设广东、天津、福建自贸试验区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pilot free trade zones were established in Guangdong, Tianjin, and Fujian based on the model of the China (Shanghai) Pilot Free Trade Zone. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民币加入国际货币基金组织特别提款权货币篮子。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The RMB was included in the IMF's Special Drawing Rights basket. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>亚洲基础设施投资银行正式成立，丝路基金投入运营。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank was officially inaugurated, and the Silk Road Fund opened for business. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>签署中韩、中澳自贸协定和中国－东盟自贸区升级议定书。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China signed free trade agreements with the Republic of Korea and Australia, respectively,and signed the Protocol to Amend the Framework Agreement on Comprehensive Economic Cooperation between China and ASEAN. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“一带一路”建设成效显现，国际产能合作步伐加快，高铁、核电等中国装备走出去取得突破性进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Progress was made in the Silk Road Economic Belt and 21st Century Maritime Silk Road Initiative (the Belt and Road Initiative), the pace of our industrial-capacity cooperation with other countries was stepped up, and breakthroughs were made in China's export of high-speed railway and nuclear power equipment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是聚焦提质增效，推动产业创新升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we worked to promote industrial innovation and upgrading to improve economic performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施创新驱动发展战略纲要和意见，出台推动大众创业、万众创新政策举措，落实“互联网+”行动计划，增强经济发展新动力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To strengthen the new growth engines, an innovation-driven development plan was adopted along with guidelines on its implementation, policies and measures were introduced to encourage public participation in starting businesses and making innovations, and the Internet Plus action plan was implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一大批创客走上创业创新之路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A great number of makers started businesses and made innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善农业支持政策，促进农业发展方式加快转变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Improvements were made to policies in support of agriculture to promote transformation of the agricultural growth model. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>针对工业增速下降、企业效益下滑，我们一手抓新兴产业培育，一手抓传统产业改造提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addressing the decline in industrial growth and the downward slide incorporate performance, we worked to foster new industries and upgrade traditional ones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动实施《中国制造2025》，设立国家新兴产业创业投资引导基金、中小企业发展基金，扩大国家自主创新示范区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We launched the Made in China 2025 initiative to upgrade manufacturing, set up government funds to encourage investment in emerging industries and to develop small and medium-sized enterprises, and established more national innovation demonstration zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极化解过剩产能，推进企业兼并重组。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We cut overcapacity and encouraged business acquisitions and restructuring. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>近三年淘汰落后炼钢炼铁产能9000多万吨、水泥2.3亿吨、平板玻璃7600多万重量箱、电解铝100多万吨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Cuts made in outdated production capacity over the past three years have included over 90 million metric tons of steel and iron, 230 million metric tons of cement, over 76 million weight cases of plate glass, and more than one million metric tons of electrolytic aluminum. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进生产性、生活性服务业加快发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The development of production- and consumer-oriented service industries picked up momentum. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>狠抓节能减排和环境保护，各项约束性指标超额完成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took serious measures to conserve energy, reduce emissions, and protect the environment, exceeding obligatory targets. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>公布自主减排行动目标，推动国际气候变化谈判取得积极成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We released self-imposed emissions reduction targets and contributed to the positive outcomes of international negotiations on climate change.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是着眼开拓发展空间，促进区域协调发展和新型城镇化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we promoted coordinated development between regions and the new type of urbanization to expand development space. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推动东、中、西、东北地区“四大板块”协调发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Work continued to promote the coordinated development of the eastern region, the central region, the western region, and the northeast;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点推进“一带一路”建设、京津冀协同发展、长江经济带发展“三大战略”，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>priority was placed on moving forward with the Three Initiatives-the Belt and Road Initiative, the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei integration initiative, and the Yangtze Economic Belt initiative.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在基础设施、产业布局、生态环保等方面实施一批重大工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A number of major projects were also launched to develop infrastructure, improve the distribution of industries, and achieve ecological and environmental conservation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施促进西藏和四省藏区、新疆发展的政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Policies and measures were introduced to promote the development of Tibet, Xinjiang, and Tibetan ethnic areas in the provinces of Sichuan, Yunnan, Gansu, and Qinghai. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进户籍制度改革，出台居住证制度，加强城镇基础设施建设，新型城镇化取得新成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We pressed ahead with the reform of the household registration system, adopted a residence certification system, and stepped up the development of urban infrastructure, making progress in developing new urbanization.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是紧扣增进民生福祉，推动社会事业改革发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we promoted the reform and development of social programs to improve living standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在财力紧张情况下，保障民生力度继续加大。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Despite fiscal constraints, we continued to intensify efforts to help ensure the wellbeing of our people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推出新的政策，重点解决高校毕业生和就业困难群体的就业创业问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New policies were launched to create jobs and business startup opportunities for college graduates and those with difficulties finding employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇保障性安居工程住房基本建成772万套，棚户区住房改造开工601万套，农村危房改造432万户，一大批住房困难家庭圆了安居梦。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the course of the year, 7.72 million government-subsidized housing units were basically completed in urban areas, work started on the reconstruction of 6.01 million housing units in rundown urban areas, and 4.32 million dilapidated houses in rural areas were rebuilt, helping large numbers of families that are struggling with housing realize their dream of having a home to settle in.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快改善贫困地区义务教育薄弱学校办学条件，深化中小学教师职称制度改革，重点高校招收贫困地区农村学生人数又增长10.5%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We moved more quickly to improve conditions in badly built and poorly operated schools providing compulsory education in poor areas, deepened the reform of the professional title system for elementary and secondary school teachers, and increased the number of students from poor rural areas who were enrolled in key institutions of higher learning by a further 10.5%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推开县级公立医院综合改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Comprehensive reform was carried out in all public hospitals at the county level,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓展居民大病保险，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the coverage of the serious disease insurance scheme was extended to more rural and non-working urban residents,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立重特大疾病医疗救助制度、困难残疾人生活补贴和重度残疾人护理补贴制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a system of assistance for treating major and serious diseases was put in place, and a system for providing living allowances for people with disabilities who are in need and for granting nursing care subsidies to persons with severe disabilities was established. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高低保、优抚、企业退休人员基本养老金等标准，推行机关事业单位养老保险制度改革并完善工资制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased subsistence allowances, benefits for entitled groups, and basic pension benefits for enterprise retirees, implemented the reform of the pension system for employees of Party and government offices and public institutions, and improved their wage system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强基本公共文化服务建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts to develop basic public cultural services were also intensified. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广大人民群众有了更多获得感。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All of this has resulted in a stronger sense of benefit in society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>六是促进社会和谐稳定，推动依法行政和治理方式创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Sixth, we developed new ways of conducting law-based administration and governance to promote social harmony and stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院提请全国人大常委会审议法律议案11件，制定修订行政法规8部。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The State Council submitted 11 legislative proposals to the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress and enacted or revised eight sets of administrative regulations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政务公开加快推进，推广电子政务和网上办事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts were accelerated to increase government transparency and expand the application of e-government and online administration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立重大政策落实督查问责机制，开展第三方评估。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We set up a mechanism to inspect and establish accountability for the implementation of major government policies and introduced third-party evaluations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有效应对自然灾害和突发事件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We responded effectively to natural disasters and emergencies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强安全生产监管，事故总量和重特大事故、重点行业事故数量继续下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Efforts were stepped up to ensure workplace safety; as a result, we have seen a continued reduction in the number of total accidents, including the number of accidents of a serious or large-scale nature as well as those in industries where accidents tend to be more common. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进食品安全创建示范行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We moved ahead with the demonstration initiative to ensure food safety. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化社会治安综合治理，依法打击各类违法犯罪活动，有力维护了公共安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened all-round efforts to maintain law and order and cracked down on crimes in accordance with the law to safeguard public security.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们深入开展“三严三实”专题教育，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The campaign to build understanding of the Three Stricts and Three Honests* was intensified,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>锲而不舍落实党中央八项规定精神，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the CPC Central Committee's eight-point decision on improving Party and government conduct continued to be implemented,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决纠正“四风”，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>action was taken against formalism, bureaucratism, hedonism, and extravagance,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格执行国务院“约法三章”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and rigorous efforts were made to carry out the State Council's three-point decision on curbing government spending. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强行政监察和审计监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Administrative supervision and oversight through auditing were strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推进党风廉政建设和反腐败斗争，一批腐败分子受到惩处。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We stepped up efforts to improve Party conduct and government integrity and fight corruption, and brought a number of offenders to justice.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们隆重纪念中国人民抗日战争暨世界反法西斯战争胜利70周年，集中宣示了我国作为世界反法西斯战争东方主战场的历史地位和重大贡献，彰显了中国人民同各国人民共护和平、共守正义的坚定信念！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We marked the 70th anniversary of the victory in the Chinese People's War of Resistance against Japanese Aggression and the Global War against Fascism. This anniversary was a reminder of China's place in history as the main theater in the East during the Global War against Fascism and its major contribution to the war effort. The Chinese people marked this occasion to demonstrate their dedication to safeguarding peace and upholding justice together with other peoples.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，全方位外交成果丰硕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the past year, China's all-round diplomacy has delivered fruitful outcomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>习近平主席等国家领导人出访多国，出席联合国系列峰会、二十国集团领导人峰会、亚太经合组织领导人非正式会议、气候变化大会、东亚合作领导人系列会议、世界经济论坛等重大活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>President Xi Jinping and other Chinese leaders have visited many countries and attended international events including the United Nations summits, the G20 Leaders Summit, the 23rd APEC Economic Leaders Meeting, the 21st Session of the Conference of the Parties to the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change, the East Asian leaders' meetings on cooperation, and the World Economic Forum annual meeting 2016. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>成功举行中非合作论坛峰会、中欧领导人会晤，启动中拉论坛。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Summit of the Forum on China-Africa Cooperation and the China-EU Leaders' Meeting were held, and the China and the Community of Latin American and Caribbean States (CELAC) Forum was inaugurated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同主要大国关系取得新进展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fresh progress was made in China's relations with other major countries;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同周边国家务实合作深入推进，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>pragmatic cooperation with neighboring countries was strengthened;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同发展中国家友好合作不断拓展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>friendship and cooperation with other developing countries grew;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同联合国等国际组织和国际机制的关系全面加强，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>relations with the United Nations and other international organizations and mechanisms were strengthened in all areas;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济外交、人文交流卓有成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and notable achievements were made in economic diplomacy and cultural exchanges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国作为负责任大国，在国际和地区事务中发挥了重要的建设性作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As a responsible major country, China played an important constructive role in international and regional affairs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年取得的成绩，是以习近平同志为总书记的党中央统揽全局、科学决策的结果，是全党全军全国各族人民齐心协力、顽强拼搏的结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We owe these achievements to the sound overall decisions made by the CPC Central Committee headed by General Secretary Xi Jinping, and to the concerted and determined efforts of all members of the Party, all members of the armed forces, and all the people of China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我代表国务院，向全国各族人民，向各民主党派、各人民团体和各界人士，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I wish to express our sincere gratitude to the people of all ethnic groups in China including public figures from all sectors of society and to the other parties and the people's organizations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向香港特别行政区同胞、澳门特别行政区同胞、台湾同胞和海外侨胞，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I express our heartfelt appreciation to our fellow countrymen and women in the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions and in Taiwan, and to Chinese nationals overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向关心和支持中国现代化建设事业的各国政府、国际组织和各国朋友，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I also wish to express our sincere thanks to the governments, international organizations, and friends from all over the world who have shown understanding and support for China in her endeavor to modernize.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在充分肯定去年成绩的同时，我们也清醒看到，我国发展中还存在不少困难和问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While recognizing our achievements, we are also keenly aware that our country is still confronted with many difficulties and problems in pursuing development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>受全球贸易萎缩等因素影响，去年我国进出口总额出现下降，预期增长目标未能实现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the decline in global trade, amongst other factors, China experienced a fall in its total imports and exports and failed to reach its growth objective in this regard. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>投资增长乏力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Growth in investment is sluggish,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些行业产能过剩严重，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>overcapacity is a serious problem in certain industries,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>部分企业生产经营困难，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>some enterprises are facing difficulties in production and operations,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>地区和行业走势分化，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>growth prospects are mixed for different regions and different industries,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政收支矛盾突出，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>notable imbalances exist between government revenue and expenditures,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>资本市场基础性制度还不完善，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the basic institutions for the capital market still need to be improved,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>金融等领域存在风险隐患。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and there are latent risks in the financial and other sectors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民群众关心的医疗、教育、养老、食品药品安全、收入分配、城市管理等方面问题较多，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There are many problems in medical care, education, elderly care, food and medicine safety, income distribution, and urban management that are of concern to the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>环境污染形势仍很严峻，严重雾霾天气在一些地区时有发生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The situation remains grave when it comes to environmental pollution, and some regions are frequently hit by severe smog. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>特别令人痛心的是，去年发生了“东方之星”号客轮翻沉事件和天津港特别重大火灾爆炸等事故，人员伤亡和财产损失惨重，教训极其深刻，必须认真汲取。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Particularly distressing, last year saw the sinking of the cruise ship Oriental Star on the Yangtze and the massive explosion in Tianjin Port. The deaths and injuries and the damage and loss of property from these incidents were devastating, and the profound lessons these incidents have taught us should never be forgotten. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作还存在不足，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There are still inadequacies in the work of the government.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有些改革和政策措施落实不到位，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some reforms, policies, and measures have not been fully implemented;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>少数干部不作为、不会为、乱作为，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>a small number of government employees either do not or are unable to fulfill their duties, or behave irresponsibly;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些领域的不正之风和腐败问题不容忽视。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and the corruption and misconduct in some sectors cannot be ignored. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要进一步增强忧患意识和担当意识，下更大力气解决这些问题，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must be more mindful of the difficulties ahead, more ready to assume responsibility, and more hardworking in ensuring these problems are solved.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>始终以民之所望为施政所向，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The wishes of the people should always determine the aim of our governance;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>尽心竭力做好政府工作，决不辜负人民重托。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>we must do our utmost to deliver a strong performance in our work and never fail to live up to the great trust the people have placed in us.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>2015年是“十二五”收官之年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The period covered by the 12th Five-Year Plan came to a close in 2015. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去五年，我国发展成就举世瞩目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>During the past five years, impressive achievements were made in China's development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>党的十八大以来，在以习近平同志为总书记的党中央坚强领导下，面对错综复杂的国际环境和艰巨繁重的国内改革发展稳定任务，我们继续坚持稳中求进工作总基调，深化改革开放，实施一系列利当前、惠长远的重大举措，“十二五”规划确定的主要目标任务全面完成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Since the 18th CPC National Congress in 2012, we have found ourselves in a complicated international environment, and we have faced the challenging tasks of carrying out reform and development and maintaining stability at home. However, under the guidance of the CPC Central Committee headed by General Secretary Xi Jinping, we have continued our commitment to the general principle of making progress while working to keep performance stable, deepened reform and opening up, and adopted a series of major measures that should deliver both immediate and long-term benefits. As a result, we successfully fulfilled all the main tasks and targets set out in the 12th Five-Year Plan.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是经济持续较快发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, a high rate of economic development was maintained. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值年均增长7.8%，经济总量稳居世界第二位，成为全球第一货物贸易大国和主要对外投资大国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>During this period, China's GDP grew at an average annual rate of 7.8%. This growth enabled China to comfortably maintain its position as the world's second-largest economy, and become the largest trading nation in terms of goods as well as a major outbound investor.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是结构调整取得标志性进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, milestone progress was achieved in structural adjustments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>服务业成为第一大产业，工业化与信息化融合加深，农业综合生产能力明显增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Service industries have grown to be the largest economic sector, information technology has been further integrated into industrialization, and overall agricultural production capacity has notably improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>消费成为支撑经济增长的主要力量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumption has become a major driver of growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>超过一半人口居住在城镇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over half of China's population now resides in urban areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗下降18.2%，主要污染物排放量减少12%以上。 </seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Energy consumption per unit of GDP has dropped by 18.2%, and the emissions of major pollutants have been cut by over 12%.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是基础设施水平全面跃升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, across-the-board improvements were made in infrastructure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>铁路营业里程达到12.1万公里，其中高速铁路超过1.9万公里，占世界60%以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The length of railways in service reached 121,000 kilometers, of which more than 19,000 kilometers are high-speed rail lines-more than 60% of the world's total. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高速公路通车里程超过12万公里。南水北调东、中线工程通水。建成全球最大的第四代移动通信网络。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The length of expressways open to traffic exceeded 120,000 kilometers, the eastern and middle routes of the South-to-North Water Diversion Project were put into operation, and the world's largest 4G mobile network was built in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是科技创新实现重大突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, significant breakthroughs were made in scientific and technological innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>量子通信、中微子振荡、高温铁基超导等基础研究取得一批原创性成果，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Original achievements were made in quantum communications, neutrino oscillation, and iron-based high-temperature superconductivity through basic research.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>载人航天、探月工程、深海探测等项目达到世界先进水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>World-class advances were made in manned spaceflight, the lunar exploration program, and deep-water exploration.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是人民生活水平显著提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, living standards improved significantly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民收入增长快于经济增长，城乡收入差距持续缩小。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Personal income increased faster than economic growth, and the urban-rural income gap was narrowed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业人数超过6400万人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over 64 million urban jobs were created. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇保障性安居工程住房建设4013万套，上亿群众喜迁新居。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government subsidies were used to build 40.13 million housing units in urban areas, providing new homes for around 100 million people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农村贫困人口减少1亿多，解决3亿多农村人口饮水安全问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of rural residents living in poverty was cut by more than 100 million, and over 300 million rural residents gained access to safe drinking water.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>六是社会发展成就斐然。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Sixth, notable achievements were made in social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育公平和质量明显提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Significant progress was made in ensuring equal access to education, and the quality of education markedly improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>基本医疗保险实现全覆盖，基本养老保险参保率超过80%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Basic health insurance was expanded to achieve complete coverage, and participation in basic pension plans exceeded 80% of the whole population. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>文化软实力持续提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's soft power continued to grow. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法治国全面推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The rule of law was advanced in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国特色军事变革成就显著。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Significant achievements were made in the military revolution with Chinese characteristics. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经过五年努力，我国经济实力、科技实力、国防实力、国际影响力又上了一个大台阶。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the past five years, China's economic strength, scientific and technological capabilities, defense capabilities, and international influence have all been strengthened considerably.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“十二五”时期的辉煌成就，充分显示了中国特色社会主义的巨大优越性，集中展现了中国人民的无穷创造力，极大增强了中华民族的自信心和凝聚力，必将激励全国各族人民在实现“两个一百年”奋斗目标的新征程上奋力前行！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The achievements attained during the period of the 12th Five-Year Plan fully demonstrate the strength of socialism with Chinese characteristics and the creativity of the Chinese people. The Chinese people can derive great confidence and a strengthened sense of unity from these achievements, drawing on them to forge ahead on this new leg of the journey toward realizing the Two Centenary Goals.*</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二、“十三五”时期主要目标任务和重大举措</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies, Let me now brief you on the main targets, tasks, and measures for the period of the 13th Five-Year Plan from 2016 through 2020.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>根据《中共中央关于制定国民经济和社会发展第十三个五年规划的建议》，国务院编制了《国民经济和社会发展第十三个五年规划纲要（草案）》，提交大会审查。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the basis of the CPC Central Committee Recommendations for the 13th Five-Year Plan for Economic and Social Development, the State Council has drawn up the draft of the 13th Five-Year Plan for Economic and Social Development and submitted it to this session for your review and approval.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>《纲要草案》紧紧围绕全面建成小康社会奋斗目标，针对发展不平衡、不协调、不可持续等突出问题，强调要牢固树立和贯彻落实创新、协调、绿色、开放、共享的发展理念，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The draft, centering on the goal of finishing building a moderately prosperous society in all respects and designed to address serious issues such as unbalanced, uncoordinated, and unsustainable development, stresses the need to promote innovative, coordinated, green, open, and shared development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>明确了今后五年经济社会发展的主要目标任务，提出了一系列支撑发展的重大政策、重大工程和重大项目，突出了以下六个方面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It proposes the main targets and tasks for economic and social development over the next five years as well as development policies, initiatives, and projects. The following are the six areas highlighted in the draft.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——保持经济中高速增长，推动产业迈向中高端水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We should work to maintain a medium-high rate of growth and promote the development of industries toward the medium-high end. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实现全面建成小康社会目标，到2020年国内生产总值和城乡居民人均收入比2010年翻一番，“十三五”时期经济年均增长保持在6.5%以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects and double the 2010 GDP and per capita personal income by 2020, the economy needs to grow at an average annual rate of at least 6.5% during this five-year period. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进产业结构优化升级，实施一批技术水平高、带动能力强的重大工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To that end, we will move faster to improve or upgrade the structure of industry and launch initiatives that use advanced technologies and can drive industrial development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>到2020年，先进制造业、现代服务业、战略性新兴产业比重大幅提升，全员劳动生产率从人均8.7万元提高到12万元以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our goal is that by 2020, advanced manufacturing, modern services, and strategic emerging industries as a proportion of GDP will have risen significantly and that per capita labor productivity will have risen from 87,000 yuan to over 120,000 yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>届时，我国经济总量超过90万亿元，发展的质量和效益明显提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By that time, China's aggregate economic output should have exceeded 90 trillion yuan, and the quality and efficacy of development should have significantly improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在我们这样一个人口众多的发展中国家，这将是非常了不起的成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For a developing country like China with such a large population, this will be a truly remarkable achievement.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——强化创新引领作用，为发展注入强大动力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We should ensure that innovation better drives and energizes development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新是引领发展的第一动力，必须摆在国家发展全局的核心位置，深入实施创新驱动发展战略。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Innovation is the primary driving force for development and must occupy a central place in China's development strategy, which is why we must implement a strategy of innovation-driven development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动一批新的国家重大科技项目，建设一批高水平的国家科学中心和技术创新中心，培育壮大一批有国际竞争力的创新型领军企业，建设一批全面创新改革试验区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should launch new national science and technology programs, build first-class national science centers and technological innovation hubs, help develop internationally competitive high-innovation enterprises, and establish pilot reform zones for all-round innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续推动大众创业、万众创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should make consistent efforts to encourage the public to start businesses and make innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进大数据、云计算、物联网广泛应用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should promote the extensive application of big data, cloud computing, and the Internet of Things. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建设质量强国、制造强国、知识产权强国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to move faster to transform China into a manufacturer of advanced and quality products and a country that is strong on intellectual property rights. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>到2020年，力争在基础研究、应用研究和战略前沿领域取得重大突破，全社会研发经费投入强度达到2.5%，科技进步对经济增长的贡献率达到60%，迈进创新型国家和人才强国行列。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should strive to achieve major breakthroughs in basic research, applied research, and research in strategic and frontier fields by 2020. China's investment in research and development is expected to reach 2.5% of GDP, and the contribution of scientific and technological advances toward economic growth should come to reach 60%. Fulfilling these objectives will turn China into an innovative and talent-rich country.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——推进新型城镇化和农业现代化，促进城乡区域协调发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We should make progress in new urbanization and agricultural modernization as well as in balancing development between urban and rural areas and between regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>缩小城乡区域差距，既是调整经济结构的重点，也是释放发展潜力的关键。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Narrowing the gap between urban and rural areas and between regions is not only a key part of economic structural adjustment; it is also crucial for unleashing developmental potential. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要深入推进以人为核心的新型城镇化，实现1亿左右农业转移人口和其他常住人口在城镇落户，完成约1亿人居住的棚户区和城中村改造，引导约1亿人在中西部地区就近城镇化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should advance the new, people-centered urbanization. This will mean granting urban residency to around 100 million people with rural household registration living in urban areas and other permanent urban residents, completing the rebuilding of both rundown areas and "villages" in cities involving about 100 million people, and enabling around 100 million rural residents to live in local towns and cities in the central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>到2020年，常住人口城镇化率达到60%、户籍人口城镇化率达到45%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By 2020, permanent urban residents should account for 60% of China's population, and 45% of the Chinese people should be registered as permanent urban residents. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施一批水利、农机、现代种业等工程，推动农业适度规模经营和区域化布局、标准化生产、社会化服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should launch initiatives to develop water conservancy in agriculture, farming machinery, and the modern seed industry, encourage appropriately scaled-up agricultural operations, and promote regional distribution, standardized production, and commercial agricultural services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>到2020年，粮食等主要农产品供给和质量安全得到更好保障，农业现代化水平明显提高，新农村建设取得新成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By 2020, the supply, quality, and safety of food crops and other major agricultural products should be better ensured, notable headway should have been made in modernizing agriculture, and fresh progress should have been made in developing the new countryside. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以区域发展总体战略为基础，以“三大战略”为引领，形成沿海沿江沿线经济带为主的纵向横向经济轴带，培育一批辐射带动力强的城市群和增长极。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Guided by the general strategy for regional development, we should pursue the Three Initiatives to form north-south and east-west intersecting economic belts along the coastline, the Yangtze River, and major transportation routes, and foster new growth poles and city clusters that facilitate the development of surrounding areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强重大基础设施建设，高铁营业里程达到3万公里、覆盖80%以上的大城市，新建改建高速公路通车里程约3万公里，实现城乡宽带网络全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should also expand major infrastructure projects, with the aim of increasing the length of high-speed railways in service to 30,000 kilometers and linking more than 80% of big cities in China with high-speed railways, building or upgrading around 30,000 kilometers of expressways, and achieving full coverage of access to broadband networks in both urban and rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——推动形成绿色生产生活方式，加快改善生态环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We should encourage green ways of working and living and speed up efforts to conserve ecosystems and the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持在发展中保护、在保护中发展，持续推进生态文明建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to protect the environment while pursuing development and achieve development in a well-protected environment, making sustained efforts to build a sound ecological system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施大气、水、土壤污染防治行动计划，划定生态空间保护红线，推进山水林田湖生态工程，加强生态保护和修复。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to take serious action to prevent and control air, water, and soil pollution, set a red line that the country's total area of ecological spaces should not fall below, move forward with eco-friendly projects to protect and restore mountains, waters, forests, and farmlands, and intensify ecological conservation and restoration efforts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今后五年，单位国内生产总值用水量、能耗、二氧化碳排放量分别下降23%、15%、18%，森林覆盖率达到23.04%，能源资源开发利用效率大幅提高，生态环境质量总体改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the next five years, we should aim to ensure that water consumption, energy consumption, and carbon dioxide emissions per unit of GDP are cut by 23%, 15%, and 18%, respectively, and that forest coverage reaches 23.04%. We should also make it our aim, within this timeframe, to develop and use energy and resources much more efficiently and make improvements to the quality of ecosystems and the environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>特别是治理大气雾霾取得明显进展，地级及以上城市空气质量优良天数比率超过80%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In particular, we should strive for major progress in the control and prevention of air pollution and see to it that the air quality of cities at and above the prefectural level is good or excellent for 80% of the year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要持之以恒，建设天蓝、地绿、水清的美丽中国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must work to build, through tireless efforts, a Beautiful China where the sky is blue, the land is green, and the water runs clear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——深化改革开放，构建发展新体制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We need to deepen reform and opening up to create new institutions for development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展根本上要靠改革开放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fundamentally, development relies on reform and opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须全面深化改革，坚持和完善基本经济制度，建立现代产权制度，基本建成法治政府，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must deepen reform across the board, uphold and improve the basic economic system, establish a modern system of property rights, and see that a rule of law government is basically in place.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>使市场在资源配置中起决定性作用和更好发挥政府作用，加快形成引领经济发展新常态的体制机制和发展方式。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It should be ensured that the market plays the decisive role in resource allocation and the government better plays its role, and work should be accelerated to create the systems, mechanisms, and growth model that will guide the new normal in economic development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“一带一路”建设取得重大进展，国际产能合作实现新的突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should work for significant progress in pursuing the Belt and Road Initiative and for breakthroughs in our cooperation with other countries on industrial capacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对外贸易向优进优出转变，服务贸易比重显著提升，从贸易大国迈向贸易强国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should promote the optimization of imports and exports, significantly increase the proportion of trade in services, and promote China's transformation from a trader of quantity to a trader of quality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实行准入前国民待遇加负面清单管理制度，逐步构建高标准自由贸易区网络，基本形成开放型经济新体制新格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should put into force across the board the management system for pre-establishment national treatment plus a negative list, and progressively build a network of high-standard free trade areas. With these efforts, we should be able to usher in a new phase in building an open economy based on new systems.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——持续增进民生福祉，使全体人民共享发展成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We need to ensure that continuous progress is made in raising living standards, and see that everyone shares in the fruits of development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以人民为中心的发展思想，努力补齐基本民生保障的短板，朝着共同富裕方向稳步前进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Guided by the vision of people-centered development, we need to continue to strengthen points of weakness in meeting basic needs for the people in order to achieve common prosperity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决打赢脱贫攻坚战，我国现行标准下的农村贫困人口实现脱贫，贫困县全部摘帽，解决区域性整体贫困。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to fight hard to win the war against poverty and help lift out of poverty all rural residents falling below the current poverty line, and achieve poverty alleviation in all poor counties and areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立国家基本公共服务项目清单。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should put in place a national catalogue of basic public services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全更加公平更可持续的社会保障制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should establish more equitable and sustainable social security systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施义务教育学校标准化、普及高中阶段教育、建设世界一流大学和一流学科等工程，劳动年龄人口平均受教育年限从10.23年提高到10.8年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to ensure that all schools providing compulsory education comply with educational standards, that everyone has access to secondary education, that China has more world-class universities and first-class fields of discipline, and that the average number of years of schooling received by the working-age population increases from 10.23 to 10.8 years. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实现城镇新增就业5000万人以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to create 50 million plus new urban jobs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善收入分配制度，缩小收入差距，提高中等收入人口比重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to improve the income distribution system, reduce the income gap, and increase the proportion of the middle-income group in the whole populace. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善住房保障体系，城镇棚户区住房改造2000万套。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should improve systems of government housing support, which should include the rebuilding of 20 million housing units in rundown urban areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进健康中国建设，人均预期寿命提高1岁。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to work for progress in building a Healthy China and achieve a one-year increase in average life expectancy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极应对人口老龄化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to respond proactively to population aging. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建现代公共文化服务体系，实施公民道德建设、中华文化传承等工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should build a modern system of public cultural services and put into effect cultural programs to boost civic morality and keep Chinese culture thriving. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们既要让人民的物质生活更殷实，又要让人民的精神生活更丰富。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These efforts should enable people not only to enjoy a better life in material terms, but also to live a more enriching intellectual and cultural life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好“十三五”时期经济社会发展工作，实现全面建成小康社会目标，必须着力把握好三点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To achieve success in our work to promote economic and social development during the period of the 13th Five-Year Plan and finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects, we must keep to the following three guidelines:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是牢牢抓住发展第一要务不放松。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, give top priority to development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展是硬道理，是解决我国所有问题的关键。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Development is of primary importance to China and is the key to solving every problem we face. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今后五年是跨越“中等收入陷阱”的重要阶段，各种矛盾和风险明显增多。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>During the next five years, we must take particular care to avoid falling into the "middle-income trap," and we need to address an increasing number of problems and risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展如逆水行舟，不进则退。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pursuing development is like sailing against the current: you either forge ahead or drift downstream. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须毫不动摇坚持以经济建设为中心，推动科学发展，妥善应对风险挑战，使中国经济这艘巨轮破浪远航。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must remain committed to economic development as our central task, endeavor to promote sound development, and respond effectively to risks and challenges so as to ensure that China's economy, like a gigantic ship, breaks the waves and goes the distance.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是大力推进结构性改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, make major headway in carrying out structural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>当前发展中总量问题与结构性问题并存，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At present, we face problems both with aggregate supply and demand and with our structures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>结构性问题更加突出，要用改革的办法推进结构调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The structural problems are more acute, and reform should be conducted to adjust these structures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在适度扩大总需求的同时，突出抓好供给侧结构性改革，既做减法，又做加法，减少无效和低端供给，扩大有效和中高端供给，增加公共产品和公共服务供给，使供给和需求协同促进经济发展，提高全要素生产率，不断解放和发展社会生产力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While working to achieve an appropriate expansion of aggregate demand, we need to give particular emphasis to structural reform on the supply side, reducing supply in some areas while increasing it in others. This means that we need to reduce ineffective and lower-end supply while increasing effective and medium- and high-end supply, increase the supply of public goods and services, ensure that development is driven by both supply and demand, and improve total-factor productivity. This should enable us to unleash and develop productive forces.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是加快新旧发展动能接续转换。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, accelerate the shift in driving forces for development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济发展必然会有新旧动能迭代更替的过程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the course of economic development, it is only natural that old drivers of growth are replaced by new ones.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>当传统动能由强变弱时，需要新动能异军突起和传统动能转型，形成新的“双引擎”，才能推动经济持续增长、跃上新台阶。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As conventional driving forces weaken, it is critical that new driving forces emerge and that the conventional ones undergo a transformation so that new twin engines are formed; only then is it possible to upgrade the economy and achieve sustainable growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>当前我国发展正处于这样一个关键时期，必须培育壮大新动能，加快发展新经济。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is the crucial period in which China currently finds itself, and during which we must build up powerful new drivers in order to accelerate the development of the new economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要推动新技术、新产业、新业态加快成长，以体制机制创新促进分享经济发展，建设共享平台，做大高技术产业、现代服务业等新兴产业集群，打造动力强劲的新引擎。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to move faster to develop new technologies, industries, and forms of business, boost the development of a sharing economy through institutional innovations, create sharing platforms, and develop emerging industry clusters such as high-tech and modern service industry clusters, thus creating strong new engines. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>运用信息网络等现代技术，推动生产、管理和营销模式变革，重塑产业链、供应链、价值链，改造提升传统动能，使之焕发新的生机与活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use network-based information technology and other modern technologies to drive changes in models of production, management, and marketing, create new industry chains, supply chains, and value chains, and transform and upgrade conventional drivers, thus injecting them with new vitality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从根本上说，发展的不竭力量蕴藏在人民群众之中。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Ultimately, it is the people who are the inexhaustible source of power that drives development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>9亿多劳动力、1亿多受过高等教育和有专业技能的人才，是我们最大的资源和优势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A workforce of over 900 million, of whom over 100 million have received higher education or are professionally trained: this is our greatest resource and strength. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实现新旧动能转换，推动发展转向更多依靠人力人才资源和创新，既是一个伴随阵痛的调整过程，也是一个充满希望的升级过程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Obviously, replacing old drivers of growth with new ones and achieving a shift in development toward greater reliance on human resources, human capital, and innovation is a process of painful adjustment. But it is at the same time an upgrading process with great promise. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>只要闯过这个关口，中国经济就一定能够浴火重生、再创辉煌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We just have to get through this process, and we can, without question, reinvigorate the economy and ensure its dynamic growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>展望今后五年，我们充满必胜信心。如期实现全面建成小康社会目标，人民生活将会更加美好，中国特色社会主义事业前景一定会更加光明！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Looking ahead to the next five years, we are fully confident that we will finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects within the set timeframe, that our people will enjoy better lives, and that there will be an even brighter future for the cause of building socialism with Chinese characteristics.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三、2016年重点工作</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I now want to discuss the major areas of work for 2016.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年是全面建成小康社会决胜阶段的开局之年，也是推进结构性改革的攻坚之年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is the first year of the decisive stage in finishing building a moderately prosperous society in all respects and a crucial year in carrying out structural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好政府工作，必须</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To ensure that the government's goal for this year is accomplished, we must do the following:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高举中国特色社会主义伟大旗帜，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- hold high the great banner of socialism with Chinese characteristics;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面贯彻党的十八大和十八届三中、四中、五中全会精神，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- implement the guiding principles of the 18th National Congress of the CPC and the third, fourth, and fifth plenary sessions of the 18th CPC Central Committee;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以邓小平理论、“三个代表”重要思想、科学发展观为指导，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- follow the guidance of Deng Xiaoping Theory, the Theory of Three Represents, and the Scientific Outlook on Development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入贯彻习近平总书记系列重要讲话精神，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- put into practice the guiding principles from General Secretary Xi Jinping's major policy addresses;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>按照“五位一体”总体布局和“四个全面”战略布局，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- work in accordance with the overall plan for promoting all-round economic, political, cultural, social, and ecological progress and the Four-Pronged Comprehensive Strategy;*</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持改革开放，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- continue reform and opening up;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以新发展理念引领发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- follow the new vision of development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持稳中求进工作总基调，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- follow the general principle of making progress while working to keep performance stable;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适应经济发展新常态，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- adapt to the new normal in economic development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实行宏观政策要稳、产业政策要准、微观政策要活、改革政策要实、社会政策要托底的总体思路，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- follow the general guidelines that macro policies should be stable, industrial policies targeted, micro policies flexible, reform policies practical, and that social policies should ensure basic needs;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把握好稳增长与调结构的平衡，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- maintain a balance between ensuring steady growth and making structural adjustments;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持经济运行在合理区间，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- ensure that the economy operates within an appropriate range;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力加强供给侧结构性改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- strengthen supply-side structural reform;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快培育新的发展动能，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- accelerate the fostering of new driving forces for development;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改造提升传统比较优势，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- strengthen traditional comparative advantages;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓好去产能、去库存、去杠杆、降成本、补短板，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- cut overcapacity and excess inventory, deleverage, reduce costs, and strengthen points of weakness;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强民生保障，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- strengthen basic safeguards for public wellbeing;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实防控风险，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- prevent and control risks.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力实现“十三五”时期经济社会发展良好开局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>By working to achieve all of these, we should get off to a good start in economic and social development during the period covered by the 13th Five-Year Plan.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年发展的主要预期目标是：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The main development targets for 2016 are as follows:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值增长6.5%－7%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- GDP growth of 6.5% to 7%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民消费价格涨幅3%左右，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- CPI increase kept at around 3%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业1000万人以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- creation of at least ten million new urban jobs;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇登记失业率4.5%以内，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- registered urban unemployment rate kept within 4.5%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进出口回稳向好，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- a steady rise in import and export volumes;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国际收支基本平衡，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- a basic balance in international payments;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民收入增长和经济增长基本同步。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- increases in personal income basically in step with economic growth;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗下降3.4%以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- a reduction in energy consumption per unit of GDP of at least 3.4%;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>主要污染物排放继续减少。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- further reductions in the release of major pollutants.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济增长预期目标6.5%－7%，考虑了与全面建成小康社会目标相衔接，考虑了推进结构性改革的需要，也有利于稳定和引导市场预期。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In setting a projected growth rate of between 6.5% and 7%, we have taken into consideration the need to finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects and the need to advance structural reform. It will also help guide market expectations and keep them stable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳增长主要是为了保就业、惠民生，有6.5%－7%的增速就能够实现比较充分的就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The aim of maintaining stable growth is primarily to ensure employment and promote the people's wellbeing, and a growth rate of between 6.5% and 7% will allow for relatively full employment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>综合分析各方面情况，今年我国发展面临的困难更多更大、挑战更为严峻，我们要做打硬仗的充分准备。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A comprehensive analysis of all factors shows that China will face more and tougher problems and challenges in its development this year, so we must be fully prepared to fight a difficult battle. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从国际看，世界经济深度调整、复苏乏力，国际贸易增长低迷，金融和大宗商品市场波动不定，地缘政治风险上升，外部环境的不稳定不确定因素增加，对我国发展的影响不可低估。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Internationally, the global economy is experiencing profound changes and struggling to recover; growth in trade is weak;there are fluctuations in the financial and commodity markets; geopolitical risks are rising; and there are increasing instabilities and uncertainties in China's external environment. We should not underestimate the impact all of this will have on China's development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从国内看，长期积累的矛盾和风险进一步显现，经济增速换挡、结构调整阵痛、新旧动能转换相互交织，经济下行压力加大。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Domestically, problems and risks that have been building up over the years are becoming more evident; the change of pace in economic growth, the difficulties associated with structural adjustments, and the transformation of the drivers of growth present interwoven problems; and downward pressure on the economy is growing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>但困难和挑战并不可怕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>But we will not be daunted by these problems and challenges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国的发展从来都是在应对挑战中前进的，没有过不去的坎。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China has from the start been developing while responding to challenges; there is no difficulty we cannot get beyond. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经过多年的快速发展，我国物质基础雄厚，经济韧性强、潜力足、回旋余地大，改革开放不断注入新动力，创新宏观调控积累了丰富经验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Thanks to years of rapid development, China has laid a solid material foundation, and its economy is hugely resilient and has enormous potential and ample room for growth. At the same time, reform and opening up has been injecting new impetus into economic growth, and a wealth of experience has been gained in developing new ways of conducting macro regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>特别是我们有中国共产党的坚强领导和中国特色社会主义制度，中国人民勤劳智慧。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In addition, we have the guidance of the CPC and the system of socialism with Chinese characteristics, and our people are talented and hardworking. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>只要我们万众一心，共克时艰，就一定能够实现全年经济社会发展目标。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As long as we work together as one to surmount all difficulties, we will definitely achieve the targets for economic and social development in 2016.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要重点做好八个方面工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will carry out the following eight tasks:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（一）稳定和完善宏观经济政策，保持经济运行在合理区间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. Improve and keep stable our macroeconomic policies to ensure that the economy performs within an appropriate range. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们宏观调控还有创新手段和政策储备，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At present, we still have new instruments for macro regulation and a good reserve of policies at our disposal. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>既要立足当前、有针对性地出招，顶住经济下行压力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the one hand, we will focus on current realities and take targeted steps to withstand the downward pressure on the economy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>又要着眼长远、留有后手、谋势蓄势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the other hand, we must have our long-term development goals in mind, keep some policy tools as options for later use, strategize our moves, and gather strength. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续实施积极的财政政策和稳健的货币政策，创新宏观调控方式，加强区间调控、定向调控、相机调控，统筹运用财政、货币政策和产业、投资、价格等政策工具，采取结构性改革尤其是供给侧结构性改革举措，为经济发展营造良好环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement proactive fiscal policy and prudent monetary policy, develop new approaches to macro regulation, strengthen range-based, targeted, and well-timed regulation, use fiscal and monetary policies and industry, investment, and pricing policy tools in a coordinated way, and implement structural reform, particularly supply-side structural reform, so as to create an enabling environment for economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极的财政政策要加大力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will pursue a more proactive fiscal policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年拟安排财政赤字2.18万亿元，比去年增加5600亿元，赤字率提高到3%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The government deficit for 2016 is projected to be 2.18 trillion yuan, an increase of 560 billion yuan over last year, meaning the deficit-to-GDP ratio will rise to 3%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>其中，中央财政赤字1.4万亿元，地方财政赤字7800亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Of the deficit, 1.4 trillion yuan will be carried by the central government, and the remaining 780 billion yuan will be carried by local governments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>安排地方专项债券4000亿元，继续发行地方政府置换债券。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Special bonds for local governments will total 400 billion yuan, and local government debt-converting bonds will continue to be issued. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国财政赤字率和政府负债率在世界主要经济体中相对较低，这样的安排是必要的、可行的，也是安全的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's deficit-to-GDP ratio and government debt ratio are lower than those of other major economies; such steps are necessary, feasible, and also safe.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适度扩大财政赤字，主要用于减税降费，进一步减轻企业负担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The moderate increase in government deficit is projected primarily to cover tax and fee reductions for enterprises, a step that will further reduce their burdens. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年将采取三项举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The following three measures will be adopted this year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是全面实施营改增，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, business tax will be replaced with VAT in all sectors.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从5月1日起，将试点范围扩大到建筑业、房地产业、金融业、生活服务业，并将所有企业新增不动产所含增值税纳入抵扣范围，确保所有行业税负只减不增。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Starting from May 1st, the scope of work to pilot this measure will be extended to the construction, real estate, financial, and consumer service industries, and VAT deductions will cover all new immovable property of enterprises to ensure that the tax burdens on all industries are reduced. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是取消违规设立的政府性基金，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, government-managed funds set up without authorization will be abolished;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>停征和归并一批政府性基金，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>the collection of contributions to certain government-managed funds will be suspended, and some of these funds will be consolidated;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大水利建设基金等免征范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and more enterprises will be exempted from contributing to water conservancy construction funds and other government-managed funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是将18项行政事业性收费的免征范围，从小微企业扩大到所有企业和个人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, exemptions from 18 administrative charges which currently apply only to small and micro businesses will be expanded to include all enterprises and individuals. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施上述政策，今年将比改革前减轻企业和个人负担5000多亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Through the above policies, the burdens on enterprises and individuals will be cut by more than 500 billion yuan this year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时，适当增加必要的财政支出和政府投资，加大对民生等薄弱环节的支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At the same time, we will increase government expenditures and investment as appropriate to work on living standards and other areas in need of strengthening. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新财政支出方式，优化财政支出结构，该保的一定要保住，该减的一定要减下来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop new ways for government funds to be spent and improve the government spending mix to ensure that all essential items receive sufficient funding, while non-essential items are cut.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快财税体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal and tax reforms will be stepped up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进中央与地方事权和支出责任划分改革，合理确定增值税中央和地方分享比例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move forward with the reform of the way powers and expenditure responsibilities are shared between the central and local governments, ensuring that the proportion of VAT revenue received by the central and local governments is determined appropriately. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把适合作为地方收入的税种下划给地方，在税政管理权限方面给地方适当放权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Taxes suitable as sources of local government revenue will be handed over to local governments along with the corresponding administrative powers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步压缩中央专项转移支付规模，今年一般性转移支付规模增长12.2%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government special transfer payments to local governments will be further reduced, while this year's general transfer payments will be increased by 12.2%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推开资源税从价计征改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will extend ad valorem rates to all resource taxes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法实施税收征管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the law-based administration of tax collection. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立规范的地方政府举债融资机制，对财政实力强、债务风险较低的，按法定程序适当增加债务限额。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish a well-regulated mechanism for local governments to secure financing through bond issuance and make moderate upward adjustments to debt ceilings for local governments with strong financial resources and low debt risks through statutory procedures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要坚持过紧日子，把每一笔钱都花在明处、用在实处。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels must tighten their belts and spend every sum of money where it can be seen and where it's most needed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳健的货币政策要灵活适度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will pursue prudent monetary policy that is flexible and appropriate. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年广义货币M2预期增长13%左右，社会融资规模余额增长13%左右。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Both the M2 money supply and aggregate financing in the economy are forecasted to grow by around 13% in 2016. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要统筹运用公开市场操作、利率、准备金率、再贷款等各类货币政策工具，保持流动性合理充裕，疏通传导机制，降低融资成本，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use a full range of monetary policy tools including open market operations, interest rates, required reserve ratios, and re-lending to maintain sufficient liquidity at a proper level, improve the transmission mechanism of monetary policy, and reduce financing costs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对实体经济特别是小微企业、“三农”等支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide more support for the real economy, particularly for small and micro businesses as well as agriculture, rural areas, and farmers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化金融体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of the financial sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快改革完善现代金融监管体制，提高金融服务实体经济效率，实现金融风险监管全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster in the reform to improve the modern financial regulatory system and ensure that the financial sector serves the real economy more efficiently and that regulation covers all financial risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化利率市场化改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Interest rates will be further liberalized. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续完善人民币汇率市场化形成机制，保持人民币汇率在合理均衡水平上基本稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Improvements will be made to the market-based mechanism for setting the RMB exchange rate to ensure it remains generally stable at an appropriate and balanced level. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化国有商业银行和开发性、政策性金融机构改革，发展民营银行，启动投贷联动试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of state-owned commercial banks as well as development and policy-backed financial institutions, develop private banks, and launch trials to allow commercial banks to participate in combined debt-equity investments into startups and small businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进股票、债券市场改革和法治化建设，促进多层次资本市场健康发展，提高直接融资比重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move forward with the reform of stock and bond markets and increase the level of rule of law in their development, promote the sound development of the multilevel capital market, and ensure that the proportion of direct financing is increased. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适时启动“深港通”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Shenzhen-Hong Kong Stock Connect will be launched at an appropriate time. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立巨灾保险制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A catastrophe insurance system will be established. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>规范发展互联网金融。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to see that Internet finance develops in line with regulations,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展普惠金融和绿色金融。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will make a major push to develop inclusive and green finance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强全口径外债宏观审慎管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen unified, macroprudential management of foreign debt. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎紧制度笼子，整顿规范金融秩序，严厉打击金融诈骗、非法集资和证券期货领域的违法犯罪活动，坚决守住不发生系统性区域性风险的底线。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will tighten institutional constraints, safeguard order in the financial sector, crack down on financial fraud, illegal fundraising, and unlawful and criminal activities in the securities and futures markets, and make sure that no systemic or regional financial risks arise.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（二）加强供给侧结构性改革，增强持续增长动力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2. Strengthen supply-side structural reform to drive sustained growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>围绕解决重点领域的突出矛盾和问题，加快破除体制机制障碍，以供给侧结构性改革提高供给体系的质量和效率，进一步激发市场活力和社会创造力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To solve acute problems in key areas, we must work faster to remove institutional obstacles and carry out supply-side structural reform to improve the quality and efficiency of the supply system, and further stimulate market vitality and the creativity of society.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动简政放权、放管结合、优化服务改革向纵深发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will deepen reforms to streamline administration, delegate more powers, improve regulation, and provide better services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以敬民之心，行简政之道，切实转变政府职能、提高效能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the people in mind, we will streamline administration, transform the functions of the government, and improve its performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续大力削减行政审批事项，注重解决放权不同步、不协调、不到位问题，对下放的审批事项，要让地方能接得住、管得好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As we continue to cancel the requirement of government review for more matters, we will focus on addressing unsynchronized, uncoordinated, and incomplete delegation of powers and make sure that local governments to which powers of review have been delegated are able to properly exercise those powers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化商事制度改革，开展证照分离试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of the business system and launch trials to separate operating permits and business licenses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面公布地方政府权力和责任清单，在部分地区试行市场准入负面清单制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will release the lists of all powers and responsibilities of local governments, and begin piloting a negative list for market access in some regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对行政事业性收费、政府定价或指导价经营服务性收费、政府性基金、国家职业资格，实行目录清单管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw up lists and catalogues to manage administrative charges, business fees and charges set by the government or set under its guidance, government-managed funds, and professional qualifications recognized by the state. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建设统一开放、竞争有序的市场体系，打破地方保护。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to establish a unified, open, competitive, and orderly market system, and put an end to local protectionism. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化价格改革，加强价格监管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen pricing reform and tighten up supervision of prices. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>修改和废止有碍发展的行政法规和规范性文件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will revise or abolish any administrative regulations and normative documents that are holding back development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新事中事后监管方式，全面推行“双随机、一公开”监管，随机抽取检查对象，随机选派执法检查人员，及时公布查处结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop new ways of conducting oversight over the whole process of business operations, and introduce across the board an oversight model drawing on random inspections by randomly selected law enforcement officers or inspectors and requiring the prompt release of results. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进综合行政执法改革，实施企业信用信息统一归集、依法公示、联合惩戒、社会监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the reform for coordinated administrative law enforcement and adopt a unified approach to gathering information on enterprise credit, release such information in accordance with the law, ensure joint punitive action is taken where necessary, and encourage public oversight. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推行“互联网+政务服务”，实现部门间数据共享，让居民和企业少跑腿、好办事、不添堵。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out the "Internet Plus government services" model and promote better information sharing between government departments, so that the public and businesses need to make fewer visits to government departments to get things done, find procedures simpler, and find the service satisfactory. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>简除烦苛，禁察非法，使人民群众有更平等的机会和更大的创造空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will cut red tape and root out illegalities to ensure that the people have more equal opportunities and greater space for creativity.=</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分释放全社会创业创新潜能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will ensure that the whole country's potential for starting businesses and making innovations is released. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力实施创新驱动发展战略，促进科技与经济深度融合，提高实体经济的整体素质和竞争力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the strategy of innovation-driven development, see that science and technology become more deeply embedded in the economy, and improve the overall quality and competitiveness of the real economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是强化企业创新主体地位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will ensure that enterprises lead in making innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实企业研发费用加计扣除和加速折旧政策，完善高新技术企业、科技企业孵化器等税收优惠政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement additional tax deductions for their research and development, accelerate the depreciation of their fixed assets, and increase tax policy support for high-tech enterprises and science and technology business incubators. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持行业领军企业建设高水平研发机构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support leading enterprises in building top-level research and development institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快将国家自主创新示范区试点政策推广到全国，再建设一批国家自主创新示范区、高新区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to achieve nationwide implementation of the policy of national innovation demonstration zones, and establish another set of national innovation demonstration zones and high-tech development zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是发挥大众创业、万众创新和“互联网+”集众智汇众力的乘数效应。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will help people to pool their ideas and talents through a synergy of business startups, innovation, and the Internet Plus. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>打造众创、众包、众扶、众筹平台，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Platforms will be created for crowd innovation, crowd support, crowdsourcing, and crowdfunding,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建大中小企业、高校、科研机构、创客多方协同的新型创业创新机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and mechanisms will be built to encourage new types of business startups and innovation-making through cooperation between enterprises, institutions of higher learning, research institutes, and makers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设一批“双创”示范基地，培育创业创新服务业，规范发展天使、创业、产业等投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish demonstration centers for business startups and innovation, foster a business startup and innovation service industry, and ensure angel investment, venture capital, industrial investment, and other investment develop in accordance with regulations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持分享经济发展，提高资源利用效率，让更多人参与进来、富裕起来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give our support to the development of a sharing economy and see that resources are used more efficiently and that more people take part and benefit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施更积极、更开放、更有效的人才引进政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adopt more active, open, and effective policies to attract talent from overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强知识产权保护和运用，依法严厉打击侵犯知识产权和制假售假行为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the protection and use of intellectual property rights and look to the law to crack down on the infringement of these rights and on the production and sale of counterfeit products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是深化科技管理体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will deepen the reform of the management system for science and technology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大高校和科研院所自主权，砍掉科研管理中的繁文缛节。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Greater autonomy will be given to universities and research institutes, and red tape will be cut in the management of research projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施支持科技成果转移转化的政策措施，完善股权期权税收优惠政策和分红奖励办法，鼓励科研人员创业创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Policies and measures will be implemented to support the transfer and commercialization of scientific and technological achievements, and tax incentives for stocks and options, and profit sharing and bonus plans will be improved to encourage researchers to start businesses and make innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力弘扬创新文化，厚植创新沃土，营造敢为人先、宽容失败的良好氛围，充分激发企业家精神，调动全社会创业创新积极性，汇聚成推动发展的磅礴力量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will foster a culture of innovation and create an enabling environment for innovation in which people venture to break new ground and failure is tolerated. I am sure that these initiatives will inspire entrepreneurialism and motivate our society to start businesses and make innovations, and thus create a powerful force to drive development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力化解过剩产能和降本增效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will ensure that overcapacity is cut, costs are lowered, and business performance is improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点抓好钢铁、煤炭等困难行业去产能，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on addressing the overcapacity in the steel, coal, and other industries facing difficulties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持市场倒逼、企业主体、地方组织、中央支持，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In this process, the market should serve as a check, enterprises should be the major actors, local governments should play a coordinating role, and the central government should provide support.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>运用经济、法律、技术、环保、质量、安全等手段，严格控制新增产能，坚决淘汰落后产能，有序退出过剩产能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use economic, legal, technological, environmental, quality inspection, and safety-related means to strictly control the expansion of production capacity, shut down outdated production facilities, and eliminate overcapacity in a planned way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>采取兼并重组、债务重组或破产清算等措施，积极稳妥处置“僵尸企业”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will address the issue of "zombie enterprises" proactively yet prudently by using measures such as mergers, reorganizations, debt restructurings, and bankruptcy liquidations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善财政、金融等支持政策，中央财政安排1000亿元专项奖补资金，重点用于职工分流安置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal, financial, and other policies will be improved to support this work. One hundred billion yuan in rewards and subsidies will be provided by the central government, which will be mainly used to resettle employees laid off from these enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>采取综合措施，降低企业交易、物流、财务、用能等成本，坚决遏制涉企乱收费，对违规行为要严肃查处。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take a full range of measures to reduce the transaction, logistics, financial, and energy consumption costs of enterprises, and work to put a stop to the collection of arbitrary and unwarranted fees from enterprises and be strict about investigating and punishing violations of regulations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>努力改善产品和服务供给。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to ensure the supply of goods and services is improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>突出抓好三个方面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will concentrate our efforts on the following three areas:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是提升消费品品质。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will see that the quality of consumer goods is improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快质量安全标准与国际标准接轨，建立商品质量惩罚性赔偿制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to bring domestic quality and safety standards in line with international standards, and establish a system for making producers pay punitive compensation for failing to meet product quality standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励企业开展个性化定制、柔性化生产，培育精益求精的工匠精神，增品种、提品质、创品牌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also encourage enterprises to use flexible and custom-tailored production processes and foster a craftsmanship spirit of striving for the best, so that more types of products, products of a higher quality, and brand products will be made. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是促进制造业升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will work to upgrade manufacturing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进“中国制造+互联网”，建设若干国家级制造业创新平台，实施一批智能制造示范项目，启动工业强基、绿色制造、高端装备等重大工程，组织实施重大技术改造升级工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to promote the integrated development of Made in China 2025 and the Internet Plus action plan; build national platforms for innovation in manufacturing; carry out demonstration programs in smart manufacturing; launch projects to build a more solid foundation for industry development, promote green manufacturing, and develop high-end equipment; and carry out major technological transformation and upgrading initiatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是加快现代服务业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will accelerate the development of the modern service sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动新一轮国家服务业综合改革试点，实施高技术服务业创新工程，大力发展数字创意产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will launch a new round of national pilot projects for all-round service sector reform as well as projects to promote innovation in high-tech services, and channel great efforts into developing the digital creative industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>放宽市场准入，提高生产性服务业专业化、生活性服务业精细化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will relax restrictions on market access to the service sector, and ensure greater specialization in producer services and higher refinement in consumer services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设一批光网城市，推进5万个行政村通光纤，让更多城乡居民享受数字化生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiber-optic networks will be developed in a number of cities and 50,000 administrative villages will be linked up to fiber-optic networks, thus enabling more urban and rural residents to enjoy a more digital way of life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推进国有企业改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will push for progress in SOE reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今明两年，要以改革促发展，坚决打好国有企业提质增效攻坚战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year and next, we will use reform to promote the development of SOEs and push hard to ensure success in upgrading them and improving their performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动国有企业特别是中央企业结构调整，创新发展一批，重组整合一批，清理退出一批。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will prompt SOEs, especially those managed by the central government, to make structural adjustments so that some will be developed through innovation, others will be reorganized or merged, and still others will exit the market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进股权多元化改革，开展落实企业董事会职权、市场化选聘经营者、职业经理人制度、混合所有制、员工持股等试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out reforms to diversify their types of equity and introduce on a trial basis the assumption of powers and responsibilities by corporate boards of directors, competitive open selection and recruitment of executives, recruitment of professional managers, mixed ownership, and employee equity stakes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化企业用人制度改革，探索建立与市场化选任方式相适应的高层次人才和企业经营管理者薪酬制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the enterprise personnel management system and explore the possibility of establishing remuneration systems for senior ranking personnel and corporate executives that are compatible with competitive selection and recruitment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快改组组建国有资本投资、运营公司。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work faster to establish state capital investment and management companies through reorganization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以管资本为主推进国有资产监管机构职能转变，防止国有资产流失，实现国有资产保值增值。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To prevent the loss of state assets and ensure their value is maintained or increased, we will encourage state-owned asset supervisory and management authorities to shift their focus to the use of state capital. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>赋予地方更多国有企业改革自主权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local governments will be granted more power over SOE reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快剥离国有企业办社会职能，解决历史遗留问题，让国有企业瘦身健体，增强核心竞争力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move more quickly to relieve SOEs of their obligations to operate social programs and resolve their other longstanding issues, enabling them to become leaner and healthier and to increase their core competitiveness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更好激发非公有制经济活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will energize the non-public sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大幅放宽电力、电信、交通、石油、天然气、市政公用等领域市场准入，消除各种隐性壁垒，鼓励民营企业扩大投资、参与国有企业改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will significantly relax restrictions on entry into markets such as electricity, telecommunications, transport, petroleum, natural gas, and municipal public utilities, remove hidden barriers, and encourage private companies to increase investment in these areas and participate in SOE reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在项目核准、融资服务、财税政策、土地使用等方面一视同仁。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In these fields, private companies will enjoy the same treatment afforded to SOEs in terms of project verification and approval, financing, fiscal and tax policies, and land availability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法平等保护各种所有制经济产权，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, in accordance with the law, provide equal protection to the property rights of entities under all forms of ownership;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严肃查处侵犯非公有制企业及非公有制经济人士合法权益的行为，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will ensure that, without fail, infringements on the legitimate rights and interests of non-public sector enterprises and individuals are investigated and prosecuted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>营造公平、公正、透明、稳定的法治环境，构建新型政商关系，促进各类企业各展其长、共同发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create a rule of law environment that is fair, just, transparent, and stable and establish new government-business relations to help all types of enterprises develop side by side based on their own respective strengths.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（三）深挖国内需求潜力，开拓发展更大空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. Tap the potential of domestic demand to increase the space for development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适度扩大需求总量，积极调整改革需求结构，促进供给需求有效对接、投资消费有机结合、城乡区域协调发展，形成对经济发展稳定而持久的内需支撑。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to achieve a moderate expansion of aggregate demand, adjust and reform the composition of demand, strive for better alignment between supply and demand and between investment and consumption, and work to achieve greater balance in the development of urban and rural areas and of different regions. This will create steady and long-term domestic demand to sustain economic development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增强消费拉动经济增长的基础作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will strengthen the foundational role of consumption in promoting economic growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适应消费升级趋势，破除政策障碍，优化消费环境，维护消费者权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To adapt to the trend toward high-end consumption, we will remove policy barriers, improve the consumer environment, and safeguard the rights and interests of consumers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持发展养老、健康、家政、教育培训、文化体育等服务消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the growth of consumption in elderly care, health services, housekeeping services, educational and training services, and cultural and sports services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>壮大网络信息、智能家居、个性时尚等新兴消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to strengthen the growth of emerging areas of consumption such as information goods and services, smart homes, and personalized fashion. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进线上线下协调互动、平等竞争，推动实体商业创新转型。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote coordination, interaction, and fair competition between the online and the offline and encourage physical stores to transform themselves through innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善物流配送网络，促进快递业健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will help ensure the improvement of logistics networks and the healthy development of express delivery services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>活跃二手车市场，大力发展和推广以电动汽车为主的新能源汽车，加快建设城市停车场和充电设施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to stimulate the second-hand car market, channel great effort into developing and promoting the use of new-energy vehicles, particularly electric vehicles, and move faster to build urban car parks and install charging facilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在全国开展消费金融公司试点，鼓励金融机构创新消费信贷产品。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out nationwide trials to set up consumer financing companies and encourage financial institutions to develop new consumer credit products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>降低部分消费品进口关税，增设免税店。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will cut import tariffs on some consumer goods and increase the number of duty-free stores. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实带薪休假制度，加强旅游交通、景区景点、自驾车营地等设施建设，规范旅游市场秩序，迎接正在兴起的大众旅游时代。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure people are able to take their paid vacations, strengthen the development of tourist and transport facilities, scenic spots and tourist sites, and recreational vehicle parks, and see that the tourist market operates in line with regulations. With these efforts, we will usher in a new era of mass tourism.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥有效投资对稳增长调结构的关键作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will see that effective investment plays a key role in maintaining stable growth and making structural adjustments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国基础设施和民生领域有许多短板，产业亟需改造升级，有效投资仍有很大空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The many weak areas in infrastructure and public services in China and the urgent need for industry upgrading leave vast scope for growth in effective investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要启动一批“十三五”规划重大项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will launch a number of projects set forth in the 13th Five-Year Plan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完成铁路投资8000亿元以上、公路投资1.65万亿元，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More than 800 billion yuan will be invested in railway construction, and investment in road construction will reach 1.65 trillion yuan.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>再开工20项重大水利工程，建设水电核电、特高压输电、智能电网、油气管网、城市轨道交通等重大项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A further 20 water conservancy projects will be carried out, and major projects will be launched to develop hydropower, nuclear power, ultra high-voltage power transmission, smart grids, pipelines for oil and gas transmission, and urban rail transit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央预算内投资安排5000亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government budgetary investment will be 500 billion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化投融资体制改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the investment and financing systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续以市场化方式筹集专项建设基金，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Funds for specific projects will continue to be raised through market-based mechanisms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动地方融资平台转型改制进行市场化融资，探索基础设施等资产证券化，扩大债券融资规模。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local financing platforms will be required to transform themselves and shift toward market-based financing, the securitization of tangible assets such as infrastructure will be explored, and debt financing will be increased. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善政府和社会资本合作模式，用好1800亿元引导基金，依法严格履行合同，充分激发社会资本参与热情。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the public-private partnership model, make good use of the 180 billion yuan in seed funds, and strictly honor contracts in accordance with the law, so as to bring the enthusiasm of private investors to the table.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进新型城镇化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will advance new urbanization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇化是现代化的必由之路，是我国最大的内需潜力和发展动能所在。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Urbanization is the path we need to take to develop a modern China. It is where we will find the greatest potential for domestic demand and the most powerful force for sustaining economic development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年重点抓好三项工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will take the following three major steps regarding urbanization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是加快农业转移人口市民化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will move faster to see that urban residency is granted to more people with rural household registration living in urban areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化户籍制度改革，放宽城镇落户条件，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of the household registration system and relax restrictions on eligibility for urban residency.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全“人地钱”挂钩政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will introduce policies for making both the transfer payments and the land designated for urban development granted to the government of a local jurisdiction conditional upon the number of people with rural household registration who are granted permanent urban residency in that jurisdiction. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大新型城镇化综合试点范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The full range of trials for developing new urbanization will be extended to more areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居住证具有很高的含金量，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Residence cards are important assets for their holders. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要加快覆盖未落户的城镇常住人口，使他们依法享有居住地义务教育、就业、医疗等基本公共服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must move faster to ensure that permanent urban residents without urban residency are issued residence cards, thus enabling them to enjoy, as provided for by law, the right to access compulsory education, employment, medical care, and other basic public services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展中西部地区中小城市和小城镇，容纳更多的农民工就近就业创业，让他们挣钱顾家两不误。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of small towns and small and medium-sized cities in the central and western regions to help more rural migrant workers find employment or start businesses in urban areas closer to home so that they do not have to choose between earning money and taking care of the families they leave behind. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是推进城镇保障性安居工程建设和房地产市场健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will promote the construction of government-subsidized housing in urban areas and the healthy development of the real estate market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年棚户区住房改造600万套，提高棚改货币化安置比例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will see to it that six million housing units are rebuilt in rundown urban areas and that more people displaced by the rebuilding of such areas receive monetary housing compensation rather than housing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善支持居民住房合理消费的税收、信贷政策，适应住房刚性需求和改善性需求，因城施策化解房地产库存，促进房地产市场平稳运行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Taking into consideration people's demand for buying homes or improving their housing situation, we will improve the tax and credit policies to support justified personal housing consumption and adopt different policies in different cities as appropriate to their local conditions, in order to cut housing inventory and promote stability in the real estate market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立租购并举的住房制度，把符合条件的外来人口逐步纳入公租房供应范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will put in place a housing system which encourages both renting and purchasing and, over time, enable eligible non-registered urban residents to apply for public rental housing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是加强城市规划建设管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will redouble our efforts to improve urban planning, development, and management. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增强城市规划的科学性、前瞻性、权威性、公开性，促进“多规合一”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make urban planning more sound, forward-looking, authoritative, and transparent and encourage local governments to integrate their various types of urban plans into a single master plan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开工建设城市地下综合管廊2000公里以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Construction will begin on at least 2,000 kilometers of utility tunnels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推广绿色建筑和建材，大力发展钢结构和装配式建筑，加快标准化建设，提高建筑技术水平和工程质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively promote environmentally friendly buildings and construction materials, make a big push to develop steel understructures and prefabricated modules, accelerate work to ensure adherence to construction standards, and see that the level of technique in building and the quality of construction projects are improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进城市管理体制创新，打造智慧城市，完善公共交通网络，治理交通拥堵等突出问题，改善人居环境，使人民群众生活得更安心、更省心、更舒心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage institutional innovation in urban management, work hard to create smart cities,improve public transport networks, address traffic congestion and other prominent problems, and improve living environments so that people can enjoy a more secure, relaxing, and satisfying city life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化区域发展格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to improve the layout of development across regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进“一带一路”建设，落实京津冀协同发展规划纲要，加快长江经济带发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will push ahead with the Belt and Road Initiative, carry out the development plan for the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei integration initiative, and speed up the development of the Yangtze Economic Belt. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施西部大开发“十三五”规划，实施新一轮东北地区等老工业基地振兴战略，出台促进中部地区崛起新十年规划，支持东部地区在体制创新、陆海统筹等方面率先突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw up and implement the 13th five-year plan for the large-scale development of the western region, implement a new round of strategies for revitalizing the old industrial bases in the Northeast and other parts of the country, adopt the new ten-year plan for fuelling the rise of the central region, and support the eastern region as it leads the country in making breakthroughs in institutional innovation and coordinated land and maritime development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进资源型地区经济转型升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the economic transformation and upgrading of resource-dependent regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持革命老区、民族地区、边疆地区、贫困地区发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of old revolutionary base areas, areas with concentrations of ethnic minorities, border areas, and poor areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定和实施国家海洋战略，维护国家海洋权益，保护海洋生态环境，拓展蓝色经济空间，建设海洋强国。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work out and implement a national maritime strategy, safeguard national maritime rights and interests, protect marine ecosystems and habitats, and open up more space for the blue economy so as to strengthen China's maritime development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（四）加快发展现代农业，促进农民持续增收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. Speed up efforts to develop modern agriculture and ensure sustained increases in rural incomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续毫不放松抓好“三农”工作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will, with as much care and attention as ever, continue focusing on our work related to agriculture, rural areas, and farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善强农惠农富农政策，深化农村改革，拓展农民就业增收渠道，着力提高农业质量、效益和竞争力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen policy support for these areas, deepen rural reform, expand the channels through which farmers can find employment and increase their income, and work to ensure that the quality, performance, and competitiveness of agriculture improve.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快农业结构调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will speed up structural adjustment in agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮食连续增产，为稳定物价、改善民生提供了有力保障，但也面临库存大幅增加、市场价格下跌等问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The output of food crops has continued to rise in recent years. This has helped to keep prices stable and ensure people's wellbeing, but it has also resulted in a buildup of excess stockpiles and falling market prices. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要完善农产品价格形成机制，引导农民适应市场需求调整种养结构，适当调减玉米种植面积。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To resolve this problem, we will improve the pricing mechanisms for agricultural products, while guiding farmers in adjusting what and how much they grow and breed in response to market demand and in making appropriate reductions to the amount of cultivated land devoted to growing corn. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>按照“市场定价、价补分离”原则，积极稳妥推进玉米收储制度改革，保障农民合理收益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Following the principle of letting the market determine prices and delinking subsidies from prices, we will reform in an active yet prudent way the system of corn purchase and storage to ensure reasonable returns for corn-growing farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要多措并举消化粮食库存，大力支持农产品精深加工，发展畜牧业，延伸农业产业链条；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adopt a full range of measures to reduce excess stockpiles of food, provide strong support for the processing of agricultural products to increase their value, develop the livestock industry, and extend the agricultural production chain.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定新一轮退耕还林还草方案，今年退耕还林还草1500万亩以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will formulate a plan for a new round of initiatives to turn marginal farmland into forest or grassland, with the target for this year being more than one million hectares. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这件事一举多得，务必抓好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There is much to be gained in this, and it must be carried out to full effect. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极发展多种形式农业适度规模经营，完善对家庭农场、专业大户、农民合作社等新型经营主体的扶持政策，培养新型职业农民，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of suitably scaled-up agricultural operations in diversified forms; improve policy support for family farms, large and specialized agricultural family operations, farming cooperatives, and other emerging forms of agribusiness; and cultivate a new type of skilled farmer.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励农户依法自愿有偿流转承包地，开展土地股份合作、联合或土地托管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage farmers, on a voluntary basis and in accordance with relevant laws, to transfer the land they contract to work on in return for compensation, enter into cooperation or association based on land as shares, or place their land under trusteeship. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化农村集体产权、农垦、集体林权、国有林场、农田水利、供销社等改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the rural collective property rights system, state farms on reclaimed land, collective forest tenure, state forestry farms, farmland irrigation and water conservancy, and rural supply and marketing cooperatives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化农业基础支撑。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- The foundation of agriculture will be strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面完成永久基本农田划定并实行特殊保护，加强高标准农田建设，增加深松土地1.5亿亩，新增高效节水灌溉面积2000万亩。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will complete our work nationwide on designating permanent basic cropland and provide special protection for such cropland, promote the development of high-standard cropland, improve the subsoil of an additional ten million hectares of cropland, and increase the area of cropland covered by efficient water-saving irrigation by 1.33 million hectares. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>探索耕地轮作休耕制度试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will explore trials of crop rotation and fallow land. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农业科技创新与推广，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the innovation and application of agricultural science and technology.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入开展粮食绿色高产高效创建，实施化肥农药零增长行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote green, high-yield, and cost efficient food crop production and achieve zero growth in the use of chemical fertilizers and insecticides. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障财政对农业投入，建立全国农业信贷担保体系，完善农业保险制度和农村金融服务，引导带动更多资金投向现代农业建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In fiscal allocations, investment in agriculture will be ensured, a national agricultural credit guaranty system will be established, the agricultural insurance system and rural financial services will be improved, and more investment in agricultural modernization will be encouraged.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改善农村公共设施和服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will improve public services and facilities in rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大农村基础设施建设力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up the development of rural infrastructure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新建改建农村公路20万公里，具备条件的乡镇和建制村要加快通硬化路、通客车。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>An additional 200,000 kilometers of rural roads will be built or upgraded. In towns, townships, and incorporated villages, where conditions allow, efforts should be stepped up to build paved roads and provide access to bus services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓紧新一轮农村电网改造升级，两年内实现农村稳定可靠供电服务和平原地区机井通电全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will act promptly to launch a new round of efforts to upgrade rural power grids, and our goal is to ensure a stable and reliable supply of power to all rural areas and all electric pumpsets on rural flatlands within the next two years. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施饮水安全巩固提升工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build on past progress to make further advances in providing access to safe drinking water. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动电子商务进农村。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the introduction of e-commerce into rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展农村人居环境整治，建设美丽宜居乡村。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to improve rural living environments, building an even more livable and beautiful countryside.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施脱贫攻坚工程。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will combat poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要完成1000万以上农村贫困人口脱贫任务，其中易地搬迁脱贫200万人以上，继续推进贫困农户危房改造。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will help more than ten million rural residents lift themselves out of poverty, including over two million poor residents who are to be relocated from inhospitable areas, and continue to rebuild the dilapidated housing of poor rural households. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政扶贫资金增长43.4%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government funds for poverty alleviation efforts will be increased by 43.4%. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在贫困县推进涉农资金整合。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In poor counties, various funds for rural development will be integrated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持精准扶贫脱贫，因人因地施策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take targeted measures to alleviate and eliminate poverty in light of local conditions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力培育特色产业，支持就业创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will channel significant energy into cultivating business operations with distinctive local features in support of employment and business development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>解决好通路、通水、通电、通网络等问题，增强集中连片特困地区和贫困人口发展能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will construct infrastructure such as roads, water and power supply, and Internet access, and work to strengthen the ability of contiguous poor areas and persons in need to achieve development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国家各项惠民政策和民生项目，要向贫困地区倾斜。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>National programs aimed at providing people with policy support and promoting people's wellbeing will be weighted toward poor areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入开展定点扶贫、东西协作扶贫，支持社会力量参与脱贫攻坚。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give stronger support to targeted poor areas, encourage the eastern region to help in the alleviation of poverty in the western region, and support nongovernmental participation in combatting poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扶贫脱贫是硬任务，各级政府已经立下军令状，必须按时保质保量完成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Poverty reduction is a must, governments at all levels have made the pledge, and it must be accomplished both qualitatively and quantitatively within the timeframe set.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（五）推进新一轮高水平对外开放，着力实现合作共赢。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>5. Carry out a new round of high-quality opening up and work to achieve mutually beneficial cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对国际经济合作和竞争格局的深刻变化，顺应国内经济提质增效升级的迫切需要，要坚定不移扩大对外开放，在开放中增强发展新动能、增添改革新动力、增创竞争新优势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the face of profound changes in international economic cooperation and competition, and in response to the urgent need to improve the performance of and upgrade China's economy, we must open wider to the outside world with unwavering resolve. By doing so, we can strengthen new drivers of development, add new forces to propel reform forward, and create new competitive strengths for China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进“一带一路”建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to secure solid progress in pursuing the Belt and Road Initiative. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹国内区域开发开放与国际经济合作，共同打造陆上经济走廊和海上合作支点，推动互联互通、经贸合作、人文交流。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote domestic regional development and opening up and international economic cooperation in a coordinated way, work with other countries and regions to build overland economic corridors and maritime cooperation hubs, and promote connectivity, economic and trade cooperation, and cultural exchange. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建沿线大通关合作机制，建设国际物流大通道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to develop cooperative mechanisms for achieving compatibility in customs clearance procedures along the routes and build international logistics networks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进边境经济合作区、跨境经济合作区、境外经贸合作区建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of border economic cooperation zones, cross-border economic cooperation zones, and overseas economic and trade cooperation zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持共商共建共享，使“一带一路”成为和平友谊纽带、共同繁荣之路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With a commitment to achieving common development and shared growth through joint consultation, we will ensure that the Belt and Road Initiative creates bonds of peace, friendship, and common prosperity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大国际产能合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to achieve greater industrial-capacity cooperation with other countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持企业为主、政府推动、市场化运作，实施一批重大示范项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will launch demonstration projects in accordance with the principle that enterprises should be the main actors, that government should provide support, and that operations should be market based. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实和完善财税金融支持政策，设立人民币海外合作基金，用好双边产能合作基金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and implement related supporting fiscal, tax, and financial policies, establish an RMB overseas cooperation fund and make good use of bilateral industrial-capacity cooperation funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动装备、技术、标准、服务走出去，打造中国制造金字品牌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote greater use of Chinese equipment, technology, standards, and services in the international market, and help Chinese manufacturing brands gain international recognition.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进外贸创新发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will develop innovative ways to promote foreign trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对外需持续低迷的严峻形势，要多措并举，遏制进出口下滑势头。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Faced with continuously weak foreign demand, we need to take a combination of measures to stop the decline in imports and exports. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一要加快落实和完善政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will move faster to improve and implement policies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化出口退税率结构，确保及时足额退税，严厉打击骗取退税。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the structure of export tax rebate rates, ensure rebates are paid promptly and in full, and crack down on fraudulent claims. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加短期出口信用保险规模，实现成套设备出口融资保险应保尽保。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase short-term export-credit insurance and provide export financing insurance for all insurable complete sets of equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二要鼓励商业模式创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will encourage innovative business models. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大跨境电子商务试点，支持企业建设一批出口产品“海外仓”，促进外贸综合服务企业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand trials in cross-border e-commerce, support enterprises in developing overseas warehouses for export products, and promote the development of enterprises that provide comprehensive foreign trade services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三要优化贸易结构。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will improve the trade mix. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展服务贸易创新发展试点，增加服务外包示范城市，加快发展文化对外贸易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will launch trials to create innovative ways of developing trade in services, see that more cities become trendsetters in providing foreign outsourced services, and accelerate the development of foreign trade in cultural goods and services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进一步整合优化海关特殊监管区域，促进加工贸易向中西部地区转移、向产业链中高端延伸。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will further integrate and improve special customs regulation zones, and encourage processing trade to move to the central and western regions and extend to the medium-high end of the industrial chain. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四要推进贸易便利化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will further facilitate trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推广国际贸易“单一窗口”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that the single window system is implemented for international trade nationwide. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>降低出口商品查验率。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reduce the frequency of inspections for exports. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五要实施更加积极的进口政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we will adopt a more proactive import policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大先进技术设备、关键零部件及紧缺能源原材料进口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase the import of advanced technology and equipment, key spare parts and components, and energy and raw materials in short supply in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高利用外资水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to make better use of overseas investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续放宽投资准入，扩大服务业和一般制造业开放，简化外商投资企业设立程序，加大招商引资力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to relax market access restrictions on investment, further open the service sector and the general manufacturing sector, simplify procedures for establishing companies with overseas investment, and step up efforts to attract more investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新内陆和沿边开放模式，打造新的外向型产业集群，引导外资更多投向中西部地区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create new models of opening up for inland and border areas, develop new overseas-oriented industrial clusters, and encourage more overseas investment in the central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大自贸试验区试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pilot free trade zones will be established in more parts of the country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新开发区体制机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the systems and mechanisms for governing development zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们将营造更加公平、更为透明、更可预期的投资环境，中国要始终成为富有吸引力的外商投资热土。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With these efforts, China's investment environment will become even more fair, transparent, and predictable, and China will be able to maintain strong appeal and serve as a favorite destination for overseas investment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快实施自由贸易区战略。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will accelerate implementation of the free trade zone strategy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极商签区域全面经济伙伴关系协定，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We wish to actively negotiate and sign the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership agreement. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快中日韩自贸区等谈判，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will help speed up negotiations on the establishment of the China-Japan-RoK free trade area. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进中美、中欧投资协定谈判，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to make progress in negotiations on investment agreements between China and the United States and between China and the European Union.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强亚太自贸区联合战略研究。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will help strengthen collective strategic research on the Free Trade Area of the Asia-Pacific. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们愿与各方一道，推进贸易投资自由化，共同构建均衡、共赢、包容的国际经贸体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China wishes to work with all interested parties to move ahead with trade and investment liberalization and establish an international economic and trade system that is balanced, inclusive, and beneficial for all.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（六）加大环境治理力度，推动绿色发展取得新突破。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>6. Step up environmental governance efforts and work to see breakthroughs in green development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>治理污染、保护环境，事关人民群众健康和可持续发展，必须强力推进，下决心走出一条经济发展与环境改善双赢之路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pollution control and environmental protection are important to both the health of our people and sustainable development, so we must work hard moving forward and resolve to take a path that leads to both economic development and environmental improvement.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重拳治理大气雾霾和水污染。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will take strong measures against air and water pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年化学需氧量、氨氮排放量要分别下降2%，二氧化硫、氮氧化物排放量分别下降3%，重点地区细颗粒物（PM2.5）浓度继续下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will ensure that chemical oxygen demand and ammonia nitrogen emissions are both reduced by 2%, sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions are cut by 3%, and the density of fine particulate matter (PM2.5) in key areas continues to fall. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力抓好减少燃煤排放和机动车排放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will focus on promoting the reduction of emissions from the burning of coal and motor vehicles. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强煤炭清洁高效利用，减少散煤使用，推进以电代煤、以气代煤。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to promote cleaner and more efficient use of coal, ensure there is less use of untreated coal, and do more to see coal substituted with electricity and natural gas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实施燃煤电厂超低排放和节能改造。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will upgrade coal-burning power plants nationwide to achieve ultra-low emissions and energy efficiency,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快淘汰不符合强制性标准的燃煤锅炉。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will move faster to shut down coal-fired boilers that do not meet compulsory standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加天然气供应，完善风能、太阳能、生物质能等发展扶持政策，提高清洁能源比重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase natural gas supply, improve policy support for the development of wind, solar, and biomass energy, and increase the proportion of clean energy in total energy consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励秸秆资源化综合利用，限制直接焚烧。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage a whole range of forms of straw utilization and restrict open burning. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推广车用燃油国五标准，淘汰黄标车和老旧车380万辆。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will push for the use of automobile gasoline and diesel fuel that meet National-V standards nationwide and see that 3.8 million old or high-emission vehicles are taken off the roads. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在重点区域实行大气污染联防联控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will coordinate efforts to prevent and control air pollution in regions where it presents a problem. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推进城镇污水处理设施建设与改造，加强农业面源污染和流域水环境综合治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will press ahead with the nationwide development and upgrading of urban sewage treatment facilities, and strengthen comprehensive efforts aimed at controlling agricultural pollution from non-point sources and at improving the water environment in river basin areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大工业污染源治理力度，对排污企业全面实行在线监测。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up efforts to deal with industrial pollution at the source and conduct online monitoring of all polluting enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化环境保护督察，做到奖惩分明。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen environmental inspection and reward and punish as appropriate. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新修订的环境保护法必须严格执行，对超排偷排者必须依法严厉打击，对姑息纵容者必须依法严肃追究。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must ensure that the newly revised Environmental Protection Law is strictly enforced, that those who emit pollutants beyond the limit allowed by their permit or without a permit are severely punished as stipulated by law, and that those who knowingly allow such violations are held to account in accordance with the law.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展节能环保产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will work to develop the energy conservation and environmental protection industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大绿色环保标准覆盖面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that environmental standards are applied in more areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善扶持政策，支持推广节能环保先进技术装备，广泛开展合同能源管理和环境污染第三方治理，加大建筑节能改造力度，加快传统制造业绿色改造。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve policy support to encourage the use of energy-saving and environmentally friendly advanced technologies and equipment, promote on a large scale contracted energy management and third-party treatment of environmental pollution, and work to see that energy-saving renovations in buildings are strengthened and efforts are accelerated to make traditional manufacturing more eco-friendly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展全民节能、节水行动，推进垃圾分类处理，健全再生资源回收利用网络，把节能环保产业培育成我国发展的一大支柱产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage everyone to conserve energy and water, make progress in using sorted treatment of waste, improve the networks for recycling renewable resources, and turn the energy conservation and environmental protection industries into pillar industries underpinning China's development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强生态安全屏障建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will continue to develop ecological security barriers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全生态保护补偿机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve mechanisms for compensating for ecological conservation efforts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>停止天然林商业性采伐，实行新一轮草原生态保护补助奖励政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Commercial logging in natural forests will be banned, and a new round of subsidy and award policies for grassland ecological conservation efforts will be implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进地下水超采区综合治理试点，实施湿地等生态保护与恢复工程，继续治理荒漠化、石漠化和水土流失。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Trials to comprehensively deal with the over-abstraction of groundwater will be moved ahead, more will be done to protect and restore wetlands and other ecosystems, and continued efforts will be made to curb desertification, rock desertification, and soil erosion. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保护环境，人人有责。每一个社会成员都要自觉行动起来，为建设美丽中国贡献力量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Every one of us has an obligation to protect the environment -- we call on every member of society to act and contribute to the building of a Beautiful China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（七）切实保障改善民生，加强社会建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>7. Strengthen social development to promote people's well being. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为政之道，民生为本。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The best form of governance is that which puts people's wellbeing first. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要念之再三、铭之肺腑，多谋民生之利，多解民生之忧。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must never lose sight of this and do more to improve the lives of our people and address their concerns. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政收入增长虽放缓，但该给群众办的实事一件也不能少。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Growth in government revenue is slowing, but when it comes to getting things done for the welfare of the people, we mustn't drop a single thing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力扩大就业创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will promote growth in employment and new businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施更加积极的就业政策，鼓励以创业带动就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will pursue a more proactive employment policy and encourage business startups that create employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年高校毕业生将高达765万人，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, there will be up to 7.65 million college graduates.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要落实好就业促进计划和创业引领计划，促进多渠道就业创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use multiple channels to increase employment and encourage entrepreneurship by implementing initiatives for promoting employment of college graduates and guiding them in starting up their own businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>用好失业保险基金结余，增加稳就业资金规模，做好企业下岗职工技能培训和再就业工作，对城镇就业困难人员提供托底帮扶。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make good use of the surplus from unemployment insurance funds and increase funds for keeping job creation stable to provide skills training for laid-off enterprise employees and help them find new employment and offer basic needs assistance to those in urban areas who face difficulties in securing employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完成2100万人次以上农民工职业技能提升培训任务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over 21 million training opportunities should be provided for migrant workers to improve their skills. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对灵活就业、新就业形态的扶持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen assistance for flexible employment and new forms of employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实做好退役军人安置和就业创业服务工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that demobilized military personnel are settled into new jobs or have good access to employment and business startup services.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展更高质量更加公平的教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will promote fairer access to quality education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育承载着国家的未来、人民的期盼。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Education is where a country's future and its people's hopes and aspirations lie. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>公共教育投入要加大向中西部和边远、贫困地区倾斜力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will allocate a greater share of funds for public education to the central and western regions and to remote and poor areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统一城乡义务教育经费保障机制，改善薄弱学校和寄宿制学校办学条件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will unify the urban and rural mechanisms for funding compulsory education and improve conditions in boarding schools and schools which are badly built or poorly operated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持普惠性幼儿园发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of kindergartens open to all children. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>办好特殊教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that special needs education is well provided. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快健全现代职业教育体系，分类推进中等职业教育免除学杂费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work faster to modernize the vocational education system and, type by type, begin waiving all tuition and miscellaneous fees at schools providing secondary vocational education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对贫困家庭学生率先免除普通高中学杂费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Students from families with financial difficulties will be the first to be exempted from tuition and miscellaneous fees at regular senior high schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实提高乡村教师待遇政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The salary and other benefits of teachers in rural areas will be increased. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进远程教育，扩大优质教育资源覆盖面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to promote distance learning and expand the reach of quality educational resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升高校教学水平和创新能力，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Institutions of higher learning should strengthen their teaching and their capacity for innovation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动具备条件的普通本科高校向应用型转变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Regular undergraduate institutions will be encouraged to shift their focus toward providing applied education if they are in a position to do so. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续扩大重点高校面向贫困地区农村招生规模，落实和完善农民工随迁子女在当地就学和升学考试政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to help see the increased enrollment of students from poor rural areas into key colleges, and improve and implement policies enabling children who live with their migrant worker parents to go to secondary school or take college entrance exams in their city of residence. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持和规范民办教育发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of privately run educational institutions and work to ensure they meet all relevant standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>教育要促进学生德智体美全面发展，注重培养各类高素质创新型人才。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Education should promote the moral, intellectual, physical, and artistic development of students, and particular attention should be given to fostering all kinds of high-caliber creative talent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从家庭到学校、从政府到社会，都要为孩子们的安全健康、成长成才担起责任，共同托起明天的希望。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Families, schools, governments, and our society as a whole must together shoulder the responsibility of ensuring our children, our hope for tomorrow, are safe, healthy, and can grow up with the opportunity to reach their full potential.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>协调推进医疗、医保、医药联动改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will advance the coordinated reform of medical services, medical insurance, and the medicine industry. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健康是幸福之基。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Health is at the root of happiness. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要实现大病保险全覆盖，政府加大投入，让更多大病患者减轻负担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we aim to realize full coverage of the serious disease insurance scheme, and government funding for the scheme will be increased to reduce the financial burdens of more people suffering from serious diseases. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政安排城乡医疗救助补助资金160亿元，增长9.6%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The central government will allocate 16 billion yuan to be used in both rural and urban areas for medical assistance and subsidies, an increase of 9.6% over last year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>整合城乡居民基本医保制度，财政补助由每人每年380元提高到420元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will merge the basic medical insurance systems for rural and non-working urban residents and raise government subsidies for the scheme from 380 to 420 yuan per capita per annum. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革医保支付方式，加快推进基本医保全国联网和异地就医结算。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform the ways for making medical insurance payouts and expedite the building of a nationwide network for basic medical insurance so that medical expenses can be settled where they are incurred via basic medical insurance accounts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大公立医院综合改革试点城市范围，协同推进医疗服务价格、药品流通等改革。深化药品医疗器械审评审批制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that more cities participate in piloting comprehensive public hospital reform; move forward in a coordinated way with medical service pricing reform and reform in medicine distribution; and deepen the reform of the evaluation and approval systems for medicines and medical equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快培养全科医生、儿科医生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to train general practitioners and pediatricians. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在70%左右的地市开展分级诊疗试点。基本公共卫生服务经费财政补助从人均40元提高到45元，促进医疗资源向基层和农村流动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out trials for tiered medical services in around 70% of prefecture-level cities, increase basic annual per capita government subsidies for public health services from 40 to 45 yuan, and see that more medical resources are channeled toward the community level in urban areas and toward rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励社会办医。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the development of privately run hospitals. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展中医药、民族医药事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of traditional Chinese medicine and the medical traditions of ethnic minorities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立健全符合医疗行业特点的人事薪酬制度，保护和调动医务人员积极性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish HR and remuneration systems suited to the medical sector to motivate medical practitioners and protect their enthusiasm. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>构建和谐医患关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure harmony in the relationship between doctor and patient. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善一对夫妇可生育两个孩子的配套政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the supporting policies to complement the decision to allow all couples to have two children.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为了人民健康，要加快健全统一权威的食品药品安全监管体制，严守从农田到餐桌、从企业到医院的每一道防线，让人民群众饮食用药安全放心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To see that the health of our people is protected, we will speed up the development of unified and authoritative safety monitoring systems for food and pharmaceuticals and reinforce every line of defense from the farm to the dining table, and from the enterprise to the hospital. This should ensure that people have access to safe food and medicine and can have confidence in what they are eating and taking.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>织密织牢社会保障安全网。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will build an extensive and tightly woven social safety net. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续提高退休人员基本养老金标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to raise basic pension benefits for retirees. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地要切实负起责任，确保养老金按时足额发放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local governments need to fulfill their duties to ensure that pension benefits are paid on time and in full. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定划转部分国有资本充实社保基金办法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work out methods for putting a portion of state capital into social security funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展养老服务业综合改革试点，推进多种形式的医养结合。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Initiatives will be launched to pilot comprehensive reform of the elderly care service industry, and progress should be made in developing a variety of forms of combined medical and care services for the elderly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实临时救助、特困人员救助供养等制度，合理确定救助供养标准，完善工作机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the temporary assistance scheme and the system for providing basic assistance to persons living in extreme poverty, appropriately determining how much to grant and improving how it is granted. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城乡低保人均补助标准分别提高5%和8%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Per capita subsidies for subsistence allowances in rural and urban areas will be increased by 8% and 5%, respectively. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快健全城乡社会救助体系，使困难群众遇急有助、遇困有帮，让社会充满关爱和温暖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up the development of social assistance systems so that people with urgent needs have access to assistance and support, helping society become a caring and warm one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进文化改革发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will promote the reform and development of the cultural sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>用中国梦和中国特色社会主义凝聚共识、汇聚力量，培育和践行社会主义核心价值观，加强爱国主义教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw on the Chinese Dream and socialism with Chinese characteristics to build consensus and pool strength, nurture and practice the core socialist values, and make greater efforts to foster patriotism. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施哲学社会科学创新工程，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out an initiative to encourage innovation in philosophy and the social sciences.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展文学艺术、新闻出版、广播影视、档案等事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the development of literature and art; the press and publishing; radio, television, and film; and archiving. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设中国特色新型智库。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New types of Chinese think tanks will be developed. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强文物和非物质文化遗产保护利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's cultural relics and intangible cultural heritage will be more effectively protected and put to better use. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化群众性精神文明创建活动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support popular activities which promote cultural and ethical progress. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>倡导全民阅读，普及科学知识，弘扬科学精神，提高国民素质和社会文明程度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to foster a love of reading in our people, popularize scientific knowledge, promote the spirit of science, improve the overall caliber of the population and raise the level of civility in society. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进传统媒体与新兴媒体融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the integrated development of traditional and new media. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>培育健康网络文化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the development of a healthy online culture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化中外人文交流，加强国际传播能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to deepen cultural exchanges with other countries and strengthen our capacity for international communication. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化文化体制改革，引导公共文化资源向城乡基层倾斜，推动文化产业创新发展，繁荣文化市场，加强文化市场管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen structural reform of the cultural sector, see that more public cultural resources are made available in rural and urban communities, promote the creative development of the cultural sector, see that markets for cultural products and services flourish, and strengthen regulation of such markets. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进数字广播电视户户通。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enable more households to enjoy digital broadcasting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好北京冬奥会和冬残奥会筹办工作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make thorough preparations for the 2022 Beijing Winter Olympic Games and Paralympic Games. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>倡导全民健身新时尚。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage new trends in popular fitness activities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强和创新社会治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will strengthen and develop new forms of social governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好基层基础工作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make sure foundational work and work at the community level is carried out to proper effect. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进城乡社区建设，促进基层民主协商。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote urban and rural community development and encourage democratic consultation at the community level. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持工会、共青团、妇联等群团组织参与社会治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the participation of people's organizations, such as trade unions, Communist youth league organizations, and women's federations, in social governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快行业协会商会与行政机关脱钩改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to untie industry associations and chambers of commerce from any connections they still have with the government.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法规范发展社会组织，支持专业社会工作、志愿服务和慈善事业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Social organizations will be developed and regulated in accordance with the law, and support will be given to the development of specialized social work, volunteer services, and charity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强社会信用体系建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up the development of the social credit system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实保障妇女、儿童、残疾人权益，加强对农村留守儿童和妇女、老人的关爱服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure the full protection of the rights and interests of women, children, and people with disabilities, and strengthen support and services provided to the children, women, and elderly who remain in rural areas while their family members work away in the cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化司法体制改革，开展法治宣传教育，启动实施“七五”普法规划，做好法律援助和社区矫正工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the judicial system, work to raise public awareness of the rule of law, begin to implement the seventh five-year plan for increasing public knowledge of the law, and see that a good job is done in terms of legal aid provision and community corrections. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善国家网络安全保障体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the national system for cybersecurity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新社会治安综合治理机制，以信息化为支撑推进社会治安防控体系建设，依法惩治违法犯罪行为，严厉打击暴力恐怖活动，增强人民群众的安全感。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New ways will be developed to improve the mechanisms for maintaining law and order, an IT-based system for crime prevention and control will be developed, unlawful and criminal activities will be punished in accordance with the law, and violent terrorist activities will be dealt with severely. All these steps will ensure people's security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改进信访工作，完善多元调解机制，有效化解矛盾纠纷，促进社会平安祥和。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve on work related to the handling of complaints made by letter or in person and refine the mechanisms for multimodal dispute mediation, so as to address disputes and ensure social peace and harmony.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>生命高于一切，安全重于泰山。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Nothing is more valuable than life, and ensuring public safety is of paramount importance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须坚持不懈抓好安全生产和公共安全，加强安全基础设施和防灾减灾能力建设，健全监测预警应急机制，提高气象服务水平，做好地震、测绘、地质等工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must continue our efforts to ensure workplace and public safety, improve safety infrastructure and build capacity to prevent and mitigate disasters, enhance monitoring, early-warning, and emergency response mechanisms, improve meteorological services, and deliver a good performance in seismology, surveying, mapping, and geology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善和落实安全生产责任、管理制度和考核机制，实行党政同责、一岗双责，加大失职追责力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and implement the system of accountability, management, and evaluation for workplace safety to ensure that both CPC committees and governments are held accountable and that officials take responsibility for workplace safety in performing their duties, and intensify efforts to see that those who fail to uphold safety standards are held accountable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格监管执法，坚决遏制重特大安全事故发生，切实保障人民生命财产安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will tighten oversight and law enforcement to guard against and prevent the occurrence of major workplace accidents and protect the lives and property of our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（八）加强政府自身建设，提高施政能力和服务水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>8. Improve government functions, strengthen our administrative capacity, and deliver quality government services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重任千钧惟担当。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The most formidable tasks demand the greatest sense of mission. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对异常艰巨复杂的改革发展任务，各级政府要深入贯彻落实新发展理念，把全面建成小康社会使命扛在肩上，把万家忧乐放在心头，建设人民满意的法治政府、创新政府、廉洁政府和服务型政府。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Faced with the onerous and complex tasks of reform and development, we in governments at all levels should follow the new vision on development in our work, bear the weight of finishing building a moderately prosperous society in all respects on our shoulders, keep the people's wellbeing at the forefront of our minds, and build a law-based, innovative, clean, and service-oriented government that the people are satisfied with.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持依法履职，把政府活动全面纳入法治轨道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will ensure that all government duties are performed in accordance with the law and that all government activities are carried out in line with the rule of law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府及其工作人员要带头严格遵守宪法和法律，自觉运用法治思维和法治方式推动工作，法定职责必须为，法无授权不可为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels and all their employees must take the lead in strictly abiding by the Constitution and other laws and conscientiously apply rule of law thinking and approaches in their work; they must carry out all statutory functions and duties and may not do anything not authorized by law.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极推行政府法律顾问制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will actively promote the legal consultation system for government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进政务公开，充分发挥传统媒体、新兴媒体作用，利用好网络平台，及时回应社会关切，使群众了解政府做什么、怎么做。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to make government operations more open by making use of both traditional and new media including the Internet to respond in a timely manner to social concerns and inform the public about what the government is doing and how. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要依法接受同级人大及其常委会的监督，自觉接受人民政协的民主监督，接受社会和舆论监督，让权力在阳光下运行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We in governments at all levels must, as required by law, subject ourselves to the oversight of the people's congresses at the same levels and their standing committees, and we should willingly subject ourselves to the democratic oversight of CPPCC committees, public oversight, and public opinion-based oversight, so as to exercise power in an open and transparent way.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持廉洁履职，深入推进反腐倡廉。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will ensure that government duties are performed with integrity and intensify efforts to fight corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真落实党风廉政建设主体责任，严厉整治各种顶风违纪行为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that leading Party and government officials at all levels assume full responsibility for improving Party conduct and government integrity, and we will severely punish all types of behavior that constitute flagrant violations of discipline. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强行政监察，推进审计全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Administrative supervision will be strengthened, and the whole government system will be placed under auditing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以减权限权、创新监管等举措减少寻租空间，铲除滋生腐败土壤。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Steps will be taken, such as reducing or limiting certain powers and adopting new forms of supervision, to eliminate room for rent-seeking and eradicate the breeding grounds of corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动党风廉政建设向基层延伸，坚决纠正侵害群众利益的不正之风，坚定不移惩治腐败。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that efforts to improve Party conduct and government integrity are extended right down to the community level, resolutely correct improper conduct that harms the interests of the general public, and punish corruption without fail.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持勤勉履职，提高执行力和公信力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- We will ensure that officials perform their duties diligently, that government decisions are fully implemented, and that the government's public credibility is improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作人员要恪尽职守、夙夜在公，主动作为、善谋勇为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government workers must take an active approach to their work, carry out effective planning and decisive implementation, fulfill all their duties, and work tirelessly in service of the public. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入践行“三严三实”，增强政治意识、大局意识、核心意识、看齐意识，加强作风和能力建设，打造高素质专业化的公务员队伍。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will practice the Three Stricts and Three Honests; become more aware of the need to uphold political integrity, keep in mind the bigger picture, follow the CPC as the core of the Chinese leadership, act consistently with CPC Central Committee policy; and improve conduct and competence in order to become a contingent of top-performing public servants with a good command of professional expertise. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全并严格执行工作责任制，确保各项政策和任务不折不扣落到实处。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and strictly enforce the work responsibility system and fully execute all policies and tasks without fail. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全督查问责机制，坚决整肃庸政懒政怠政行为，决不允许占着位子不干事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve oversight and accountability systems, root out incompetence, inertia, and negligence, and show zero tolerance for those who are on the government payroll but do not perform their duties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全激励机制和容错纠错机制，给改革创新者撑腰鼓劲，让广大干部愿干事、敢干事、能干成事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve incentive mechanisms and mechanisms to allow for and address mistakes, supporting and motivating those who are committed to carrying out reforms and making innovations. This will help ensure that our officials want to act, are not afraid to act, and are able to act and deliver. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国改革开放30多年的辉煌成就，就是广大干部群众干出来的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The remarkable achievements made in China's reform and opening up over the past 30 plus years are a result of the actions of our people and our officials.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>上下同欲者胜。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Success belongs to those who share, from top to bottom, in one purpose. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要充分发挥中央和地方两个积极性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep both the central and local governments fully motivated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对真抓实干成效明显的地方，在建设资金安排、新增建设用地、财政沉淀资金统筹使用等方面，加大奖励支持力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Localities which work diligently and make notable achievements will receive greater incentives and support in terms of development funds, land designations for new construction projects, and idle budgetary funds made available to them. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励各地从实际出发干事创业，形成竞相发展的生动局面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage all localities to conduct their work in light of their particular circumstances and create a motivational sense of competition in pursuit of development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！中华民族是一个大家庭，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There are several other areas I wish to address. First, all the people of China are of one family.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进各民族和睦相处、和衷共济、和谐发展，是各族人民的根本利益和共同责任。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Helping the people of all our ethnic groups to live together, share in a common cause, and develop in harmony is in the fundamental interests of us all, and is our joint responsibility. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持中国特色解决民族问题的正确道路，坚持和完善民族区域自治制度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will stick to the Chinese way-the right way-of managing ethnic issues, and uphold and improve the system of regional ethnic autonomy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格执行党的民族政策，深入开展民族团结进步创建活动，推动建立各民族相互嵌入式的社会结构和社区环境，促进各民族交往交流交融。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will follow closely the Party's policies concerning ethnic groups, launch extensive activities to promote ethnic unity and progress, facilitate the development of a social structure and a community environment in which different ethnic groups are integrated, and promote interaction, communication, and integration between ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实促进民族地区发展的差别化支持政策，加强对口帮扶，保护和发展少数民族优秀传统文化及特色村镇，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement differentiated policies in support of the development of areas with concentrations of ethnic minorities, offer assistance through pairing programs, and protect and develop the fine traditional cultures of ethnic minorities and towns and villages rich in ethnic heritage.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大扶持人口较少民族发展力度，大力实施兴边富民行动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up support for the development of ethnic groups with smaller populations and boost efforts to promote the development of the border regions to improve the lives of the people there. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>让全国各族人民共同迈向全面小康社会。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In short, we will ensure that all the people of China work together for a moderately prosperous society in all respects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要全面贯彻党的宗教工作基本方针，坚持依法管理宗教事务，促进宗教关系和谐，发挥宗教界人士和信教群众在促进经济社会发展中的积极作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the Party's basic policy on religion, regulate religious affairs in accordance with the law, promote harmonious relations between religions, and see that religious leaders and believers are actively involved in promoting economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要认真落实侨务政策，依法维护海外侨胞和归侨侨眷的合法权益，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement our policies on work related to overseas Chinese, and work in accordance with the law to safeguard the lawful rights and interests of overseas Chinese nationals, Chinese nationals who have returned to China from overseas, and the relatives of overseas Chinese nationals who live in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分发挥他们的独特优势和重要作用，不断增强海内外中华儿女的向心力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give full expression to their unique strengths and important roles, rally their support, and strengthen the bonds of attachment and affection of all Chinese, whether at home or overseas, to our motherland.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！过去一年，国防和军队建设取得显著成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, last year saw significant progress in strengthening national defense and the armed forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，要紧紧围绕实现党在新形势下的强军目标，深入推进政治建军、改革强军、依法治军，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, in keeping with the Party's goal of building strong armed forces under new conditions, we will boost efforts to build the armed forces through political work and reform, and run them by law.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面加强军队革命化现代化正规化建设，坚决维护国家安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to make the military more revolutionary, modern, and well-structured in every respect, and remain committed to safeguarding national security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持党对军队绝对领导的根本原则和制度，落实古田全军政治工作会议精神。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold the fundamental principle and institution of the Party having absolute leadership over the armed forces, and put into practice the guiding principles adopted at the military's meeting on political work held in Gutian, Fujian. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹推进各方向各领域军事斗争准备，严密组织日常战备和边海空防管控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen in a coordinated way military preparedness on all fronts and for all scenarios, and work meticulously to ensure combat readiness and border, coastal, and air defense control. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强后勤保障和装备发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up the development of logistics and equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推进领导指挥体制改革，部署展开军队规模结构和政策制度等改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make steady progress in reforming military leadership and command structures, and launch reform of the military's size and structure as well as its policies and institutions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高军队建设法治化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure law-based development of the armed forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设现代化武装警察部队。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will modernize the armed police force. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强全民国防教育和国防动员建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Public awareness about the importance of national defense and national defense mobilization will be strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动重要领域军民融合深度发展，在重要基础设施建设中充分考虑国防需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Closer military-civilian integration will be promoted in important fields, and full consideration will be given to defense needs in the development of important infrastructure. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展国防科技工业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop defense-related science, technology, and industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要大力支持国防和军队建设，走出一条新时期鱼水情深的军政军民团结之路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels should give full support to strengthening national defense and the armed forces, and we should strive to forge an ever closer bond between the military and the government and between the military and the people in this new era.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！我们将全面准确贯彻“一国两制”、“港人治港”、“澳人治澳”、高度自治的方针，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will implement, both to the letter and in spirit, the principles of "one country, two systems," the people of Hong Kong governing Hong Kong, the people of Macao governing Macao, and both regions enjoying a high degree of autonomy,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格依照宪法和基本法办事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will act in strict compliance with China's Constitution and the basic laws of the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全力支持香港、澳门特别行政区行政长官和政府依法施政。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We pledge our full support to the chief executives and governments of the two regions as they conduct governance in accordance with their respective laws. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥港澳独特优势，提升港澳在国家经济发展和对外开放中的地位和功能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give expression to the distinctive strengths of Hong Kong and Macao, and elevate their positions and roles in China's economic development and opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化内地与港澳合作，促进港澳提升自身竞争力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to deepen cooperation between the mainland and these two regions and help Hong Kong and Macao strengthen their competitiveness. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们相信，香港、澳门一定会保持长期繁荣稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We are convinced that Hong Kong and Macao will maintain long-term prosperity and stability.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要继续坚持对台工作大政方针，坚持“九二共识”政治基础，坚决反对“台独”分裂活动，维护国家主权和领土完整，维护两岸关系和平发展和台海和平稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will remain committed to our major policies on Taiwan, uphold the 1992 Consensus as the political foundation, resolutely oppose separatist activities for the independence of Taiwan, safeguard China's sovereignty and territorial integrity, maintain the peaceful growth of cross-Straits relations, and safeguard peace and stability in the Taiwan Straits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进两岸经济融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strive to make progress in cross-Straits economic integration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进两岸文教、科技等领域交流，加强两岸基层和青年交流。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage cultural, educational, scientific, and technological exchanges and help strengthen exchanges between ordinary people and the younger generation between both sides of the Straits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们将秉持“两岸一家亲”理念，同台湾同胞共担民族大义，共享发展机遇，携手构建两岸命运共同体。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Guided by the conviction that people on both sides of the Straits belong to one and the same family, we will share with our fellow countrymen and women in Taiwan both the responsibility of the Chinese nation and opportunities for development and jointly build a cross-Straits community of common destiny.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！我们将继续高举和平、发展、合作、共赢的旗帜，践行中国特色大国外交理念，维护国家主权、安全、发展利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Finally, we will continue to hold aloft the banner of peace, development, cooperation, and mutual benefit, practice the distinctive vision guiding China in conducting its diplomacy as a major country, and safeguard its sovereignty, security, and developmental interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>办好在我国举行的二十国集团领导人峰会，推动世界经济创新增长，完善全球经济金融治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will host the G20 leaders' summit to promote innovative growth in the global economy and improve global economic and financial governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强与各主要大国协调合作，建设良性互动、合作共赢的大国关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up coordination and cooperation with all other major countries and develop with them relations characterized by positive interaction and win-win cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>秉持亲诚惠容的周边外交理念，与地区国家持久和平相处、联动融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Guided by the policy of amity, sincerity, mutual benefit, and inclusiveness in developing relations with our neighbors, we will work with other countries in our region to maintain lasting peaceful relations and coordinated and integrated development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化南南合作、促进共同发展，维护发展中国家正当合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will help deepen South-South cooperation, promote common development, and safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of developing countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设性参与解决全球性和热点问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will participate constructively in solving global and sensitive issues. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快海外利益保护能力建设，切实保护我国公民和法人安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to strengthen our capacity for safeguarding China's overseas interests and protect the safety of Chinese nationals and legal persons. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国愿与国际社会一道，为人类和平与发展事业不懈努力！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China will work tirelessly with the rest of the international community to promote the peace and development of all of humanity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>奋斗才能赢得未来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our future can be secured only through hard work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>让我们更加紧密地团结在以习近平同志为总书记的党中央周围，凝心聚力，奋发进取，努力完成今年经济社会发展目标任务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let us rally closer around the CPC Central Committee headed by General Secretary Xi Jinping and, working together and remaining of one mind, strive to fulfill this year's economic and social development tasks and targets.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>确保全面建成小康社会决胜阶段良好开局，为建成富强民主文明和谐的社会主义现代化国家、实现中华民族伟大复兴的中国梦作出新的贡献！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let us thus make a good start to the decisive stage of finishing building a moderately prosperous society in all respects, and make new contributions to turning China into a modern socialist country that is prosperous, strong, democratic, culturally advanced, and harmonious and to achieving the Chinese Dream of the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>