<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<tmx version="1.4">
<header creationtool="ABBYY Aligner" creationtoolversion="1.0" segtype="sentence" o-tmf="ATM" adminlang="en-US" srclang="en-US" datatype="plaintext">
</header>
<body>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作报告</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>REPORT ON THE WORK OF THE GOVERNMENT</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——2017年3月5日在第十二届全国人民代表大会第五次会议上</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Delivered at the Fifth Session of the 12th National People's Congress of the People's Republic of China on March 5, 2017</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院总理　李克强</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Li Keqiang Premier of the State Council</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>现在，我代表国务院，向大会报告政府工作，请予审议，并请全国政协各位委员提出意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I will now report to you on the work of the government and ask for your deliberation and approval. I also wish to have comments on my report from the members of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC).</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一、2016年工作回顾</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let me begin with a review of our work in 2016.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，我国发展面临国内外诸多矛盾叠加、风险隐患交汇的严峻挑战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the past year, China's development has faced grave challenges posed by a great many problems and interwoven risks and dangers both at home and abroad. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在以习近平同志为核心的党中央坚强领导下，全国各族人民迎难而上，砥砺前行，推动经济社会持续健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>However, under the strong leadership of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, we the Chinese people have risen to the challenge and worked hard to press ahead, driving forward sustained, healthy economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>党的十八届六中全会正式明确习近平总书记的核心地位，体现了党和人民的根本利益，对保证党和国家兴旺发达、长治久安，具有十分重大而深远的意义。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At the Sixth Plenary Session of the 18th Party Central Committee, the core position of General Secretary Xi Jinping was formally affirmed, which reflects the fundamental interests of the Party and the Chinese people, and is of crucial and far-reaching significance for ensuring the flourishing and long-term stability of the Party and the country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地区、各部门不断增强政治意识、大局意识、核心意识、看齐意识，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All regions and all government departments have steadily strengthened their consciousness of the need to maintain political integrity, think in big-picture terms, uphold the leadership core, and keep in alignment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动全面建成小康社会取得新的重要进展，全面深化改革迈出重大步伐，全面依法治国深入实施，全面从严治党纵深推进，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Pushing ahead with all-around efforts, we have achieved major progress in finishing building a moderately prosperous society in all respects, made important strides in deepening reform, continued to exercise law-based governance, and made further progress in practicing strict Party self-governance;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年经济社会发展主要目标任务圆满完成，“十三五”实现了良好开局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we have accomplished the year's main tasks and targets for economic and social development, and got the 13th Five-Year Plan off to a great start.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——经济运行缓中趋稳、稳中向好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The economy has registered a slower but stable performance with good momentum for growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值达到74.4万亿元，增长6.7%，名列世界前茅，对全球经济增长的贡献率超过30%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>GDP reached 74.4 trillion yuan, representing 6.7-percent growth, and seeing China outpace most other economies. China contributed more than 30 percent of global growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民消费价格上涨2%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The CPI rose by 2 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>工业企业利润由上年下降2.3%转为增长8.5%，单位国内生产总值能耗下降5%，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With an 8.5-percent increase in profits, industrial enterprises reversed the previous year's negative growth of 2.3 percent. Energy consumption per unit of GDP fell by 5 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济发展的质量和效益明显提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Economic performance improved markedly in quality and returns.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——就业增长超出预期。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Employment growth exceeded projections. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年城镇新增就业1314万人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 13.14 million new urban jobs were added over the course of the year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高校毕业生就业创业人数再创新高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of college graduates finding employment or starting businesses reached another record high. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>年末城镇登记失业率4.02%，为多年来最低。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The registered urban unemployment rate stood at 4.02 percent at year-end 2016, the lowest level in years. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>13亿多人口的发展中大国，就业比较充分，十分不易。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For China, a large developing country with a population of over 1.3 billion, attaining this level of employment is no easy task.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——改革开放深入推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Continued advances were made in reform and opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重要领域和关键环节改革取得突破性进展，供给侧结构性改革初见成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Breakthroughs were made in reforms in major sectors and key links, and initial success was achieved in supply-side structural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对外开放推出新举措，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New measures were introduced for opening China up,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“一带一路”建设进展快速，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>rapid progress was made in pursuing the Belt and Road Initiative,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一批重大工程和国际产能合作项目落地。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and a number of major projects and industrial-capacity cooperation projects with other countries were launched.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——经济结构加快调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Economic structural adjustment was stepped up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>消费在经济增长中发挥主要拉动作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Consumption was the main driver of economic growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>服务业增加值占国内生产总值比重上升到51.6%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The value created by the service sector rose to 51.6 percent of GDP. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高技术产业、装备制造业较快增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>High-tech industries and equipment manufacturing grew rapidly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农业稳中调优，粮食再获丰收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In agriculture, production was stable and structural adjustments were made, and we had continued good grain harvests.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——发展新动能不断增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New drivers of growth gained strength. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新驱动发展战略深入实施。科技领域取得一批国际领先的重大成果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Further progress was made in pursuing the innovation-driven development strategy, and a number of world-leading achievements were made in science and technology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新兴产业蓬勃兴起，传统产业加快转型升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Emerging industries were thriving, and the transformation and upgrading of traditional industries accelerated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大众创业、万众创新广泛开展，全年新登记企业增长24.5%，平均每天新增1.5万户，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>People were busy launching businesses or making innovations, with a 24.5-percent year-on-year increase in the number of new businesses registered-an average of 15,000 new businesses daily.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加上个体工商户等，各类市场主体每天新增4.5万户。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With self-employed traders and other market entities included we had an average of 45,000 new market entities launched per day. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新动能正在撑起发展新天地。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>New growth drivers are opening new prospects for China's development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——基础设施支撑能力持续提升。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Infrastructure became ever-better able to sustain development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新建高速铁路投产里程超过1900公里，新建改建高速公路6700多公里、农村公路29万公里。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over 1,900 kilometers of new high-speed rail lines came into service, and more than 6,700 kilometers of expressways and 290,000 kilometers of rural roads were built or upgraded. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城市轨道交通、地下综合管廊建设加快。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Construction picked up pace on urban rail transit facilities and underground utility tunnels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新开工重大水利工程21项。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Construction began on 21 major water conservancy projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新增第四代移动通信用户3.4亿、光缆线路550多万公里。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of 4G mobile communications subscribers grew by 340 million and over 5.5 million kilometers of optical fiber cables were added.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>——人民生活继续改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Living standards were improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全国居民人均可支配收入实际增长6.3%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Personal per capita disposable income increased by 6.3 percent in real terms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>农村贫困人口减少1240万，易地扶贫搬迁人口超过240万。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of people living in poverty in rural areas was reduced by 12.4 million, including more than 2.4 million people relocated from inhospitable areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>棚户区住房改造600多万套，农村危房改造380多万户。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More than 6 million homes in rundown urban areas and over 3.8 million dilapidated rural houses were renovated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内旅游快速增长，出境旅游超过1.2亿人次，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In tourism, domestic trips showed rapid growth, and overseas trips exceeded 120 million.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城乡居民生活水平有新的提高。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>People in both urban and rural areas saw arise in living standards.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国成功主办二十国集团领导人杭州峰会，推动取得一系列开创性、引领性、机制性重要成果，在全球经济治理中留下深刻的中国印记。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China successfully hosted the G20 2016 Hangzhou Summit, and helped to deliver a number of important pioneering, leading, and institutional outcomes, thus doing its part for global economic governance.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>回顾过去一年，走过的路很不寻常。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2016 was an unusual year in our country's development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们面对的是世界经济和贸易增速7年来最低、国际金融市场波动加剧、地区和全球性挑战突发多发的外部环境，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China was confronted with an external environment in which the world saw the lowest economic and trade growth in seven years, growing volatility in global financial markets, and sudden and frequent regional and global challenges. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对的是国内结构性问题突出、风险隐患显现、经济下行压力加大的多重困难，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Domestically, China faced multiple difficulties: major structural problems, prominent risks and dangers, and mounting downward pressure on the economy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对的是改革进入攻坚期、利益关系深刻调整、影响社会稳定因素增多的复杂局面。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China found itself in a complex environment as reform entered a critical stage, profound changes took place affecting interests, and factors impacting social stability grew. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在这种情况下，经济能够稳住很不容易，出现诸多向好变化更为难得。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Given all these factors, it was not easy for us to maintain stable economic performance. And yet we succeeded, and even managed to make progress on many fronts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这再次表明，中国人民有勇气、有智慧、有能力战胜任何艰难险阻，中国经济有潜力、有韧性、有优势，中国的发展前景一定会更好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Once again, this shows that we the Chinese people have the courage, ingenuity, and ability to overcome any difficulty or hardship. It also shows that the Chinese economy possesses potential, resilience, and strengths, so we can be sure there is even better development ahead for China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一年来，我们主要做了以下工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I will now move on to discuss our main work last year:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是继续创新和加强宏观调控，经济运行保持在合理区间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we continued to develop new and more effective ways of carrying out regulation at the macro level, thus keeping the economy performing within an appropriate range.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年宏观调控面临多难抉择，我们坚持不搞“大水漫灌”式强刺激，而是依靠改革创新来稳增长、调结构、防风险，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year, we faced difficult choices in conducting macro-level regulation, but we stood firm in not adopting strong stimulus policies that would have had an economy-wide impact, and strived instead to maintain steady growth, adjust the structure, and guard against risks through reform and innovation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在区间调控基础上，加强定向调控、相机调控。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened targeted and well-timed regulation on the basis of range-based regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极的财政政策力度加大，增加的财政赤字主要用于减税降费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More proactive fiscal policy was pursued, and the increase in the fiscal deficit was used mainly to cover tax and fee cuts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推开营改增试点，全年降低企业税负5700多亿元，所有行业实现税负只减不增。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The trial replacement of business tax with value added tax (VAT) was extended to cover all sectors, slashing the tax burden of businesses for the year by over 570 billion yuan and reducing tax burdens in every sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施中央与地方增值税收入划分过渡方案，确保地方既有财力不变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A transitional plan for sharing VAT revenue between the central and local governments was formulated and implemented to ensure financial resources of local governments remained unchanged. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大地方政府存量债务置换规模，降低利息负担约4000亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More local government bonds were issued to replace outstanding debts, reducing interest payments by roughly 400 billion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳健的货币政策灵活适度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A prudent monetary policy was pursued in a flexible and appropriate manner. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广义货币M2增长11.3%，低于13%左右的预期目标。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The M2 money supply increased by 11.3 percent, below our projected target of around 13 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>综合运用多种货币政策工具，支持实体经济发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We used a range of monetary policy tools to support the development of the real economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施促进消费升级措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Measures were taken to upgrade consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>出台鼓励民间投资等政策，投资出现企稳态势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We unveiled policies to encourage private investment, and saw investment begin to stabilize. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>分类调控房地产市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We exercised category-based regulation over the real estate market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强金融风险防控，人民币汇率形成机制进一步完善，保持了在合理均衡水平上的基本稳定，维护了国家经济金融安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened efforts to manage financial risks. The RMB exchange rate regime continued to improve, and the exchange rate remained generally stable at an adaptive and equilibrium level. With these measures, we have safeguarded China's economic and financial security.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是着力抓好“三去一降一补”，供给结构有所改善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we focused on five priority tasks -- cutting overcapacity, reducing excess inventory, deleveraging, lowering costs, and strengthening areas of weakness -- thereby improving the composition of supply.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以钢铁、煤炭行业为重点去产能，全年退出钢铁产能超过6500万吨、煤炭产能超过2.9亿吨，超额完成年度目标任务，分流职工得到较好安置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Particular priority was given to cutting overcapacity in the steel and coal sectors. Over the year, steel production capacity was cut by more than 65 million metric tons and coal by over 290 million metric tons, going beyond annual targets. Effective assistance was provided to laid-off employees. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持农民工在城镇购房，提高棚改货币化安置比例，房地产去库存取得积极成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We supported migrant workers in buying urban homes; and we increased the proportion of people affected by rebuilding in rundown urban areas receiving monetary compensation, making good progress in reducing real estate inventory. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动企业兼并重组，发展直接融资，实施市场化法治化债转股，工业企业资产负债率有所下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Business acquisitions and reorganizations were encouraged, direct financing was promoted, and market- and law-based debt-to-equity swaps were carried out, lowering the debt-to-asset ratio of industrial enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着眼促进企业降成本，出台减税降费、降低“五险一金”缴费比例、下调用电价格等举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To help enterprises lower operating costs, we introduced measures to cut taxes and fees, lower the share paid by enterprises for social security contributions (Notes: This includes old-age insurance, health insurance, unemployment insurance, workers' compensation, maternity insurance, and housing provident fund schemes) and cut the price of electricity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大补短板力度，办了一批当前急需又利长远的大事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We boosted efforts to strengthen areas of weakness and undertook major initiatives that both help to meet urgent needs today and promise long-term benefits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是大力深化改革开放，发展活力进一步增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we worked hard to deepen reform and opening up, further strengthening the vitality of development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面深化改革，推出一批标志性、支柱性改革举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Reform was deepened across the board, and a good number of landmark and pillar reform initiatives were undertaken. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>围绕处理好政府和市场关系这一经济体制改革的核心问题，持续推进简政放权、放管结合、优化服务改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To balance the government-market relationship -- the pivotal issue in economic structural reform -- we continued reforms to streamline administration, delegate powers, and improve regulation and services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在提前完成本届政府减少行政审批事项三分之一目标的基础上，去年又取消165项国务院部门及其指定地方实施的审批事项，清理规范192项审批中介服务事项、220项职业资格许可认定事项。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>My administration's goal of cutting the number of items requiring government review by a third had been achieved ahead of schedule. On that basis, last year we cancelled the requirement on a further 165 items for review by State Council departments and authorized local governments. We also overhauled and standardized 192 items of intermediary services for government review as well as 220 items of approvals and accreditations for professional qualifications. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化商事制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We deepened institutional reforms in the business sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推行“双随机、一公开”，增强事中事后监管的有效性，推进“互联网+政务服务”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We introduced an oversight model of random inspection and public release across the board (Note: The model comprises inspections of randomly selected entities by randomly selected inspectors and the public release of inspection results., and cut the price of electricity), made operational and post-operational oversight more effective, and promoted the Internet Plus government services model. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动国有企业调整重组和混合所有制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We pushed ahead with reforms to restructure and reorganize state-owned enterprises (SOEs) and introduce into them mixed ownership structures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立公平竞争审查制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We established a review system to ensure fair competition. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化资源税改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We deepened resource tax reforms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善农村土地“三权分置”办法，建立贫困退出机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved measures for separating rural land ownership rights, contract rights, and management rights, and established a mechanism for determining whether people have been lifted out of poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进科技管理体制改革，扩大高校和科研院所自主权，出台以增加知识价值为导向的分配政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made progress in reforming the science and technology management system, gave greater autonomy to colleges and research institutes, and adopted profit distribution policies oriented toward increasing the value of knowledge. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>放开养老服务市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We opened up the elderly services market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大公立医院综合改革试点，深化药品医疗器械审评审批制度改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We expanded the trials of comprehensive reforms in public hospitals and deepened reform of the evaluation and approval systems for medicine and medical equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定自然资源统一确权登记办法，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We formulated unified measures to determine and register natural resource rights.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展省以下环保机构监测监察执法垂直管理、耕地轮作休耕改革等试点，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We piloted reforms for conducting direct oversight by provincial-level environmental protection agencies over the environmental monitoring and inspection work of environmental protection agencies below the provincial level, as well as crop rotation and fallow land reforms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推行河长制，健全生态保护补偿机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The river chief system was introduced for all lakes and rivers across the country, and the mechanisms for compensating for ecological conservation efforts were improved. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革为经济社会发展增添了新动力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Reform has given new impetus to economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极扩大对外开放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We opened China wider to the rest of the world. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进“一带一路”建设，与沿线国家加强战略对接、务实合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As we pushed ahead with the Belt and Road Initiative, we worked to increase complementarity between the development strategies of, and practical cooperation between, China and other countries along the routes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民币正式纳入国际货币基金组织特别提款权货币篮子。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The RMB was formally included in the IMF's Special Drawing Rights basket. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“深港通”开启。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Shenzhen-Hong Kong Stock Connect was launched. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善促进外贸发展措施，新设12个跨境电子商务综合试验区，进出口逐步回稳。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved measures for promoting trade, and built 12 new integrated experimental zones for cross-border e-commerce, bringing about a steady recovery in the volume of import and export. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推广上海等自贸试验区改革创新成果，新设7个自贸试验区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The new practices of pilot free trade zones in Shanghai and elsewhere were used to establish another seven pilot zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>除少数实行准入特别管理措施领域外，外资企业设立及变更一律由审批改为备案管理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The requirement for review and approval for setting up and making significant adjustments to foreign enterprises was replaced by a simple filing process, with the exception of a few areas where special market access requirements apply. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实际使用外资1300多亿美元，继续位居发展中国家首位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In 2016, China utilized more than US$130 billion of overseas investment, continuing to rank first among developing countries.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是强化创新引领，新动能快速成长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we strengthened innovation's leading role, spurring the rapid development of new growth drivers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进“互联网+”行动和国家大数据战略，全面实施《中国制造2025》，落实和完善“双创”政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took further steps to implement the Internet Plus action plan and the national big data strategy, fully implemented the Made in China 2025 initiative, and implemented and improved policies and measures to encourage people to launch businesses and innovate. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>部署启动面向2030年的科技创新重大项目，支持北京、上海建设具有全球影响力的科技创新中心，新设6个国家自主创新示范区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We developed and launched a plan for completing major science and technology programs by 2030, supported Beijing and Shanghai in building themselves into global R&amp;D centers, and established another six national innovation demonstration zones. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全社会研发经费支出与国内生产总值之比达到2.08%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's R&amp;D spending reached 2.08 percent of GDP. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内有效发明专利拥有量突破100万件，技术交易额超过1万亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of in-force Chinese patents issued in China passed the million mark, and the value of technology transactions exceeded one trillion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>科技进步贡献率上升到56.2%，创新对发展的支撑作用明显增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The contribution of scientific and technological progress to economic growth rose to 56.2 percent, and innovation's role in powering development grew markedly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是促进区域城乡协调发展，新的增长极增长带加快形成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we promoted more balanced development between regions and between rural and urban areas, and saw faster emergence of new growth poles and growth belts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施“一带一路”建设、京津冀协同发展、长江经济带发展三大战略，启动建设一批重点项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We stepped up work to implement the three strategic initiatives (the Belt and Road, Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei integration, and the Yangtze Economic Belt), and began construction on a number of key projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>编制西部大开发“十三五”规划，实施新一轮东北振兴战略，推动中部地区崛起，支持东部地区率先发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We formulated the plan for the 13th Five-Year Plan period for large-scale development in the western region, launched a new round of initiatives as part of the Northeast revitalization strategy, drove progress in the rise of the central region, and supported the eastern region in leading the rest of the country in pursuing development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进新型城镇化，深化户籍制度改革，全面推行居住证制度，又有1600万人进城落户。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We sped up efforts to promote new types of urbanization, deepened reform of the household registration system, introduced the residence card system nationwide, and granted urban residency to another 16 million people from rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展的协同叠加效应不断显现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The synergy building through coordinated development became more and more evident.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>六是加强生态文明建设，绿色发展取得新进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Sixth, we strengthened ecological conservation and made fresh progress in pursuing green development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施生态文明建设目标评价考核办法，建设国家生态文明试验区。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We formulated and introduced measures for assessing progress made in ecological improvement, and established national pilot zones for ecological conservation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化大气污染治理，二氧化硫、氮氧化物排放量分别下降5.6%和4%，74个重点城市细颗粒物（PM2.5）年均浓度下降9.1%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took stronger measures against air pollution and, as a result, saw a 5.6-percent decline in sulfur dioxide emissions, a 4-percent cut in nitrogen oxide emissions, and a 9.1-percent drop in the annual average density of fine particulate matter (PM2.5) in 74 key cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化能源结构，清洁能源消费比重提高1.7个百分点，煤炭消费比重下降2个百分点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued to improve the energy mix, increasing the share of clean energy consumption by 1.7 percentage points and cutting the share of coal consumption by 2 percentage points. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进水污染防治，出台土壤污染防治行动计划。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We continued efforts to prevent and control water pollution, and adopted an action plan for preventing and controlling soil pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展中央环境保护督察，严肃查处一批环境违法案件，推动了环保工作深入开展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government inspections on environmental protection accountability were launched and violations of environmental protection laws were investigated and prosecuted, giving impetus to deeper efforts to protect the environment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>七是注重保障和改善民生，人民群众获得感增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Seventh, we gave particular attention to ensuring and improving living standards, helping Chinese people gain a stronger sense of benefit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在财政收支压力加大情况下，民生投入继续增加。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Despite growing pressure from fiscal imbalance, we continued to increase inputs in areas related to living standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>出台新的就业创业政策，扎实做好重点人群、重点地区就业工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We launched new policies on employment and business startups, and carried out solid work on increasing employment for key target groups and priority regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推进脱贫攻坚，全国财政专项扶贫资金投入超过1000亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made all-around progress in key battles to eradicate poverty and earmarked over 100 billion yuan from government budgets for poverty relief. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高低保、优抚、退休人员基本养老金等标准，为1700多万困难和重度残疾人发放生活或护理补贴。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased subsistence allowances, benefits for entitled groups, basic pension payments, and other subsidies; and over 17 million people benefited through the provision of cost-of-living allowances for people with disabilities in financial difficulty and nursing care subsidies for people with severe disabilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政性教育经费支出占国内生产总值比例继续超过4%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal spending on education continued to be over 4 percent of GDP. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>重点高校招收贫困地区农村学生人数增长21.3%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The number of students from poor rural areas enrolled in key universities grew by 21.3 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>免除农村贫困家庭学生普通高中学杂费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We waived tuition and miscellaneous fees for students from poor rural families at regular senior high schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全年资助各类学校家庭困难学生8400多万人次。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Over the course of the year, more than 84 million grants were given to students from poor families studying in all types of schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>整合城乡居民基本医保制度，提高财政补助标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The basic health insurance systems for rural and nonworking urban residents were merged and government subsidies for the system were increased. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加基本公共卫生服务经费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More funding was provided for basic public health services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实现大病保险全覆盖，符合规定的省内异地就医住院费用可直接结算。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Full coverage of the serious disease insurance scheme was achieved, and healthcare costs meeting relevant provisions can now be settled on the spot when incurred anywhere within the provincial-level administrative area where insurance is registered. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强基层公共文化服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We increased public cultural services at the community level. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施全民健身计划，体育健儿在里约奥运会、残奥会上再创佳绩。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Fitness for All initiative was launched, and Chinese athletes gave an excellent performance at the Olympic Games and Paralympic Games in Rio de Janeiro. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去年部分地区特别是长江流域发生严重洪涝等灾害，通过及时有力开展抢险救灾，紧急转移安置900多万人次，最大限度降低了灾害损失，恢复重建有序进行。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year, parts of the country, especially the Yangtze basin, were hit by severe flooding and other disasters. We acted quickly to provide effective rescue and relief, swiftly relocated over 9 million people, minimized damage and loss, and made systematic progress with recovery and reconstruction efforts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>八是推进政府建设和治理创新，社会保持和谐稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Eighth, we continued to enhance government performance and improve governance, thus ensuring social harmony and stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国务院提请全国人大常委会审议法律议案13件，制定修订行政法规8件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The State Council submitted 13 legislative proposals to the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress (NPC) for approval and adopted or revised 8 sets of administrative regulations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善公共决策吸纳民意机制，认真办理人大代表建议和政协委员提案。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We improved mechanisms for drawing on public opinions in decision making on public issues and worked with keen attention to handle the proposals and suggestions of NPC deputies and CPPCC National Committee members. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进政务公开，省级政府部门权力和责任清单全面公布。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We made progress in strengthening government transparency by releasing lists of the powers and responsibilities of all provincial-level government departments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大督查问责力度，组织开展第三次国务院大督查，对去产能、民间投资等政策落实情况进行专项督查和第三方评估，严肃查处一些地区违规新建钢铁项目、生产销售“地条钢”等行为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We intensified accountability inspections. The third State Council accountability inspection was carried out; special inspections and third-party evaluations were conducted on the implementation of policies related to cutting overcapacity and encouraging private investment; and new steel projects launched in breach of regulations and the production and sale of substandard steel products were strictly investigated and dealt with. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强安全生产工作，事故总量和重特大事故数量继续下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We strengthened workplace safety efforts and saw a continued decline in the total number of accidents and in the number of accidents of a serious nature. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化社会治安综合治理，依法打击违法犯罪，有力维护了国家安全和公共安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We took comprehensive measures to maintain law and order and, in accordance with law, cracked down on crime and other violations, effectively safeguarding national and public security.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实开展“两学一做”学习教育，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We carried out in earnest activities to enable Party members to gain a good understanding of the Party Constitution, Party regulations, and General Secretary Xi Jinping's major policy addresses and to meet Party standards.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真落实党中央八项规定精神，坚决纠正“四风”，严格执行国务院“约法三章”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We worked scrupulously to ensure compliance with the Party Central Committee's eight-point decision on improving Party and government conduct, took firm action to address formalism, bureaucratism, hedonism, and extravagance, and rigorously enforced the State Council's three-point decision on curbing government spending. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法惩处一批腐败分子，反腐败斗争形成压倒性态势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We punished a number of corrupt officials in accordance with law, and the fight against corruption has built up irresistible momentum.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，中国特色大国外交卓有成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As a major country, China has made outstanding achievements in its diplomacy with distinctive features over the past year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>习近平主席等国家领导人出访多国，出席亚太经合组织领导人非正式会议、上海合作组织峰会、金砖国家领导人会晤、核安全峰会、联大系列高级别会议、亚欧首脑会议、东亚合作领导人系列会议等重大活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>President Xi Jinping and other Chinese leaders visited many countries. They attended major international events, including the 24th APEC Economic Leaders Meeting, the Shanghai Cooperation Organization Summit, the BRICS Leaders Meeting, the Nuclear Security Summit, high-level meetings of the 71st session of the UN General Assembly, the Asia-Europe Meeting, and the East Asian leaders meetings on cooperation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>成功举办澜沧江－湄公河合作首次领导人会议。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We hosted the first-ever Lancang-Mekong Cooperation Leaders Meeting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同主要大国协调合作得到加强，同周边国家全面合作持续推进，同发展中国家友好合作不断深化，同联合国等国际组织联系更加密切。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's coordination and cooperation with other major countries were strengthened, its comprehensive cooperation with neighboring countries continued to be boosted, its friendship and cooperation with other developing countries were deepened, and its interactions with the UN and other international organizations became closer. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极促进全球治理体系改革与完善。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China was actively involved in reforming and improving the global governance system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动《巴黎协定》生效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We played our part in ensuring that the Paris Agreement was put into force. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济外交、人文交流成果丰硕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Economic diplomacy and personal and cultural exchanges yielded notable outcomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚定维护国家领土主权和海洋权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We were resolute in upholding China's sovereignty, territorial integrity, and maritime rights and interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国作为负责任大国，在国际和地区事务中发挥了建设性作用，为世界和平与发展作出了重要贡献。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As a responsible major country, China has been playing a constructive role in international and regional issues and has made significant contributions to world peace and development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>隆重庆祝中国共产党成立95周年，隆重纪念中国工农红军长征胜利80周年，宣示了我们不忘初心、继续前进、战胜一切困难的坚强意志，彰显了全国人民走好新的长征路、不断夺取新胜利的坚定决心！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We celebrated the 95th anniversary of the founding of the Communist Party of China and the 80th anniversary of the victory of the Long March of the Chinese Workers and Peasants Red Army, demonstrating our unshakable will to remain true to the founding mission of the Party, to keep pressing ahead, and to overcome all difficulties, and showing the firm determination of all Chinese people to keep up our stride on the new Long March and continue striving for new victories.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年取得的成绩，是以习近平同志为核心的党中央正确领导的结果，是全党全军全国各族人民团结奋斗的结果。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We owe all the achievements made over the past year to the sound leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core and the concerted efforts of the Party, the military, and the people of all our nation's ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我代表国务院，向全国各族人民，向各民主党派、各人民团体和各界人士，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On behalf of the State Council, I wish to express our sincere gratitude to all our people, including public figures from all sectors of society, and to other parties and people's organizations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向香港特别行政区同胞、澳门特别行政区同胞、台湾同胞和海外侨胞，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I express our sincere appreciation to our fellow countrymen and women in the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions and in Taiwan, and to Chinese nationals overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>向关心和支持中国现代化建设事业的各国政府、国际组织和各国朋友，表示诚挚感谢！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I also wish to express our heartfelt thanks to the governments of other countries, international organizations, and friends from all over the world who have shown understanding and support for China in its endeavor to modernize.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们也清醒看到，经济社会发展中还存在不少困难和问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Yet we must not lose sight of the many problems and challenges China faces in pursuing economic and social development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济增长内生动力仍需增强，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The internal forces driving economic growth need to be strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>部分行业产能过剩严重，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Overcapacity poses a serious challenge in some industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些企业生产经营困难较多，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some enterprises face difficulties in their production and operations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>地区经济走势分化，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Economic prospects for different regions are divergent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政收支矛盾较大，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiscal imbalance is becoming great. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济金融风险隐患不容忽视。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>And potential economic and financial risks cannot be overlooked. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>环境污染形势依然严峻，特别是一些地区严重雾霾频发，治理措施需要进一步加强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Environmental pollution remains grave, and in particular, some areas are frequently hit by heavy smog. We need to further strengthen our steps to combat pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在住房、教育、医疗、养老、食品药品安全、收入分配等方面，人民群众还有不少不满意的地方。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There are also many problems causing public concern in housing, education, healthcare, elderly care, food and drug safety, and income distribution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>煤矿、建筑、交通等领域发生了一些重大安全事故，令人痛心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It is distressing that there were some major accidents in the coal mining, construction, and transportation sectors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府工作存在不足，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There is still room for improvement in government performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>有些改革举措和政策落实不到位，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Some reform policies and measures have not been fully implemented.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>涉企收费多、群众办事难等问题仍较突出，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Excess fees and charges being levied on businesses and difficulties facing individuals who want to access government services remain standout problems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>行政执法中存在不规范不公正不文明现象，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We still see problems of laws and regulations being enforced in a non-standard, unfair, or uncivil way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>少数干部懒政怠政、推诿扯皮，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A small number of government employees are lazy and neglectful of their duties or shirk responsibility. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一些领域腐败问题时有发生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Corruption often occurs in some sectors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们一定要直面挑战，敢于担当，全力以赴做好政府工作，不辱历史使命，不负人民重托。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must confront these challenges head-on, be ready to bear the weight of responsibility, and do our all to deliver. We must fulfill our historic mission and live up to the great trust placed in us by the Chinese people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二、2017年工作总体部署</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies, I now wish to discuss with you what the government will do in 2017.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年将召开中国共产党第十九次全国代表大会，是党和国家事业发展中具有重大意义的一年。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, the Communist Party of China will hold its 19th National Congress, so it will be a year of great significance for advancing the cause of the Party and our country. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好政府工作，要</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To deliver in our work this year, the government will do the following:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在以习近平同志为核心的党中央领导下，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Follow the leadership of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高举中国特色社会主义伟大旗帜，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Hold high the banner of socialism with Chinese characteristics</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面贯彻党的十八大和十八届三中、四中、五中、六中全会精神，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Implement fully the guidelines from the 18th National Party Congress and those of the third through sixth plenary sessions of the 18th Party Central Committee</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以邓小平理论、“三个代表”重要思想、科学发展观为指导，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Take as our guide Deng Xiaoping Theory, the Theory of Three Represents, and the Scientific Outlook on Development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入贯彻习近平总书记系列重要讲话精神和治国理政新理念新思想新战略，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Put into practice the principles from General Secretary Xi Jinping's major addresses and his new vision, thinking, and strategies for China's governance</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹推进“五位一体”总体布局和协调推进“四个全面”战略布局，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Promote balanced economic, political, cultural, social, and ecological progress and coordinated implementation of the Four-Pronged Comprehensive Strategy (Note: This refers to making comprehensive moves to finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects, deepen reform, advance the law-based governance of China, and strengthen Party self-governance)</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持稳中求进工作总基调，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Remain committed to the underlying principle of making progress while keeping performance stable</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>牢固树立和贯彻落实新发展理念，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Gain a strong understanding of and put into practice the new development philosophy</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适应把握引领经济发展新常态，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Adapt to, approach in the right way, and steer the new normal in economic development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以提高发展质量和效益为中心，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Give central importance to improving the quality and returns of development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持宏观政策要稳、产业政策要准、微观政策要活、改革政策要实、社会政策要托底的政策思路，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Ensure that macro-level policy is consistent, industrial policy is targeted, micro-level policy injects dynamism into the market, reform policy delivers outcomes, and social policy sees basic living needs are met</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持以推进供给侧结构性改革为主线，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Focus on supply-side structural reform</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适度扩大总需求，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Expand aggregate demand as appropriate</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强预期引导，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Do better in guiding expectations</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化创新驱动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Strengthen the role of innovation in driving development</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面做好稳增长、促改革、调结构、惠民生、防风险各项工作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Maintain stable growth, promote reform, make structural adjustments, improve living standards, and guard against risks</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持经济平稳健康发展和社会和谐稳定，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Maintain stable and sound economic development as well as social harmony and stability</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以优异成绩迎接党的十九大胜利召开。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These efforts should enable us to pave the way for the 19th National Party Congress with outstanding achievements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>综合分析国内外形势，我们要做好应对更加复杂严峻局面的充分准备。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The developments both in and outside of China require that we are ready to face more complicated and graver situations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>世界经济增长低迷态势仍在延续，“逆全球化”思潮和保护主义倾向抬头，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>World economic growth remains sluggish, and both the deglobalization trend and protectionism are growing. =</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>主要经济体政策走向及外溢效应变数较大，不稳定不确定因素明显增加。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There are many uncertainties about the direction of the major economies' policies and their spillover effects, and the factors that could cause instability and uncertainty are visibly increasing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国发展处在爬坡过坎的关键阶段，经济运行存在不少突出矛盾和问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China is at a crucial and challenging stage in its own development endeavors, and there are many salient challenges and problems in the economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>困难不容低估，信心不可动摇。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The difficulties we face are not to be underestimated, but we must remain confident that they will be overcome. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国物质基础雄厚、人力资源充裕、市场规模庞大、产业配套齐全、科技进步加快、基础设施比较完善，经济发展具有良好支撑条件，宏观调控还有不少创新手段和政策储备。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China has a solid material foundation, abundant human resources, a huge market, and a complete system of industries. It is making faster scientific and technological progress, and has a complete range of infrastructure. We have good conditions for sustaining economic development, and many innovative tools and policy options for conducting macroeconomic regulation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们坚信，有党的坚强领导，坚持党的基本路线，坚定不移走中国特色社会主义道路，依靠人民群众的无穷创造力，万众一心、奋力拼搏，我国发展一定能够创造新的辉煌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should follow the leadership of the Party, uphold the Party's fundamental political guidelines, and keep to the path of socialism with Chinese characteristics; we should rely on the inexhaustible creativity of the people, unite as one, and forge ahead. It is our firm belief that by doing this, we will make great new achievements in China's development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年发展的主要预期目标是：</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Based on the above considerations, we have set the following key projected targets for development this year:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国内生产总值增长6.5%左右，在实际工作中争取更好结果；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- GDP growth of around 6.5 percent, or higher if possible in practice</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民消费价格涨幅3%左右；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- CPI increase kept at around 3 percent</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业1100万人以上，城镇登记失业率4.5%以内；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Over 11 million new urban jobs, and a registered urban unemployment rate within 4.5 percent</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>进出口回稳向好，国际收支基本平衡；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- A steady rise in import and export volumes, and a basic balance in international payments</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>居民收入和经济增长基本同步；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- Increases in personal income basically in step with economic growth</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>单位国内生产总值能耗下降3.4%以上，主要污染物排放量继续下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>-- A reduction of at least 3.4 percent in energy consumption per unit of GDP, and continued reductions in the release of major pollutants</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年的经济增长预期目标，符合经济规律和客观实际，有利于引导和稳定预期、调整结构，也同全面建成小康社会要求相衔接。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The projected target for this year's growth is realistic and in keeping with economic principles; it will help steer and steady expectations and make structural adjustments; and it will help achieve the goal of finishing the building of a moderately prosperous society in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳增长的重要目的是为了保就业、惠民生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>An important reason for stressing the need to maintain stable growth is to ensure employment and improve people's lives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年就业压力加大，要坚持就业优先战略，实施更加积极的就业政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As employment pressure grows this year, we will continue to give top priority to creating jobs and implement a more proactive employment policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城镇新增就业预期目标比去年多100万人，突出了更加重视就业的导向。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year's target for urban job creation is one million more than last year, underlining the greater importance we are attaching to employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>从经济基本面和就业吸纳能力看，这一目标通过努力是能够实现的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Considering our sound economic fundamentals and the capacity they bring for job creation, with hard work, this target is attainable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要继续实施积极的财政政策和稳健的货币政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will continue to pursue a proactive fiscal policy and a prudent monetary policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在区间调控基础上加强定向调控、相机调控，提高预见性、精准性和有效性，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>On the basis of conducting range-based regulation, we will focus more on targeted and well-timed regulation and increase the foresight, precision, and effectiveness of our regulation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>注重消费、投资、区域、产业、环保等政策的协调配合，确保经济运行在合理区间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen coordination of consumption, investment, regional, industrial, and environmental protection policies, and ensure the economy performs within an appropriate range.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政政策要更加积极有效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will pursue a more proactive and effective fiscal policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年赤字率拟按3%安排，财政赤字2.38万亿元，比去年增加2000亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year's deficit-to-GDP ratio is projected to be 3 percent, with the fiscal deficit set at 2.38 trillion yuan, representing a year-on-year increase of 200 billion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>其中，中央财政赤字1.55万亿元，地方财政赤字8300亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To break this down, the projected deficit of the central government is 1.55 trillion yuan, and the projected deficit of local governments is 830 billion yuan. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>安排地方专项债券8000亿元，继续发行地方政府置换债券。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local government special bonds to be issued will total 800 billion yuan, and local government bonds will continue to be issued to replace their outstanding debt. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年赤字率保持不变，主要是为了进一步减税降费，全年再减少企业税负3500亿元左右、涉企收费约2000亿元，一定要让市场主体有切身感受。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The main reason for keeping this year's deficit-to-GDP ratio unchanged is to allow for further reductions in taxes and fees. Over the course of the year, the tax burden on businesses will be further eased by around 350 billion yuan, and business related fees will be further cut by around 200 billion yuan to benefit market entities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>财政预算安排要突出重点、有保有压，加大力度补短板、惠民生。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government budgets should highlight priorities; spending in some areas should be maintained while in others cuts should be made; and more should be spent to strengthen areas of weakness and improve living standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对地方一般性转移支付规模增长9.5%，重点增加均衡性转移支付和困难地区财力补助。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>General transfer payments to local governments will be increased by 9.5 percent, with the focus on increasing transfer payments for equalizing access to basic public services and stepping up subsidies for regions facing economic difficulties. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>压缩非重点支出，减少对绩效不高项目的预算安排。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will scale down non-priority spending and cut budgets for projects that do not deliver desired outcomes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要坚持过紧日子，中央部门要带头，一律按不低于5%的幅度压减一般性支出，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels should tighten their belts, and central government departments should take the lead by cutting no less than 5 percent of their general expenditures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>决不允许增加“三公”经费，挤出更多资金用于减税降费，坚守节用裕民的正道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>No increase in spending on official overseas visits, official vehicles, or official hospitality is permitted; and we will squeeze out more funds to cover cuts in taxes and fees. We will keep government spending low and enrich our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>货币政策要保持稳健中性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to pursue a prudent and neutral monetary policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年广义货币M2和社会融资规模余额预期增长均为12%左右。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The M2 money supply and aggregate financing are forecasted to grow by around 12 percent in 2017. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要综合运用货币政策工具，维护流动性基本稳定，合理引导市场利率水平，疏通传导机制，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will apply a full range of monetary policy instruments, maintain basic stability in liquidity, see that market interest rates remain at an appropriate level, and improve the transmission mechanism of monetary policy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进金融资源更多流向实体经济，特别是支持“三农”和小微企业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage a greater flow of financial resources into the real economy, particularly in support of agriculture, rural areas, and farmers, and small and micro businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持汇率市场化改革方向，保持人民币在全球货币体系中的稳定地位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The RMB exchange rate will be further liberalized, and the currency's stable position in the global monetary system will be maintained.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好今年政府工作，要把握好以下几点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To deliver a good performance this year, we in government should stick to the following guidelines:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是贯彻稳中求进工作总基调，保持战略定力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we should make progress while maintaining stable performance and keep our strategic focus. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳是大局，要着力稳增长、保就业、防风险，守住金融安全、民生保障、环境保护等方面的底线，确保经济社会大局稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Stability is of overriding importance. We should ensure stable growth, maintain employment, and prevent risks. To ensure overall economic and social stability we must not allow the redline to be crossed concerning financial security, people's wellbeing, or environmental protection. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在稳的前提下要勇于进取，深入推进改革，加快结构调整，敢于啃“硬骨头”，努力在关键领域取得新进展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should, while maintaining stable performance, endeavor to make progress, deepen reforms, accelerate structural adjustments, be prepared to take on some really tough problems, and push to make progress in key areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是坚持以推进供给侧结构性改革为主线。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we should focus on supply-side structural reform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须把改善供给侧结构作为主攻方向，通过简政减税、放宽准入、鼓励创新，持续激发微观主体活力，减少无效低效供给、扩大有效供给，更好适应和引导需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must give priority to improving supply-side structure. We should streamline administration, reduce taxes, further expand market access, and encourage innovation; and we should keep micro entities energized, reduce ineffective supply while expanding effective supply, and better adapt to and guide demand. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是一个化蛹成蝶的转型升级过程，既充满希望又伴随阵痛，既非常紧迫又艰巨复杂。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Like the struggle from chrysalis to butterfly, this process of transformation and upgrading is filled with promise but also accompanied by great pain; it is urgent, formidable, and complicated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要勇往直前，坚决闯过这个关口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should press forward with courage and get the job done. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是适度扩大总需求并提高有效性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we should expand aggregate demand as appropriate and improve its efficacy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国内需潜力巨大，扩内需既有必要也有可能，关键是找准发力点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's potential domestic demand is enormous, and it is both necessary and possible for domestic demand to be expanded. The key is to know where to start. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要围绕改善民生来扩大消费，着眼补短板、增后劲来增加投资，使扩内需更加有效、更可持续，使供给侧改革和需求侧管理相辅相成、相得益彰。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to increase consumer spending to improve people's lives, and boost investment to strengthen areas of weakness and sustain development, so that the expansion of domestic demand becomes more effective and sustainable and supply-side reform and demand-side regulation reinforce each other. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是依靠创新推动新旧动能转换和结构优化升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we should rely on innovation to replace old growth drivers with new ones and speed up structural improvement and upgrading. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国发展到现在这个阶段，不靠改革创新没有出路。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Having reached the current stage of development, China can now advance only through reform and innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们拥有世界上数量最多、素质较高的劳动力，有最大规模的科技和专业技能人才队伍，蕴藏着巨大的创新潜能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We have the largest quality workforce as well as the largest pool of scientists, engineers, and professionals in the world, and their potential for innovation is truly tremendous. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持以改革开放为动力、以人力人才资源为支撑，加快创新发展，培育壮大新动能、改造提升传统动能，提高全要素生产率，推动经济保持中高速增长、产业迈向中高端水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must continue to draw strength from reform and opening up, fully tap the potential of human resources and human capital, and move more quickly to pursue innovation-driven development. We should foster and develop new growth drivers while transforming and upgrading the traditional growth drivers, and increase total factor productivity. These steps will enable China's economy to maintain a medium-high rate of growth and China's industries to move toward the medium-high end. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是着力解决人民群众普遍关心的突出问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we should solve prominent problems of public concern. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府的一切工作都是为了人民，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All government work is for the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要践行以人民为中心的发展思想，把握好我国处于社会主义初级阶段的基本国情。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should keep in mind the fact that China remains in the primary stage of socialism and pursue a people focused development philosophy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对群众反映强烈、期待迫切的问题，有条件的要抓紧解决，把好事办好；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Where conditions permit, we will lose no time in solving problems about which the people have great concern and which demand speedy resolution.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一时难以解决的，要努力创造条件逐步加以解决。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>When problems cannot be solved for the time being, we will work to resolve them over time. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要咬定青山不放松，持之以恒为群众办实事、解难事，促进社会公平正义，把发展硬道理更多体现在增进人民福祉上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must make dedicated efforts to deliver services to the people, resolve the difficulties they face, promote social equity and justice, and demonstrate that development does better people's lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三、2017年重点工作任务</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>I now wish to discuss our major areas of work for 2017.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对今年艰巨繁重的改革发展稳定任务，我们要通观全局、统筹兼顾，突出重点、把握关键，正确处理好各方面关系，着重抓好以下几个方面工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Confronted with the formidable tasks of reform and development and maintaining stability this year, we must keep in mind the big picture and adopt a holistic approach, have clear priorities and focus on key tasks, and properly handle interactions among various sectors. We should give priority to the following areas of work.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（一）用改革的办法深入推进“三去一降一补”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>1. Pushing ahead with the five priority tasks through reform</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要在巩固成果基础上，针对新情况新问题，完善政策措施，努力取得更大成效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should, on the basis of consolidating and building on what we have achieved, improve our policies and measures in light of new developments and new problems so as to make greater progress.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实有效去产能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Take solid and effective steps to cut overcapacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要再压减钢铁产能5000万吨左右，退出煤炭产能1.5亿吨以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will further reduce steel production capacity by around 50 million metric tons and shut down at least 150 million metric tons of coal production facilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>同时，要淘汰、停建、缓建煤电产能5000万千瓦以上，以防范化解煤电产能过剩风险，提高煤电行业效率，优化能源结构，为清洁能源发展腾空间。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At the same time, we will suspend or postpone construction on or eliminate no less than 50 million kilowatts of coal-fired power generation capacity in order to guard against and defuse the risks of overcapacity in coal-fired power, improve the efficiency of this sector, optimize the energy mix, and make room for clean energy to develop. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要严格执行环保、能耗、质量、安全等相关法律法规和标准，更多运用市场化法治化手段，有效处置“僵尸企业”，推动企业兼并重组、破产清算，坚决淘汰不达标的落后产能，严控过剩行业新上产能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strictly enforce all laws, regulations, and standards on environmental protection, energy consumption, quality, and safety and make more use of market- and law-based methods as we work to address the problems of "zombie enterprises," encourage enterprise mergers, restructuring, and bankruptcy liquidations, shut down all outdated production facilities that fail to meet standards, and stringently control the launching of new projects in industries that are already saddled with overcapacity. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>去产能必须安置好职工，中央财政专项奖补资金要及时拨付，地方和企业要落实相关资金与措施，确保分流职工就业有出路、生活有保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As overcapacity is cut, we must provide assistance to laid-off workers. Central government special funds for rewards and subsidies should be promptly allocated and local governments and enterprises need to put in place related funds and measures, to ensure that laid-off workers can find new jobs and secure their livelihoods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>因城施策去库存。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Take targeted policies to cut excess urban real estate inventory. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>目前三四线城市房地产库存仍然较多，要支持居民自住和进城人员购房需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At present, there is still excess supply in the real estate markets of third- and fourth-tier cities. We will support both local and new residents in buying homes for personal use. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持住房的居住属性，落实地方政府主体责任，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to be clear that housing is for people to live in, and local governments should take primary responsibility in this respect.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快建立和完善促进房地产市场平稳健康发展的长效机制，健全购租并举的住房制度，以市场为主满足多层次需求，以政府为主提供基本保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should move faster to establish robust long-term mechanisms for promoting the steady and sound development of the real estate sector and build a better housing system that gives equal weight to buying and renting, with multiple levels of demand being met primarily by the market, and basic housing support provided by the government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强房地产市场分类调控，房价上涨压力大的城市要合理增加住宅用地，规范开发、销售、中介等行为，遏制热点城市房价过快上涨。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take more category-based and targeted steps to regulate the real estate market. Cities that are under big pressure from rising housing prices need to increase as appropriate the supply of land for residential use. We should better regulate housing development, marketing, and intermediary services, and keep home prices from rising too quickly in popular cities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>目前城镇还有几千万人居住在条件简陋的棚户区，要持续进行改造。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Today several dozen million people still live in rundown areas in cities and towns. We must continue housing renovations in these areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年再完成棚户区住房改造600万套，继续发展公租房等保障性住房，因地制宜、多种方式提高货币化安置比例，加强配套设施建设和公共服务，让更多住房困难家庭告别棚户区，让广大人民群众在住有所居中创造新生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will renovate another 6 million housing units in these areas, continue to develop public rental housing and other forms of government-subsidized housing, base measures on local circumstances and use multiple means to increase the use of monetary compensation for those affected by such rebuilding, and improve local infrastructure and public services. With these efforts, we will help more families struggling with housing to bid farewell to rundown areas, and see that with good roofs over their heads our people move on to better lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极稳妥去杠杆。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Carry out deleveraging in an active and prudent way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国非金融企业杠杆率较高，这与储蓄率高、以信贷为主的融资结构有关。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>There is high leverage in nonfinancial Chinese firms. This is caused by high savings rates and the composition of financing which is primarily based on credit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要在控制总杠杆率的前提下，把降低企业杠杆率作为重中之重。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>While working to control overall leverage, we should focus on bringing down the leverage of enterprises. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进企业盘活存量资产，推进资产证券化，支持市场化法治化债转股，发展多层次资本市场，加大股权融资力度，强化企业特别是国有企业财务杠杆约束，逐步将企业负债降到合理水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to see that the idle assets of enterprises are put to use, push ahead with securitization of corporate assets, support market- and law-based debt-to-equity swaps, develop the multilevel capital market, expand equity financing, and place tighter constraints on enterprises, especially SOEs, in leveraging, so as to gradually reduce enterprise debt to an acceptable level.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>多措并举降成本。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Take multiple measures to cut costs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大小微企业享受减半征收所得税优惠的范围，年应纳税所得额上限由30万元提高到50万元；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More small businesses with low profits will enjoy halved corporate income tax, with the upper limit of taxable annual income raised from 300,000 to 500,000 yuan.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>科技型中小企业研发费用加计扣除比例由50%提高到75%，千方百计使结构性减税力度和效应进一步显现。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>For small and medium high-tech enterprises, the proportion of R&amp;D expenses covered by the additional tax reduction policy is to be raised from 50 to 75 percent. We will do all we can to see the intensity and impact of structural tax cuts deliver further results.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>名目繁多的收费使许多企业不堪重负，要大幅降低非税负担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The great number of charges have placed an unbearable burden on many businesses; we are going to slash non-tax burdens. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一是全面清理规范政府性基金，取消城市公用事业附加等基金，授权地方政府自主减免部分基金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will completely overhaul government-managed funds, abolish municipal public utility surcharges, and authorize local governments to reduce and cancel some funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二是取消或停征中央涉企行政事业性收费35项，收费项目再减少一半以上，保留的项目要尽可能降低收费标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will abolish or suspend 35 administrative charges paid by enterprises to the central government, again cutting the number of charges by more than half; and then reduce as far as possible those that still apply. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各地也要削减涉企行政事业性收费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local governments also need to make significant cuts to government administrative fees. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三是减少政府定价的涉企经营性收费，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will reduce government-set operating fees for businesses.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>清理取消行政审批中介服务违规收费，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Unauthorized fees charged by intermediaries for government review and approval will be overhauled or abolished.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动降低金融、铁路货运等领域涉企经营性收费，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work toward lower operating fees levied on businesses in the finance and railway freight sectors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对市场调节类经营服务性收费的监管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen oversight over the collection of market-set service fees. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四是继续适当降低“五险一金”有关缴费比例。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will continue to lower as appropriate the share paid by enterprises for contributions to social security. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五是通过深化改革、完善政策，降低企业制度性交易成本，降低用能、物流等成本。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we will deepen reforms and improve policies to reduce government imposed transaction costs for businesses and lower their energy and logistics costs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各有关部门和单位都要舍小利顾大义，使企业轻装上阵，创造条件形成我国竞争新优势。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All government departments and agencies concerned should have in mind the overall interests of the country instead of their narrow departmental interests, reduce the financial burden on enterprises, and help them develop new advantages over international competition.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>精准加力补短板。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Take targeted and powerful measures to strengthen areas of weakness. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要针对严重制约经济社会发展和民生改善的突出问题，结合实施“十三五”规划确定的重大项目，加大补短板力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to focus on salient problems that are holding back economic and social development and making it difficult to improve people's standards of living, and we should integrate efforts to undertake major projects set out in the 13th Five-Year Plan with efforts to strengthen areas of weakness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快提升公共服务、基础设施、创新发展、资源环境等支撑能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should act faster to raise the capacity of public services, infrastructure, innovation-driven development, and resources and the environment to sustain development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>贫困地区和贫困人口是全面建成小康社会最大的短板。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Poor areas and people living in poverty represent the area of greatest weakness we must face as we work to finish building a moderately prosperous society in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要深入实施精准扶贫精准脱贫，今年再减少农村贫困人口1000万以上，完成易地扶贫搬迁340万人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to do more in implementing targeted poverty reduction and elimination measures. This year we will further reduce the number of rural residents living in poverty by over 10 million, including 3.4 million to be relocated from inhospitable areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央财政专项扶贫资金增长30%以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Central government funding for poverty alleviation will be increased by over 30 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强集中连片特困地区、革命老区、边疆和民族地区开发，改善基础设施和公共服务，推动特色产业发展、劳务输出、教育和健康扶贫，做好因病等致贫返贫群众帮扶，实施贫困村整体提升工程，增强贫困地区和贫困群众自我发展能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to step up development in contiguous areas of extreme poverty, old revolutionary bases, border areas, and areas with concentrations of ethnic minorities. For this we should focus on the following work: improving infrastructure and public services; fostering poverty alleviation through distinctive local businesses, the domestic and overseas export of labor, and improving education and health care; providing assistance to people who become poor or sink back into poverty due to illness; implementing the program for improving life in poor villages; and building the self-development capacity of poor areas and people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进贫困县涉农资金整合，强化资金和项目监管。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In poor counties, different rural development funds will be merged, and oversight over funds and projects will be strengthened. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>创新扶贫协作机制，支持和引导社会力量参与扶贫。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop new mechanisms for coordinating poverty reduction efforts. We will support and guide non-governmental participation in combating poverty. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实落实脱贫攻坚责任制，实施最严格的评估考核，严肃查处假脱贫、“被脱贫”、数字脱贫，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The system for ensuring responsibility is taken for poverty elimination will be effectively enforced, the strictest possible evaluations and assessments of poverty alleviation will be carried out, and stern measures will be taken to address deception, falsification, and the manipulation of numbers in poverty elimination work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>确保脱贫得到群众认可、经得起历史检验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must see that the results of our poverty elimination earn the approval of our people and stand the test of time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（二）深化重要领域和关键环节改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>2. Deepening reform in major sectors and key links</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要全面深化各领域改革，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Full reform will be deepened in all areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进基础性、关键性改革，增强内生发展动力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to advance fundamental and critical reforms to boost the internal forces driving development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续推进政府职能转变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to transform government functions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>使市场在资源配置中起决定性作用和更好发挥政府作用，必须深化简政放权、放管结合、优化服务改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To enable the market to play the decisive role in resource allocation and to give better play to the role of government, we must deepen reforms to streamline government administration, delegate more powers, and improve regulation and service. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>这是政府自身的一场深刻革命，要继续以壮士断腕的勇气，坚决披荆斩棘向前推进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This is a profound reform of government itself, which we need to continue to pursue with the courage to make painful self-adjustments and overcome all odds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实行清单管理制度，制定国务院部门权力和责任清单，加快扩大市场准入负面清单试点，减少政府的自由裁量权，增加市场的自主选择权。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the list-based management system, formulate lists of powers and responsibilities of the departments under the State Council, accelerate the extension of trials of granting market access on the basis of a negative list, and reduce the discretionary powers of the government while giving the market more freedom to take its course. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>清理取消一批生产和服务许可证。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will abolish the requirement for permits for a number of production and service activities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化商事制度改革，实行多证合一，扩大“证照分离”改革试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen institutional reforms in the business sector, merge different forms of certification required of businesses into one certificate, and expand trials to separate operating permits and business licenses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善事中事后监管制度，实现“双随机、一公开”监管全覆盖，推进综合行政执法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the system for conducting both registration and post-registration oversight over businesses, apply the oversight model of random inspection and public release to cover all business activities, and strengthen coordinated administrative law enforcement. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快国务院部门和地方政府信息系统互联互通，形成全国统一政务服务平台。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate efforts to make the information systems of the State Council departments and those of local governments better connected and form a nationally unified government service platform. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们一定要让企业和群众更多感受到“放管服”改革成效，着力打通“最后一公里”，坚决除烦苛之弊、施公平之策、开便利之门。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To see that businesses and the public benefit more from our reforms to streamline administration, delegate powers, and improve regulation and services, we must cut red tape, level the playing field, provide greater convenience, and remove that last crucial hurdle.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推进财税体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to reform fiscal and tax systems. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实和完善全面推开营改增政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement and improve policies on replacing business tax with VAT across the board. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>简化增值税税率结构，今年由四档税率简并至三档，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will simplify the structure of VAT rates, and undertake this year to turn the four tax brackets into three.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>营造简洁透明、更加公平的税收环境，进一步减轻企业税收负担。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create a simple, transparent, and fairer tax environment and further ease the tax burden of our firms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进中央与地方财政事权和支出责任划分改革，制定收入划分总体方案，健全地方税体系，规范地方政府举债行为。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to advance the reform of defining the respective financial powers and expenditure responsibilities of the central and local governments, formulate an overall plan for central and local government revenue sharing, improve the local tax system, and better regulate local government debt financing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进政府预决算公开，倒逼沉淀资金盘活，提高资金使用效率，每一笔钱都要花在明处、用出实效。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up efforts to make government budgets and final accounts more transparent to create pressure for idle budgetary funds to be put to good use. We must use funds more efficiently, and ensure every single sum is spent where it can be seen and produces results.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓好金融体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will advance reforms in the financial sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进金融机构突出主业、下沉重心，增强服务实体经济能力，坚决防止脱实向虚。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will prompt financial institutions to focus on their main business and make their services accessible to small and micro businesses, strengthen their ability to serve the real economy, and resolutely prevent them from being distracted from their intended purpose. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励大中型商业银行设立普惠金融事业部，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage large and medium commercial banks to establish inclusive finance departments. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>国有大型银行要率先做到，实行差别化考核评价办法和支持政策，有效缓解中小微企业融资难、融资贵问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Large state-owned banks should take the lead in this effort. We will adopt differentiated assessment and evaluation measures and supportive policies, and effectively address the problem of medium, small, and micro enterprises being unable to access loans or having to pay high interest to secure loans. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发挥好政策性开发性金融作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make good use of policy-backed and development-oriented finance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进农村信用社改革，强化服务“三农”功能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move forward with the reform of rural credit cooperatives and strengthen the role they play in meeting the needs of agriculture, rural areas, and farmers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化多层次资本市场改革，完善主板市场基础性制度，积极发展创业板、新三板，规范发展区域性股权市场。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the multi-tiered capital market, improve the basic systems of the main board, actively develop the ChiNext stock market and the new third board, and see that regional equity markets develop in a well-regulated way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>拓宽保险资金支持实体经济渠道。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand channels for using insurance funds to support the real economy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力发展绿色金融。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make major efforts to develop green finance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动融资租赁业健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will give impetus to the sound development of the financial leasing industry. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>当前系统性风险总体可控，但对不良资产、债券违约、影子银行、互联网金融等累积风险要高度警惕。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>At present, overall, systemic risks are under control. But we must be fully alert to the buildup of risks, including risks related to non-performing assets, bond defaults, shadow banking, and Internet finance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极稳妥推进金融监管体制改革，有序化解处置突出风险点，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take active and steady steps to advance the reform of the financial regulatory system, and work systematically to defuse major potential risks.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>整顿规范金融秩序，筑牢金融风险“防火墙”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure order in the financial sector and build a firewall against financial risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国经济基本面好，商业银行资本充足率、拨备覆盖率比较高，可动用的工具和手段多。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The fundamentals of the Chinese economy remain sound, the capital adequacy ratio and provision coverage of commercial banks remain high, and we have many financial tools and instruments that can be used. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对守住不发生系统性金融风险的底线，我们有信心和底气、有能力和办法。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We have the confidence, the ability, and the means to forestall systemic risks.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进国企国资改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of SOEs and state capital. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要以提高核心竞争力和资源配置效率为目标，形成有效制衡的公司法人治理结构、灵活高效的市场化经营机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should develop a corporate governance structure (represented by legal person) that is under effective check and a flexible and efficient market-based operating system, with a view to increasing core competitiveness and making resource allocation more effective. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要基本完成公司制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year we will basically complete the introduction of corporate systems into SOEs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化混合所有制改革，在电力、石油、天然气、铁路、民航、电信、军工等领域迈出实质性步伐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform to establish mixed ownership systems, and make substantive progress in industries including electric power, petroleum, natural gas, railways, civil aviation, telecommunications, and defense. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓好电力和石油天然气体制改革，开放竞争性业务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will advance structural reform in the power, oil and gas sectors and open their competitive operations to the private sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续推进国有企业瘦身健体、提质增效，抓紧剥离办社会职能，解决历史遗留问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do more to make SOEs leaner and healthier, and perform better; and we will redouble efforts to relieve SOEs of their obligations to operate social programs and help them resolve other longstanding issues. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进国有资本投资、运营公司改革试点。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make progress in work on piloting reforms in state capital investment and management companies. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改善和加强国有资产监管，确保资产保值增值，把人民的共同财富切实守护好、发展好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve and strengthen regulation of state assets, and ensure that state assets maintain and increase their value, as we are duty bound to see that the common wealth of the people is well protected and grows.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>更好激发非公有制经济活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do more to energize the non-public sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入落实支持非公有制经济发展的政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will thoroughly implement the policies and measures for supporting the development of the non-public sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极构建新型政商关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work actively to develop a new relationship between government and business. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励非公有制企业参与国有企业改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage non-public enterprises to participate in SOE reforms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持权利平等、机会平等、规则平等，进一步放宽非公有制经济市场准入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must ensure equal rights, equal opportunities, and fair rules, and further expand market access to the non-public sector. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>凡法律法规未明确禁入的行业和领域，都要允许各类市场主体平等进入；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All industries and sectors for which entry is not explicitly prohibited by laws or regulations should be open to different types of market entities;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>凡向外资开放的行业和领域，都要向民间资本开放；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>all industries and sectors that are open to overseas investment should be open to Chinese private capital;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>凡影响市场公平竞争的不合理行为，都要坚决制止。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and all unjustified activities that impede fair market competition should be stopped.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强产权保护制度建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the property rights protection system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保护产权就是保护劳动、保护发明创造、保护和发展生产力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Protecting property rights means protecting labor, protecting invention and innovation, and protecting and developing productive forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要加快完善产权保护制度，依法保障各种所有制经济组织和公民财产权，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work faster to improve the property rights protection system and protect in accordance with law the property rights of economic entities under all forms of ownership and the property rights of citizens.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>激励人们创业创新创富，激发和保护企业家精神，使企业家安心经营、放心投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage people to start businesses, make innovations, and create wealth, and we will inspire and protect entrepreneurship, and ensure that entrepreneurs can run their businesses and make investments with peace of mind. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对于侵害企业和公民产权的行为，必须严肃查处、有错必纠。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Activities that infringe on the property rights of businesses and citizens must be investigated and dealt with severely; anything that has been done wrong must be corrected.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推进社会体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make a big push for progress in the reform of the social system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化收入分配制度配套改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reforms in support of change in the income distribution system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推动养老保险制度改革，划转部分国有资本充实社保基金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take steady steps to advance reform of the old-age insurance system, and allocate a portion of state capital to enlarge social security funds. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化医疗、医保、医药联动改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the coordinated reform of medical services, health insurance, and the medicine industry. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面推开公立医院综合改革，全部取消药品加成，协调推进医疗价格、人事薪酬、药品流通、医保支付方式等改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will introduce overall reform in public hospitals nationwide, abolish all markups on pharmaceuticals, and make coordinated progress in reforming health care pricing, staffing and remuneration, medicine distribution, and models of health insurance payment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进教育、文化和事业单位等改革，把社会领域的巨大发展潜力充分释放出来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue reforms in education, the cultural sector, and public institutions to unleash society's vast potential for growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化生态文明体制改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen institutional reform to build a sound ecological environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善主体功能区制度和生态补偿机制，建立资源环境监测预警机制，开展健全国家自然资源资产管理体制试点，出台国家公园体制总体方案，为生态文明建设提供有力制度保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the functional zoning system and the mechanisms for compensating for ecological conservation efforts; we will put in place resource and environment monitoring and early-warning mechanisms; we will launch trials to improve the state natural resource assets management system; and we will introduce an overall plan for establishing a national parks system. All these efforts should provide effective institutional safeguards for building a sound ecological environment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（三）进一步释放国内需求潜力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>3. Doing more to unleash the potential of domestic demand</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动供给结构和需求结构相适应、消费升级和有效投资相促进、区域城乡发展相协调，增强内需对经济增长的持久拉动作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will push to see that the composition of supply becomes better matched with the composition of demand and that consumption upgrades and effective investment reinforce each other; we will promote coordinated development between regions and between rural and urban areas; and we will strengthen the role of domestic demand in sustaining growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进消费稳定增长。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote a steady increase in consumer spending. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适应消费需求变化，完善政策措施，改善消费环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to adapt to changes in consumer demand, improve our policies and measures, and create a better consumer environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一要加快发展服务消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we need to speed up the development of service consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展新一轮服务业综合改革试点，支持社会力量提供教育、文化、养老、医疗等服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will launch a new round of trials for comprehensive reform in the service sector, and support the non-governmental sector in providing educational, cultural, elderly care, healthcare, and other services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动服务业模式创新和跨界融合，发展医养结合、文化创意等新兴消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage development of new service models and cross-sectoral integration, combined medical and elderly care services, cultural and creative services, and other emerging forms of consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实带薪休假制度，完善旅游设施和服务，大力发展乡村、休闲、全域旅游。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure paid vacations are enforced, improve tourist facilities and services, and make a big push to develop rural tourism, recreational tourism, and all-for-one tourism. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大数字家庭、在线教育等信息消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase information consumption including digital homes and online learning. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进电商、快递进社区进农村，推动实体店销售和网购融合发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that communities and rural areas have better access to e-commerce and express delivery services, and encourage the integrated development of physical store sales and online shopping. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二要增加高品质产品消费。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we need to boost consumption of quality products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导企业增品种、提品质、创品牌，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide enterprises in increasing the variety of products, raising their quality, and building the brands of their products.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大内外销产品“同线同标同质”实施范围，更好满足消费升级需求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>More products sold domestically should be produced on the same production lines, meet the same standards, and be of the same quality as products for export in order to better satisfy the needs of upgrading consumption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三要整顿和规范市场秩序。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we need to ensure order in the market. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严肃查处假冒伪劣、虚假广告、价格欺诈等行为，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will be strict about investigating and punishing the production and sale of counterfeit and substandard goods, false advertising, and price fraud.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强消费者权益保护，让群众花钱消费少烦心、多舒心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the protection of consumer rights; and we will make sure that spending is an enjoyable rather than a disappointing experience for consumers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极扩大有效投资。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work proactively to expand effective investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导资金更多投向补短板、调结构、促创新、惠民生的领域。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide more investment into fields that will help to strengthen weak areas, drive structural adjustment, encourage innovation, and improve people's lives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年要完成铁路建设投资8000亿元、公路水运投资1.8万亿元，再开工15项重大水利工程，继续加强轨道交通、民用和通用航空、电信基础设施等重大项目建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will invest 800 billion yuan in railway construction and 1.8 trillion yuan in highway and waterway projects. Construction on another 15 major water conservancy projects will begin; and work on major rail transport, civil and general aviation, and telecommunications infrastructure projects will be sped up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中央预算内投资安排5076亿元。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 507.6 billion yuan of investment has been included in the central government budget this year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实和完善促进民间投资的政策措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement and improve policies and measures for encouraging private investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化政府和社会资本合作，完善相关价格、税费等优惠政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to promote public-private partnerships, and improve related policies on preferential pricing, tax, and fee arrangements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>政府要带头讲诚信，决不能随意改变约定，决不能“新官不理旧账”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Government must take the lead in acting in good faith and must never arbitrarily change agreements, and new officials must not disavow obligations undertaken by their predecessors.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化区域发展格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve planning for regional development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹推进三大战略和“四大板块”发展，实施好相关规划，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will coordinate the launching of three strategic initiatives and the development of the eastern, central, western, and northeastern regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>研究制定新举措。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure related plans are well implemented and explore and adopt new measures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动国家级新区、开发区、产业园区等创新发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost the development of national-level new areas, development zones, and industrial parks through innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持资源枯竭、生态严重退化等地区经济转型发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the economic transformation and development of areas hurt by resource depletion and severe ecological degradation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>优化空域资源配置。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Airspace resources will be better allocated. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进海洋经济示范区建设，加快建设海洋强国，坚决维护国家海洋权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up the development of maritime economy demonstration zones, we will move faster to develop China into a strong maritime country, and we will be resolute in safeguarding China's maritime rights and interests.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进新型城镇化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take solid steps to pursue a new type of urbanization. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化户籍制度改革，今年实现进城落户1300万人以上，加快居住证制度全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen the reform of the household registration system. This year, at least 13 million new urban residents will be registered as permanent urban residents. We will speed up work to introduce the urban residence card system nationwide. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持中小城市和特色小城镇发展，推动一批具备条件的县和特大镇有序设市，发挥城市群辐射带动作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of small and medium cities and small towns with distinctive local features. We will help a number of counties and very large towns that meet the criteria to steadily develop into cities, and we will make city clusters better play their role in driving the development of their surrounding areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进“多规合一”，提升城市规划设计水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage local governments to integrate their urban plans into single master plans and raise the standard of municipal planning and design. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进建筑业改革发展，提高工程质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take more steps to reform and develop the construction industry, and improve the quality of construction projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹城市地上地下建设，加强城市地质调查，再开工建设城市地下综合管廊2000公里以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote coordinated urban development above and below the ground, strengthen geological surveying, and begin construction on at least another 2,000 kilometers of underground utility tunnels in cities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动消除城区重点易涝区段三年行动，推进海绵城市建设，有效治理交通拥堵等“城市病”，使城市既有“面子”、更有“里子”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A three-year initiative will be launched to remove the risk of flooding in highly vulnerable urban areas, further progress will be made in the development of sponge cities, and effective steps will be taken to address traffic congestion and other urban maladies. All these efforts will make our cities more attractive and function better.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（四）以创新引领实体经济转型升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>4. Transforming and upgrading the real economy through innovation</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实体经济从来都是我国发展的根基，当务之急是加快转型升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The real economy has always been the foundation of China's development; the task we now face is to speed up its transformation and upgrading. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要深入实施创新驱动发展战略，推动实体经济优化结构，不断提高质量、效益和竞争力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do more to implement the strategy of innovation-driven development, upgrade the structure of the real economy, and improve its performance and competitiveness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提升科技创新能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen our capability for making technological innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善对基础研究和原创性研究的长期稳定支持机制，建设国家重大科技基础设施和技术创新中心，打造科技资源开放共享平台。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve mechanisms for providing continued long-term support for fundamental research and original research, build major national infrastructure projects for science and technology and set up technological innovation hubs, and establish platforms for sharing R&amp;D resources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进全面创新改革试验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue piloting reforms for all-around innovation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革科技评价制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform the system for assessing scientific and technological achievements. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实落实高校和科研院所自主权，落实股权期权和分红等激励政策，落实科研经费和项目管理制度改革，让科研人员不再为杂事琐事分心劳神。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see our universities and research institutes truly operate with autonomy, ensure that incentive policies like stocks, options, and dividends are implemented, and implement the reform of the systems for managing research funding and projects. These steps should keep our scientists and engineers from being distracted and allow them to focus on their research. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展知识产权综合管理改革试点，完善知识产权创造、保护和运用体系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will begin piloting reforms to conduct integrated management of intellectual property rights and improve the system for creating, protecting, and applying intellectual property rights. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化人才发展体制改革，实施更加有效的人才引进政策，广聚天下英才，充分激发科研人员积极性，定能成就创新大业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of China's systems for cultivating talent and introduce more effective policies for bringing in talent from overseas. By welcoming the world's brightest minds to China and fully motivating our scientists and engineers, we will use innovation to accomplish great things.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快培育壮大新兴产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of emerging industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实施战略性新兴产业发展规划，加快新材料、新能源、人工智能、集成电路、生物制药、第五代移动通信等技术研发和转化，做大做强产业集群。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement our plan for developing strategic emerging industries. We will accelerate R&amp;D on and commercialization of new materials, new energy, artificial intelligence, integrated circuits, bio-pharmacy, 5G mobile communications, and other technologies, and develop industrial clusters in these fields. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持和引导分享经济发展，提高社会资源利用效率，便利人民群众生活。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to support and guide the development of the sharing economy to enable greater efficiency in the use of resources and bring greater convenience to our people. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>本着鼓励创新、包容审慎原则，制定新兴产业监管规则，引导和促进新兴产业健康发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will formulate regulatory rules for emerging industries in keeping with the principle of encouraging innovation and conducting regulation in a tolerant and prudent way, and guide and promote the healthy development of emerging industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化统计管理体制改革，健全新兴产业统计。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reform of the statistics management system and improve statistics on emerging industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在互联网时代，各领域发展都需要速度更快、成本更低、安全性更高的信息网络。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the age of the Internet, faster, safer, and more cost-effective information networks are crucial to the development of every sector.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年网络提速降费要迈出更大步伐，年内全部取消手机国内长途和漫游费，大幅降低中小企业互联网专线接入资费，降低国际长途电话费，推动“互联网+”深入发展、促进数字经济加快成长，让企业广泛受益、群众普遍受惠。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will do more to increase broadband speed and lower rates for Internet services. Mobile rates for domestic roaming and long-distance calls will be cancelled; rates for broadband services for small and medium enterprises will be slashed; and rates for international calls will be lowered.We will push forward with the Internet Plus action plan and speed up the development of the digital economy. I am confident that all these steps will benefit both businesses and our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力改造提升传统产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will endeavor to transform and upgrade traditional industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施《中国制造2025》，加快大数据、云计算、物联网应用，以新技术新业态新模式，推动传统产业生产、管理和营销模式变革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to implement the Made in China 2025 initiative, promote accelerated application of big data, cloud computing, and the Internet of Things, and use new technologies, new forms of business, and new models to bring about transformation in the production, management, and marketing models of traditional industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>把发展智能制造作为主攻方向，推进国家智能制造示范区、制造业创新中心建设，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With the development of smart manufacturing as our focus, we will press ahead with building national smart manufacturing demonstration zones and manufacturing innovation centers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施工业强基、重大装备专项工程，大力发展先进制造业，推动中国制造向中高端迈进。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard on the implementation of projects to build a robust foundation for industrial development and projects to develop and make major equipment, and we will make a big push to develop advanced manufacturing, thus moving toward mid- and high-end manufacturing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善制造强国建设政策体系，以多种方式支持技术改造，促进传统产业焕发新的蓬勃生机。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve policies designed to turn China into a manufacturer of quality, and we will adopt a variety of supportive measures for technological upgrading and re-energize traditional industries.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续推进大众创业、万众创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to encourage people to start businesses and make innovations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“双创”是以创业创新带动就业的有效方式，是推动新旧动能转换和经济结构升级的重要力量，是促进机会公平和社会纵向流动的现实渠道，要不断引向深入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our policy of encouraging people to start businesses and innovate is an effective way of creating jobs through business startups and innovation; it is an important source of strength that fosters new growth drivers to replace old ones and that upgrades the economic structure; and it is an effective channel for promoting equal opportunity and facilitating vertical social mobility. We must keep on pushing hard with this policy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新建一批“双创”示范基地，鼓励大企业和科研院所、高校设立专业化众创空间，加强对创新型中小微企业支持，打造面向大众的“双创”全程服务体系，使各类主体各展其长、线上线下良性互动，使小企业铺天盖地、大企业顶天立地，市场活力和社会创造力竞相迸发。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish more entrepreneurship and innovation demonstration centers; we will encourage large enterprises, research institutes, and universities to establish specialized spaces for crowd innovation; we will strengthen support for innovative medium, small and micro businesses; and we will develop a full range of services that are accessible to the general public for the entire business startup and innovation process. All this should help entities to fully exploit their own strengths and interact both on- and off-line, and see small enterprises burgeoning nationwide, large enterprises growing mighty, and market dynamism and social creativity being fully unleashed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面提升质量水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take comprehensive steps to improve product quality. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广泛开展质量提升行动，加强全面质量管理，夯实质量技术基础，强化质量监督，健全优胜劣汰质量竞争机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take a broad range of actions to raise quality, strengthening all-around quality management, building firm technological foundations for product quality, tightening quality oversight, and improving the competitive mechanism that links a firm's fate in business to the quality of its products. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>质量之魂，存于匠心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Quality is born of workmanship. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要大力弘扬工匠精神，厚植工匠文化，恪尽职业操守，崇尚精益求精，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote workmanship and foster a culture of workmanship where workers have a strong work ethic and tirelessly seek improvement.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善激励机制，培育众多“中国工匠”，打造更多享誉世界的“中国品牌”，推动中国经济发展进入质量时代。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will refine our incentive mechanisms and see great numbers of Chinese workers exemplify workmanship and more Chinese brands enjoy international recognition. We will usher in an era of quality for economic development in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（五）促进农业稳定发展和农民持续增收。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>5. Promoting steady development of agriculture and continued increases in rural incomes</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进农业供给侧结构性改革，完善强农惠农政策，拓展农民就业增收渠道，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will do more to advance supply-side structural reform in agriculture, improve policies to boost agriculture and benefit farmers, and create more channels for rural residents to find employment and increase their incomes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保障国家粮食安全，推动农业现代化与新型城镇化互促共进，加快培育农业农村发展新动能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure China's food security, see that agricultural modernization and new urbanization reinforce each other, and speed up efforts to foster new drivers powering agricultural and rural development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进农业结构调整。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will push forward with structural adjustment in agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导农民根据市场需求发展生产，增加优质绿色农产品供给，扩大优质水稻、小麦生产，适度调减玉米种植面积，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide farmers in responding to market demand, increasing the supply of quality green agricultural products and the production of quality rice and wheat, and making appropriate reductions to the amount of land devoted to growing corn.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>粮改饲试点面积扩大到1000万亩以上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand trials to replace grain crop with feed crop cultivation to cover over 667,000 hectares. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>鼓励多渠道消化玉米库存。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage the use of multiple channels to reduce excess stockpiles of corn. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持主产区发展农产品精深加工，发展观光农业、休闲农业，拓展产业链价值链，打造农村一二三产业融合发展新格局。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support major agricultural production areas in developing intensive processing of agricultural products, develop farm-based recreation or agritourism, extend industry chains and value chains, and step up the integrated development of primary, secondary, and tertiary industries in rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强现代农业建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost the development of modern agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快推进农产品标准化生产、品牌创建和保护，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work faster to see due standards are followed in agricultural production, and promote the development and protection of brand name agricultural products.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>打造粮食生产功能区、重要农产品生产保护区、特色农产品优势区和现代农业产业园。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will create functional zones for grain production, major agricultural product protection areas, areas for growing quality and distinctively local agricultural products, and modern agriculture industrial parks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进土地整治，大力改造中低产田，推广旱作技术，新增高效节水灌溉面积2000万亩。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve rural land, upgrade low- and medium-yield cropland, and spread dry-farming techniques, adding 1.33 million hectares of farmland under highly water-efficient irrigation. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强耕地保护，改进占补平衡。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the protection of cultivated land and improve work to offset cultivated land used for other purposes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展多种形式适度规模经营，是中国特色农业现代化的必由之路，离不开农业保险有力保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Developing appropriately scaled, diversified farming operations is vital for Chinese-style agricultural modernization, and these operations need to be covered by agricultural insurance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年在13个粮食主产省选择部分县市，对适度规模经营农户实施大灾保险，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, in selected counties and county-level cities in 13 major grain-producing provinces, we will provide catastrophe insurance for farmers engaging in appropriately scaled farming operations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>调整部分财政救灾资金予以支持，提高保险覆盖面和理赔标准，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will channel a portion of budgetary disaster relief funds into this initiative and expand the coverage and raise the benefits of the insurance scheme. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善农业再保险体系，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the agricultural reinsurance system.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>以持续稳健的农业保险助力现代农业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We wish to use sustainable and sound agricultural insurance schemes to drive the development of modern agriculture.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化农村改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen rural reforms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步推进农村集体产权制度改革，深化农村土地制度改革试点，赋予农民更多财产权利。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take steady steps to reform the rural collective property rights system and deepen the pilot reform of the rural land system to see our farmers are granted more property rights. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善粮食等重要农产品价格形成机制和收储制度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve pricing mechanisms for grain and other important agricultural products as well as the system for their purchase and storage.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进农业水价综合改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will carry out comprehensive reform of the pricing for water used in agriculture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化集体林权、国有林区林场、农垦、供销社等改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen reforms related to collective forest tenure, state forestry areas and farms, state-owned farms, and rural supply and marketing cooperatives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农村基层组织建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the development of rural community-level organizations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全农村“双创”促进机制，培养更多新型职业农民，支持农民工返乡创业，进一步采取措施鼓励高校毕业生、退役军人、科技人员到农村施展才华。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the mechanisms for encouraging business startups and innovation in rural areas, train more professional farmers of new kinds, support migrant workers in starting businesses in their hometowns and villages, and take further measures to encourage college graduates, demobilized military personnel, and scientists and engineers to work in rural areas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农村公共设施建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up the development of public facilities in rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新建改建农村公路20万公里。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A total of 200,000 kilometers of roads will be upgraded or built in rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实现农村稳定可靠供电服务和平原地区机井通电全覆盖。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that all rural areas have a steady and reliable supply of power and that all electric pumpsets on rural flatlands are connected. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完成3万个行政村通光纤。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fiber-optic broadband will be extended to 30,000 administrative villages. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高农村饮水安全供水保证率。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase water supply to better ensure access to safe drinking water. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大农村危房改造力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to renovate dilapidated houses and improve rural living environments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入推进农村人居环境整治，建设既有现代文明、又具田园风光的美丽乡村。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Our goal is to develop rural China into a place where people can enjoy both the beauty of the countryside and the conveniences of modern living.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（六）积极主动扩大对外开放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>6. Actively expanding China's opening up to the world</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对国际环境新变化和国内发展新要求，要进一步完善对外开放战略布局，加快构建开放型经济新体制，推动更深层次更高水平的对外开放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Faced with new changes in the international environment and the new requirements of China's development, we need to further refine our strategic plan for opening up, work faster to build new systems for an open economy, and drive China toward both deeper and higher level opening up.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扎实推进“一带一路”建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make solid efforts to pursue the Belt and Road Initiative. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持共商共建共享，加快陆上经济走廊和海上合作支点建设，构建沿线大通关合作机制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Guided by the principle of achieving shared growth through consultation and collaboration, we will accelerate the building of overland economic corridors and maritime cooperation hubs, and establish cooperative mechanisms for achieving compatibility in customs clearance procedures along the routes. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化国际产能合作，带动我国装备、技术、标准、服务走出去，实现优势互补。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen international industrial-capacity cooperation, promoting the export of Chinese equipment, technologies, standards, and services, to see that China and other countries are able to draw on each other's strengths. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强教育、科技、文化、卫生、旅游等人文交流合作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen personal and cultural exchanges and cooperation in education, science and technology, culture, healthcare, and tourism. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高质量办好“一带一路”国际合作高峰论坛，同奏合作共赢新乐章。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that in holding the Belt and Road Forum for International Cooperation we offer a meeting of real quality, opening the page on a great new chapter of mutually beneficial cooperation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进外贸继续回稳向好。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that foreign trade continues to pick up and register steady growth. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实和完善进出口政策，推动优进优出。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement and improve our import and export policies and optimize imports and exports. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大出口信用保险覆盖面，对成套设备出口融资应保尽保。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the coverage of export credit insurance and provide export financing insurance for all insurable complete sets of large equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进服务贸易创新发展试点，设立服务贸易创新发展引导基金。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move ahead with trials to develop services trade through innovation and establish a seed fund to encourage innovation to develop services trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持市场采购贸易、外贸综合服务企业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of market procurement trade and integrated foreign trade service firms. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快外贸转型升级示范基地建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the development of demonstration centers for transforming and upgrading foreign trade. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进加工贸易向产业链中高端延伸、向中西部地区梯度转移。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will facilitate the extension of processing trade to the medium-high end of industrial chains and its relocation to central and western regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推广国际贸易“单一窗口”，实现全国通关一体化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will extend the practice of processing international trade through a single window, and achieve nationwide integration of customs clearance procedures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>增加先进技术、设备和关键零部件进口，促进贸易平衡发展和国内产业加快升级。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The import of advanced technologies, equipment, and important parts and components will be increased to promote the balanced growth of foreign trade and accelerate industrial upgrading in China.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力优化外商投资环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make big moves to improve the environment for foreign investors. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>修订外商投资产业指导目录，进一步放宽服务业、制造业、采矿业外资准入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will revise the catalog of industries open to foreign investment, and make service industries, manufacturing, and mining more open to foreign investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持外商投资企业在国内上市、发债，允许参与国家科技计划项目。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage foreign-invested firms to be listed and issue bonds in China and allow them to take part in national science and technology projects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在资质许可、标准制定、政府采购、享受《中国制造2025》政策等方面，对内外资企业一视同仁。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Foreign firms will be treated the same as domestic firms when it comes to license applications, standards-setting, and government procurement, and will enjoy the same preferential policies under the Made in China 2025 initiative. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>地方政府可在法定权限范围内，制定出台招商引资优惠政策。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Local governments can, within the scope of the powers granted them by law, adopt preferential policies to attract foreign investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>高标准高水平建设11个自贸试验区，全面推广成熟经验。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will build 11 high-standard pilot free trade zones, and widely spread practices developed in these zones that are proven to work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>引导对外投资健康规范发展，提升风险防范能力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will guide the sound and standardized development of Chinese overseas investment, and increase the ability of Chinese companies to hedge against risks. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国开放的大门会越开越大，必将继续成为最富吸引力的外商投资目的地。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China's door is going to keep on opening wider, and China will keep working to be the most attractive destination for foreign investment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进国际贸易和投资自由化便利化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote the liberalization and facilitation of international trade and investment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>经济全球化符合世界各国的根本利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Economic globalization is in the fundamental interests of all countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国将坚定不移推动全球经济合作，维护多边贸易体制主渠道地位，积极参与多边贸易谈判。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China will not shift in its commitment to promoting global economic cooperation, will uphold the multilateral trading regime as the main channel of international trade, and will play an active part in multilateral trade negotiations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们愿与有关国家一道，推动中国－东盟自贸区升级议定书全面生效实施，早日结束区域全面经济伙伴关系协定谈判，推进亚太自贸区建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China is ready to join hands with the other countries involved to fully put into force and implement the Protocol to Amend the Framework Agreement on Comprehensive Economic Cooperation between China and ASEAN, to conclude talks as soon as possible for the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership agreement, and to advance the development of the Free Trade Area of the Asia-Pacific. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续与有关国家和地区商谈投资贸易协定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to negotiate investment and trade agreements with relevant countries and regions. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国是负责任的国家，作出的承诺一直认真履行，应有的权益将坚决捍卫。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China is a responsible country. We have always striven to honor the commitments we have made, and we will firmly defend our due rights and interests.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（七）加大生态环境保护治理力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>7. Effectively strengthening environmental protection</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快改善生态环境特别是空气质量，是人民群众的迫切愿望，是可持续发展的内在要求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Faster progress in work to improve the environment, particularly air quality, is what people are desperately hoping for, and is critical to sustainable development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须科学施策、标本兼治、铁腕治理，努力向人民群众交出合格答卷。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must adopt well-designed policies, tackle both symptoms and root causes, and take tough steps to make the grade in responding to the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决打好蓝天保卫战。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make our skies blue again. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年二氧化硫、氮氧化物排放量要分别下降3%，重点地区细颗粒物（PM2.5）浓度明显下降。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, we will see that sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions are both cut by 3 percent and that fine particulate matter (PM2.5) density in key areas falls markedly. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>一要加快解决燃煤污染问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>First, we will work faster to address pollution caused by coal burning. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面实施散煤综合治理，推进北方地区冬季清洁取暖，完成以电代煤、以气代煤300万户以上，全部淘汰地级以上城市建成区燃煤小锅炉。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take comprehensive steps to reduce non-centralized coal burning operations, promote clean winter heating in the northern region, replace the use of coal with electricity and natural gas in more than 3 million households, and shut down all small coal-fired furnaces in established districts of cities at the prefectural level and above. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大燃煤电厂超低排放和节能改造力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up work on upgrading coal-fired power plants to achieve ultra-low emissions and energy conservation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>东中部地区要分别于今明两年完成，西部地区于2020年完成。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Upgrading should be completed this year in the eastern region, next year in the central region, and by 2020 in the western region. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓紧解决机制和技术问题，优先保障清洁能源发电上网，有效缓解弃水、弃风、弃光状况。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will act quickly to improve our mechanisms and technologies, enabling us to prioritize the integration of clean energy sources into the electric grid and effectively address wasted hydro-, wind- and solar-power generation capacities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>安全高效发展核电。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop nuclear power in a safe and highly efficient way. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快秸秆综合利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will also work faster to make comprehensive use of straw. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>二要全面推进污染源治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Second, we will take a full range of measures to tackle the sources of pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展重点行业污染治理专项行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take focused actions to curb pollution in key industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对所有重点工业污染源实行24小时在线监控，确保监控质量。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will place all key sources of industrial pollution under round-the-clock online monitoring, and ensure the quality of monitoring. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>明确排放不达标企业最后达标时限，到期不达标的坚决依法关停。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will set a clear deadline by which enterprises must meet required discharge standards, and take resolute law-based action to close down all those that still fail to meet standards after the deadline. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三要强化机动车尾气治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Third, we will strengthen control over exhaust emitted by motor vehicles. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>基本淘汰黄标车，加快淘汰老旧机动车，对高排放机动车进行专项整治，鼓励使用清洁能源汽车。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that basically all higher-emission vehicles are scrapped, work faster to take old vehicles off the roads, carry out dedicated initiatives to deal with high-emission vehicles, and encourage the use of clean-energy cars. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高燃油品质，在重点区域加快推广使用国六标准燃油。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the quality of fuels and move faster to promote the use of those that meet National-VI emission standards in key areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>四要有效应对重污染天气。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fourth, we will take effective steps to tackle heavy air pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强对大气污染的源解析和雾霾形成机理研究，提高应对的科学性和精准性。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen analysis of sources of air pollution and research on the causes of smog to improve the scientific basis and precision of the steps taken. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>扩大重点区域联防联控范围，强化预警和应急措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will expand the coverage of mechanisms in key areas to ensure coordinated prevention and control efforts across regions, and enhance early warning and emergency response measures. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>五要严格环境执法和督查问责。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Fifth, we will strictly enforce environmental laws and regulations, conduct inspections, and hold violators accountable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对偷排、造假的，必须依法惩治；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Illegal dischargers and fraud must be punished in accordance with law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对执法不力、姑息纵容的，必须严肃追究；</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Officials who do a poor job in enforcing the law, knowingly allow environmental violations,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>对空气质量恶化、应对不力的，必须严格问责。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>or respond inadequately to worsening air quality will be held fully accountable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>治理雾霾人人有责，贵在行动、成在坚持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Tackling smog is down to every last one of us, and success depends on action and commitment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全社会不懈努力，蓝天必定会一年比一年多起来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As long as the whole of our society keeps trying, we will have more and more blue skies with each passing year.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化水、土壤污染防治。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the prevention and control of water and soil pollution. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年化学需氧量、氨氮排放量要分别下降2%。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, chemical oxygen demand and ammonia nitrogen emissions should both drop by 2 percent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓好重点流域、区域、海域水污染和农业面源污染防治。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will effectively prevent and control water pollution in key drainage basins, regions, and sea areas and agricultural pollution from non-point sources. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>开展土壤污染详查，分类制定实施治理措施。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will undertake rigorous investigations on soil pollution and develop and implement category-based measures to tackle this problem. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强城乡环境综合整治，倡导绿色生活方式，普遍推行垃圾分类制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will take comprehensive measures to improve both urban and rural environments, advocate green living, and promote waste sorting. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>培育壮大节能环保产业，发展绿色再制造和资源循环利用产业，使环境改善与经济发展实现双赢。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen energy conservation and environmental protection industries and develop green remanufacturing and circular industries to ensure both environmental improvement and economic growth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进生态保护和建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move forward with ecological conservation and improvement. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>抓紧划定并严守生态保护红线。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will act promptly to set redlines for ecological conservation and hold firm to these lines. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积极应对气候变化。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work actively to respond to climate change. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>启动森林质量提升、长江经济带重大生态修复、第二批山水林田湖生态保护工程试点，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will begin to pilot projects to improve the quality of our forests and restore ecosystems along the Yangtze Economic Belt, and launch the second group of trial projects to conserve the ecosystems of mountains, forests, farmland, rivers, and lakes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完成退耕还林还草1200万亩以上，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will turn more than 800,000 hectares of marginal farmland into forests or grassland. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强荒漠化、石漠化治理，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will address the spread of desertification and stony deserts. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>积累更多生态财富，构筑可持续发展的绿色长城。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>These initiatives will enable us to accumulate more ecological wealth and build a green Great Wall of sustainable development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（八）推进以保障和改善民生为重点的社会建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>8. Promoting social development to ensure and improve the wellbeing of our people</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>民生是为政之要，必须时刻放在心头、扛在肩上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The wellbeing of the people is at the center of governance; it must be always on our minds and the responsibility for it must never leave our shoulders. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在当前国内外形势严峻复杂的情况下，更要优先保障和改善民生，该办能办的实事要竭力办好，基本民生的底线要坚决兜牢。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Against the backdrop of challenging and complex environments both at home and abroad, it is all the more imperative that we prioritize efforts to ensure and improve the wellbeing of our people, spare no effort to deliver benefit to them wherever possible, and ensure their basic living needs are met.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力促进就业创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strive to boost employment and business startups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善就业政策，加大就业培训力度，加强对灵活就业、新就业形态的支持。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve employment policy, strengthen employment training, and increase support for flexible employment and new forms of employment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>今年高校毕业生795万人，再创历史新高，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, 7.95 million students will graduate from college, the highest number on record.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要实施好就业促进、创业引领、基层成长等计划，促进多渠道就业创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to effectively implement initiatives to promote their employment, to guide them in starting businesses, and to encourage them to work at the community level, providing our college graduates with multiple channels to find jobs or start their own businesses. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实和完善政策，切实做好退役军人安置工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement and improve policies and see that demobilized military personnel are settled into new jobs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大就业援助力度，扶持城镇困难人员、残疾人就业，确保零就业家庭至少有一人稳定就业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will step up employment assistance to help vulnerable urban residents and people with disabilities find employment and to ensure that at least one member in every family currently with zero employment secures a stable job. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们必须牢牢抓住就业这一民生之本，让人们在劳动中创造财富，在奋斗中实现人生价值。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Employment is crucial to ensuring people's wellbeing. We will focus our effort on facilitating employment to see that through their hard work, people can create wealth and realize their full potential.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>办好公平优质教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure that our people have access to equitable and quality education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统一城乡义务教育学生“两免一补”政策，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will combine the separate policies for rural and urban students receiving compulsory education that waive tuition and miscellaneous fees, supply free textbooks, and grant living allowances for boarders from financially disadvantaged families. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快实现城镇义务教育公共服务常住人口全覆盖，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make compulsory education accessible as a public service to all permanent urban residents, with and without local urban household registration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续改善薄弱学校办学条件，扩大优质教育资源覆盖面，不断缩小城乡、区域、校际办学差距。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to improve conditions in badly built and poorly operated schools, and expand the reach of quality educational resources, so as to narrow the gap in the quality of education between urban and rural areas, different regions, and different schools. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续扩大重点高校面向贫困地区农村招生规模。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to expand the enrollment of students from poor rural areas at key colleges and universities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高博士研究生国家助学金补助标准。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase government grants for PhD students. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进世界一流大学和一流学科建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen efforts to develop more world-class universities and first-class fields of discipline. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续推动部分本科高校向应用型转变。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to encourage some undergraduate institutions to shift their focus toward providing applied education. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化高考综合改革试点。加快发展现代职业教育。加强民族教育，办好特殊教育、继续教育、学前教育和老年教育。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will pilot comprehensive reform of the college entrance examination system;accelerate the development of modern vocational education; ensure ethnic minorities improve their education; and make sure that we have good special needs education, continuing education, preschool education, and education for senior citizens. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>支持和规范民办教育发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of private education and work to ensure it meets all relevant standards. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强教师队伍建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to improve teacher performance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>制定实施《中国教育现代化2030》。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The Modernizing Chinese Education 2030 initiative will be developed and launched. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要发展人民满意的教育，以教育现代化支撑国家现代化，使更多孩子成就梦想、更多家庭实现希望。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop education that satisfies the needs of our people, make the modernization of education underpin the modernization of our country, and see that more children realize their dreams and more families have their hopes fulfilled.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推进健康中国建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make continued progress in building a Healthy China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>城乡居民医保财政补助由每人每年420元提高到450元，同步提高个人缴费标准，扩大用药保障范围。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase both government subsidies for basic health insurance for rural and nonworking urban residents from 420 to 450 yuan per person per annum and personal contributions, and will expand the scope of this insurance to cover more medicines. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>在全国推进医保信息联网，实现异地就医住院费用直接结算。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will accelerate the building of a nationwide information network for basic health insurance so that healthcare costs can be settled directly where incurred. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>完善大病保险制度，提高保障水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the major disease insurance system and increase insurance benefits for subscribers. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面启动多种形式的医疗联合体建设试点，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will launch nationwide trials to establish partnerships of different forms between medical institutions operating at different levels. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>三级公立医院要全部参与并发挥引领作用，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All municipal-level public hospitals will be expected to participate and play a leading role in this initiative.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建立促进优质医疗资源上下贯通的考核和激励机制，增强基层服务能力，方便群众就近就医。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will establish performance evaluation and incentive mechanisms that encourage the coordinated use of quality medical resources with a view to improving the capacity of community hospitals and conveniencing people by enabling access to medical services closer to home. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>分级诊疗试点和家庭签约服务扩大到85%以上地市。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will extend trials to use a tiered diagnosis and treatment model and a contracted family doctor service system to cover over 85 percent of prefectural-level cities in China. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好健康促进，继续提高基本公共卫生服务经费补助标准，加强疾病预防体系和慢性病防控体系建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In promoting better health, we will continue to increase government subsidies for funding basic public health services and strengthen the development of the disease prevention system and the chronic disease prevention and control system. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>及时公开透明有效应对公共卫生事件。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will respond to public health accidents promptly, publicly, and effectively. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保护和调动医务人员积极性。构建和谐医患关系。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure that medical practitioners remain motivated and that interactions between doctor and patient are amicable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>适应实施全面两孩政策，加强生育医疗保健服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As the policy of allowing couples to have two children has been adopted, we need to strengthen our maternity medical and healthcare services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>依法支持中医药事业发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will support the development of traditional Chinese medicine on the basis of law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>食品药品安全事关人民健康，必须管得严而又严。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The safety of food and medicine is important to the health of our people and therefore demands regulation of the utmost rigor. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要完善监管体制机制，充实基层监管力量，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With this in mind, we will improve the related regulatory system and mechanisms, and strengthen regulatory agencies on the ground. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>夯实各方责任，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that responsibilities are fully assumed by all those involved;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持源头控制、产管并重、重典治乱，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will exercise regulation that starts with the source, place equal emphasis on regulation over production and management, and see that serious violations are severely penalized.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决把好人民群众饮食用药安全的每一道关口。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will be firm in doing all we can to ensure the safety of food and medicine for our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>织密扎牢民生保障网。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will weave a strong safety net to ensure people's wellbeing. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>继续提高退休人员基本养老金，确保按时足额发放。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue raising basic pension payments and see they are paid on time and in full. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>稳步提高优抚、社会救助标准，实施好临时救助制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Standards for benefits for entitled groups and social assistance benefits will be steadily raised, and the emergency aid system will be fully implemented. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>调整完善自然灾害生活补助机制，全部完成去年洪涝灾害中倒损民房的恢复重建。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will adjust and improve the natural disaster subsidy mechanism, and finish the rebuilding of all houses damaged during flooding last year. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强农村留守儿童关爱保护和城乡困境儿童保障。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen efforts to ensure the care and protection of children who remain in rural areas while their parents work away in the cities and provide support for children living in difficult conditions in both rural and urban areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>关心帮助军烈属和孤寡老人。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will provide care and assistance to the families of military personnel and revolutionary martyrs and elderly people who live alone. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全面落实残疾人“两项补贴”制度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will achieve full coverage in providing living allowances for people with disabilities in financial difficulty and nursing care subsidies for people with severe disabilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>县级政府要建立基本生活保障协调机制，切实做好托底工作，使困难群众心里有温暖、生活有奔头。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>County-level governments must put in place coordination mechanisms for meeting people's most basic needs. They must make sure there is a social cushion in place, letting those in real need feel support is there and see hope up ahead. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>综合运用法律、行政、经济等手段，锲而不舍解决好农民工工资拖欠问题，决不允许他们的辛勤付出得不到应有回报。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will use a combination of legal, administrative, and economic means to continue resolving the problem of wage arrears for migrant workers, never allowing their hard work to go unpaid.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>发展文化事业和文化产业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop cultural programs and industries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强社会主义精神文明建设，坚持用中国梦和社会主义核心价值观凝聚共识、汇聚力量，坚定文化自信。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will foster stronger observance of socialist cultural and ethical standards, and continue to use the Chinese Dream and core socialist values to build consensus, pool energy, and strengthen our people's confidence in Chinese culture. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>繁荣发展哲学社会科学和文学艺术创作，发展新闻出版、广播影视、档案等事业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to ensure that philosophy, the social sciences, art, and literature develop and thrive, and promote the development of the press, publishing, radio, television, film, and archiving. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>建设中国特色新型智库。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will develop new types of think tanks with distinctive Chinese features. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>实施中华优秀传统文化传承发展工程，加强文物和非物质文化遗产保护利用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will implement the programs to keep fine traditional Chinese culture thriving and see that China's cultural relics and intangible cultural heritage receive effective protection and play fuller roles. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>大力推动全民阅读，加强科学普及。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work hard to foster a love of reading in our people and enable them to learn more about science. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高基本公共文化服务均等化水平。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make basic public cultural services more equitable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快培育文化产业，加强文化市场监管，净化网络环境。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will speed up our work to develop cultural industries, strengthen regulation over cultural markets, and foster a healthy cyberspace environment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化中外人文交流，推动中华文化走出去。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen personal and cultural exchanges with other countries and do more to share Chinese culture with other countries. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>做好冬奥会、冬残奥会筹办工作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make full preparations for the 2022 Winter Olympic Games and Paralympic Games in Beijing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>统筹群众体育、竞技体育、体育产业发展，广泛开展全民健身，使更多人享受运动快乐、拥有健康体魄。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote coordinated development of recreational and competitive sports and sports industries, and launch extensive Fitness-for-All initiatives so that more people will enjoy sports and stay fit and healthy. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人民身心健康、乐观向上，国家必将充满生机活力。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>When its people are healthy and optimistic, a country will certainly be full of vitality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动社会治理创新。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will explore new forms of social governance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全基层群众自治制度，加强城乡社区治理。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve the system of primary level self-governance and strengthen community governance in both urban and rural areas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>充分发挥工会、共青团、妇联等群团组织作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will see that trade unions, Communist Youth League organizations, women's federations, and other people's organizations fully play their roles. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>改革完善社会组织管理制度，依法推进公益和慈善事业健康发展，促进专业社会工作、志愿服务发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will reform and improve the system for regulating social organizations, promote the healthy development of public-interest activities and charity on the basis of law, and promote specialized social work and volunteer services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>切实保障妇女、儿童、老人、残疾人合法权益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The legitimate rights and interests of women, children, the elderly, and people with disabilities will be effectively protected. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快社会信用体系建设。加强法治宣传教育和法律服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will move faster to improve the social credit system, and work to heighten public awareness of rule of law and strengthen legal services. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>落实信访工作责任制，依法及时就地解决群众合理诉求。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enforce the responsibility system for handling public complaints and see that justified demands are addressed promptly and locally in accordance with law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深化平安中国建设，健全立体化信息化社会治安防控体系，严厉打击暴力恐怖活动，依法惩治黑恶势力犯罪、毒品犯罪和盗窃、抢劫、电信网络诈骗、侵犯个人信息等多发性犯罪，维护国家安全和社会稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to pursue the Peaceful China initiative, improve the multidimensional, IT-based crime prevention and control system, crack down hard on violent terrorist activities, and punish organized crime, drug-related crime, and common crimes like theft, robbery, telecommunications and online fraud, and infringement of personal information, thus upholding China's national security and social stability. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格规范公正文明执法，大力整治社会治安突出问题，全方位提高人民群众安全感。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will work to see that law is enforced in a strict, standardized, fair, and civil way, address prominent problems that endanger public security, and take comprehensive measures to ensure the security of our people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>人命关天，安全至上。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure workplace safety and protect people's lives. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>必须持之以恒抓好安全生产。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must work with tireless dedication to ensure workplace safety. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强安全基础设施建设，做好地震、气象、测绘、地质等工作。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen the development of safety infrastructure, and ensure the quality of work related to seismology, meteorology, surveying, mapping, and geology. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格安全生产责任制，全面落实企业主体责任、地方属地管理责任、部门监管责任，坚决遏制重特大事故发生，切实保障人民群众生命财产安全。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>To curb the occurrence of serious and major accidents and protect the lives and property of our people, we will strictly enforce the workplace safety responsibility system, and see that all responsibilities are fulfilled, namely, the primary responsibility of the enterprise itself, the regulatory responsibility of the government in the locality where the enterprise is located, and the oversight responsibility of the relevant government department.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>（九）全面加强政府自身建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>9. Strengthening the all-around improvement of government</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持党的领导，牢固树立“四个意识”，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must uphold leadership by the Party, willingly maintain political integrity, think in big-picture terms, uphold the leadership core, and keep in alignment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决维护以习近平同志为核心的党中央权威，自觉在思想上政治上行动上同党中央保持高度一致，加快转变政府职能、提高行政效能，更好为人民服务。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should firmly uphold the authority of the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core; closely follow the Central Committee in terms of thinking, political stand, and action; and speed up efforts to transform government functions and improve government performance so as to deliver better services to the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持依法全面履职。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to work to see that government functions are fully carried out in accordance with law. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府及其工作人员要深入贯彻全面依法治国要求，严格遵守宪法，尊崇法治、敬畏法律、依法行政，建设法治政府。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels and all government employees must meet every requirement for fully advancing China's law-based governance. We must strictly observe the Constitution; we must hold the rule of law in the highest esteem; we must hold the law in reverence; we must conduct administration in accordance with law, and we must build a rule of law government. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大政务公开力度。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make government operations more transparent. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持科学决策、民主决策、依法决策，广泛听取各方面意见包括批评意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will ensure that policies are made in a sound and democratic way on the basis of law; and we will widely solicit input and criticism from all interested parties in policy making. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要依法接受同级人大及其常委会的监督，自觉接受人民政协的民主监督，主动接受社会和舆论监督，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We at all levels of government must subject ourselves, as required by law, to oversight by people's congresses and their standing committees at the corresponding levels, to the democratic oversight of CPPCC committees, and to public oversight and oversight through public opinion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>认真听取人大代表、政协委员、民主党派、工商联、无党派人士和各人民团体的意见。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We should willingly solicit input from deputies to people's congresses, members of CPPCC committees, other political parties, chambers of commerce, public figures without party affiliation, and people's organizations. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>作为人民政府，所有工作都要体现人民意愿、维护人民利益、接受人民监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>As ours is a government of the people, all of our work must reflect their will, safeguard their interests, and be placed under their oversight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>始终保持廉洁本色。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will maintain ethical conduct and moral integrity at all times. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要认真落实全面从严治党要求，把党风廉政建设和反腐败工作不断引向深入。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to make every effort to fully strengthen Party self-governance, improve Party conduct and moral integrity, and effectively combat corruption. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决贯彻落实党中央八项规定精神，一以贯之纠正“四风”。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will act with firm resolve to implement the Party Central Committee's eight-point decision on improving Party and government conduct, and make continued efforts to correct formalism, bureaucratism, hedonism, and extravagance. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强行政监察和审计监督。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen administrative supervision and auditing-based oversight. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保持惩治腐败高压态势，聚焦重点领域，严肃查处侵害群众利益的不正之风和腐败问题。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to maintain a tough stance against corruption. With the focus on key areas, we will conduct full investigations into and punish corruption and other forms of misconduct that undermine people's interests. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广大公务员要持廉守正，干干净净为人民做事。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>All public servants must have integrity, be upright, and get on honestly with their jobs of serving the people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>勤勉尽责干事创业。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will perform with a strong work ethic, sense of responsibility, and enterprising spirit. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>中国改革发展的巨大成就是广大干部群众实干出来的，再创新业绩还得靠实干。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China’s remarkable achievements in reform and development are the work of officials and the people; the only way to make new achievements is more hard work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府及其工作人员要干字当头，真抓实干、埋头苦干、结合实际创造性地干，不能简单以会议贯彻会议、以文件落实文件，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Governments at all levels and all government employees must make it our priority to get things done. In performing duties, we should work hard, in a down-to-earth way; and we should be innovative as actual conditions allow. Implementing decisions made at meetings of higher-level authorities and contained in the documents they issue does not mean just holding more meetings and issuing more documents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>不能纸上谈兵、光说不练。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>It's no good to just push paper and pay lip service. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要充分发挥中央和地方两个积极性，鼓励地方因地制宜、大胆探索，竞相推动科学发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We need to keep both the central government and local governments fully motivated, and encourage local governments to work according to local circumstances and be bold in their explorations, so that together we are all promoting sustainable and balanced development. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格执行工作责任制，特别是对重点任务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strictly enforce the responsibility systems, particularly those for implementing key tasks.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要铆紧各方责任、层层传导压力，确保不折不扣落实到位。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We must see responsibilities are fulfilled without fail, that pressure is felt at every level of government, and that implementation is carried out to the letter. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化督查问责，严厉整肃庸政懒政怠政行为，坚决治理政务失信。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen oversight and accountability, take tough steps to address incompetence, inertia, and negligence, and resolvedly address failures to act in good faith in government work. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>健全激励机制和容错纠错机制，给干事者鼓劲，为担当者撑腰。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will improve mechanisms that give incentives and allow for and address mistakes so as to support those who are dedicated to their work and stand behind those who live up to their responsibilities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>广大干部要主动作为、动真碰硬，与人民群众同心协力，以实干推动发展，以实干赢得未来。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Every one of us in government must take an active approach to our work and have the courage to tackle the toughest problems; we must work closely with the people, using concrete action to make progress in development, and using genuine hard work to realize a bright future.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我国是统一的多民族国家。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China is a unified country of many ethnic groups. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要坚持和完善民族区域自治制度，认真贯彻党的民族政策，深入开展民族团结进步创建活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold and improve the system of regional ethnic autonomy, fully implement the Party's policies concerning ethnic groups, and intensify our efforts to foster ethnic unity and progress. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>组织好内蒙古自治区成立70周年庆祝活动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will make sure celebrations to mark the 70th anniversary of the founding of the Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region are a great success. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加大对民族地区发展支持力度，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will increase support for development in areas inhabited mainly by ethnic minorities. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>深入实施兴边富民行动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will deepen efforts to boost development in the border regions to benefit the people living there. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>保护和发展少数民族优秀传统文化，扶持人口较少民族发展，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will protect and develop the fine traditional cultures of ethnic minorities and support the growth of ethnic groups with smaller populations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动各族人民在全面建成小康社会进程中实现共同发展繁荣。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will encourage people of all China's ethnic groups to develop together and thrive together in the course of finishing the building of a society that is moderately prosperous in all respects. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各民族和睦相处、和衷共济、和谐发展，中华民族大家庭必将更加幸福安康。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>With people of all our ethnic groups living together in friendship, sharing in a common cause, and developing in harmony, the big family of the Chinese nation will enjoy more happiness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要全面贯彻党的宗教工作基本方针，依法管理宗教事务，促进宗教关系和谐，发挥宗教界人士和信教群众在促进经济社会发展中的积极作用。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement the Party's fundamental policy on religion, manage religious affairs in accordance with law, promote harmonious relations between religions, and encourage religious leaders and believers to actively involve themselves in promoting economic and social development.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要认真落实侨务政策，保障海外侨胞和归侨侨眷合法权益，充分发挥他们的独特优势和重要作用，海内外中华儿女的凝聚力和向心力必将不断增强。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will fully implement government policies related to overseas Chinese nationals, protect the legitimate rights and interests of overseas Chinese nationals, Chinese nationals who have returned from overseas, and the relatives of overseas Chinese nationals who reside in China, and ensure that they can all give full play to their unique strengths and perform their important roles. I am confident that all the sons and daughters of the Chinese nation, both in and outside China, will forge stronger bonds of attachment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>过去一年，国防和军队改革取得重大突破，军队革命化现代化正规化建设取得新进展新成就。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Last year, we achieved major breakthroughs in the reform of national defense and the armed forces and made fresh progress and new achievements in our work to make the military more revolutionary, modern, and well-structured. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>新的一年，我们要继续坚持以党在新形势下的强军目标为引领，推进政治建军、改革强军、依法治军，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>This year, in pursuing the Party's goal of strengthening the armed forces in a new era, we will work to build them through political work, strengthen them through reform, and ensure they are run by law.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化练兵备战，坚决有效维护国家主权、安全、发展利益。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will boost military training and preparedness, so as to ensure that the sovereignty, security, and development interests of China are resolutely and effectively safeguarded. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚持党对军队的绝对领导，维护和贯彻军委主席负责制。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will uphold the Party's absolute leadership over the armed forces and uphold and implement the system whereby the Chairman of the Central Military Commission assumes overall responsibility over military affairs. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>持续深化国防和军队改革。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to deepen reforms in national defense and the armed forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>强化海空边防管控，周密组织反恐维稳、国际维和、远海护航等重要行动。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen maritime and air defense as well as border control and ensure that important operations related to countering terrorism, safeguarding stability, international peacekeeping, and providing escort in high seas are well organized. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>提高国防科技自主创新能力，加快现代后勤建设和装备发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will enhance our capacity for innovation in defense-related science and technology and step up the development of advanced logistics and equipment. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加强全民国防教育、国防动员和后备力量建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will strengthen national defense education among the general public, and step up national defense mobilization and readiness of reserve forces. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>促进经济建设和国防建设协调、平衡、兼容发展，深化国防科技工业体制改革，推动军民融合深度发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to promote coordinated, balanced, and compatible development of the economy and national defense, deepen structural reform of defense-related science and technology industries, and intensify military-civilian integration. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各级政府要以更加扎实有力的举措，支持国防和军队改革建设，让军政军民团结之树根深、枝繁、叶茂！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We at every level of government should take more solid and vigorous steps to support the reform and development of our national defense and armed forces. We should see that the tree of unity between the military and the government and between the military and the people continues to grow deep roots and is always in blossom.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要继续全面准确贯彻“一国两制”、“港人治港”、“澳人治澳”、高度自治的方针，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to implement, both to the letter and in spirit, the principle of "one country, two systems," under which the people of Hong Kong govern Hong Kong, the people of Macao govern Macao, and both regions enjoy a high degree of autonomy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>严格依照宪法和基本法办事，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to act in strict compliance with China's Constitution and the basic laws of the Hong Kong and Macao special administrative regions;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>确保“一国两制”在香港、澳门实践不动摇、不走样、不变形。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>and we will ensure that the principle of "one country, two systems" is steadfastly applied in Hong Kong and Macao without being bent or distorted. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>全力支持香港、澳门特别行政区行政长官和政府依法施政，发展经济、改善民生、推进民主、促进和谐。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The chief executives and governments of the two regions have our full support in exercising law-based governance, growing their economies, improving people's wellbeing, advancing democracy, and promoting social harmony. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>“港独”是没有出路的。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>The notion of Hong Kong independence will lead nowhere. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要推动内地与港澳深化合作，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will promote closer cooperation between the mainland and Hong Kong and Macao.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>研究制定粤港澳大湾区城市群发展规划，发挥港澳独特优势，提升在国家经济发展和对外开放中的地位与功能。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will draw up a plan for the development of a city cluster in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, give full play to the distinctive strengths of Hong Kong and Macao, and elevate their positions and roles in China's economic development and opening up. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们对香港、澳门保持长期繁荣稳定始终充满信心。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We have always had full confidence about ensuring lasting prosperity and stability in Hong Kong and Macao.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要深入贯彻对台工作大政方针，坚持一个中国原则，维护“九二共识”共同政治基础，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will thoroughly implement the policies on our work related to Taiwan, uphold the one-China principle, and safeguard the 1992 Consensus as our common political foundation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>维护国家主权和领土完整，维护两岸关系和平发展和台海和平稳定。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will protect China's sovereignty and territorial integrity, maintain the peaceful growth of cross-Straits relations, and safeguard peace and stability in the Taiwan Straits. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>坚决反对和遏制“台独”分裂活动，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will resolutely oppose and deter separatist activities for Taiwan independence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>绝不允许任何人以任何形式、任何名义把台湾从祖国分裂出去。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will never allow any person to separate Taiwan from the motherland in any form or name. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>要持续推进两岸经济社会融合发展，为台湾同胞尤其是青年在大陆学习、就业、创业、生活提供更多便利。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will continue to advance integrated economic and social development between the two sides of the Straits, and make it more convenient for our fellow countrymen and women in Taiwan, particularly young people, to study, work, and live on the mainland. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>两岸同胞要共担民族大义，坚定不移推动祖国和平统一进程，共同创造所有中国人的幸福生活和美好明天。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>People on both sides of the Taiwan Straits should keep in mind the greater interests of the nation, firmly advance peaceful reunification of China, and jointly create better lives and a bright future for all Chinese.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>面对世界政治经济格局的深刻变化，中国将始终站在和平稳定一边，站在公道正义一边，做世界和平的建设者、全球发展的贡献者、国际秩序的维护者。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>In the face of profound changes in the international political and economic landscape, China will always stand on the side of peace and stability, will forever be committed to equity and justice, and will always work for world peace, contribute to global development, and uphold the international order. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们将坚定不移走和平发展道路，坚决维护多边体制的权威性和有效性，反对各种形式的保护主义，深入参与全球治理进程，引导经济全球化朝着更加包容互惠、公正合理的方向发展。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will keep to the path of peaceful development; firmly uphold the authority of the multilateral architecture and see that it works effectively; oppose protectionism in its different forms; become more involved in global governance; and steer economic globalization to see it become more inclusive, mutually beneficial, and equitable. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>推动构筑总体稳定、均衡发展的大国关系框架，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will contribute to a framework that ensures the overall stability and balanced development of relations between major countries.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>着力营造睦邻互信、共同发展的周边环境，全面提升同发展中国家合作水平，积极提供解决全球性和地区热点问题的建设性方案。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will endeavor to foster a neighboring environment that enhances mutual trust and common development between China and its neighbors, upgrade cooperation with all other developing countries in all fields, and offer constructive proposals for addressing global and regional hotspot issues. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>加快完善海外权益保护机制和能力建设。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will intensify efforts to improve our mechanisms and capacity for protecting China's rights and interests overseas. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们愿与国际社会一道，致力构建以合作共赢为核心的新型国际关系，为打造人类命运共同体作出新的贡献。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>China is ready to join hands with the international community and build a new type of international relations based on cooperation and mutual benefit and make new contributions to building a community of shared future for all humankind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>各位代表！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Esteemed Deputies,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>使命重在担当，实干铸就辉煌。</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>A new historical mission awaits us, and with hard work we will achieve great success. </seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>我们要更加紧密地团结在以习近平同志为核心的党中央周围，同心同德，开拓进取，努力完成今年经济社会发展目标任务，</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>We will rally even closer around the Party Central Committee with Comrade Xi Jinping at its core, and work hard with one mind and an enterprising spirit to fulfill this year's economic and social development tasks and targets.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="zh-CN"><seg>为实现“两个一百年”宏伟目标、建设富强民主文明和谐的社会主义现代化国家、实现中华民族伟大复兴的中国梦而不懈奋斗！</seg></tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="en-US"><seg>Let us work with tireless dedication to achieve the two centenary goals (Note: This refers to completing the building of a moderately prosperous society in all respects by the time the Communist Party of China celebrates its centenary in 2021 and turning the People's Republic of China into a modern socialist country that is prosperous, strong, democratic, culturally advanced, and harmonious by the time it celebrates its centenary in 2049), build China into a modern socialist country that is prosperous, strong, democratic, culturally advanced, and harmonious, and realize the Chinese Dream of national rejuvenation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>